[
    {
        "id": "POLITY-1",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "During the framing of the Indian Constitution, the Constituent Assembly held a total of eleven sessions, with sittings spread over for how many days?",
        "options": {
            "A": "180",
            "B": "165",
            "C": "115",
            "D": "132"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "165",
        "explanation": "165. The Constituent Assembly of India began its first session on 9 December 1946 in the Constitution Hall (now Central Hall of Parliament). Over nearly three years, it held 11 sessions, meeting for 165 days, including 114 days focused on discussing the Draft Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-2",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian Constitution has established _________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "partial Judicial system",
            "B": "dual judicial system",
            "C": "independent judicial system",
            "D": "plural judicial system"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "independent judicial system",
        "explanation": "independent judicial system: It means that the other organs of the government like the executive and legislature must not restrain the functioning of the judiciary in such a way that it is unable to do justice."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-3",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following, while praising the amending feature of the Indian Constitution said that ‘This variety in the amending process is wise but is rarely found’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Granville Austin",
            "B": "Ivor Jennings",
            "C": "K C Wheare",
            "D": "HM Seervai"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "K C Wheare",
        "explanation": "K C Wheare was an Australian academic who was an expert on the constitutions of the British Commonwealth. He also described the Indian Constitution as Quasi federal. Granville Austin, a well-known scholar of the Indian Constitution, said, “The amending process has proved itself as one of the most ably conceived aspects of the constitution”. Ivor Jennings said that ‘India is a federation with a strong centralising tendency’."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-4",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a feature of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Universal Adult Franchise",
            "B": "Independent Judiciary",
            "C": "Dual Citizenship",
            "D": "Blend of rigidity & flexibility"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Dual Citizenship",
        "explanation": "Dual Citizenship. India’s commitment to the rule of law is grounded in the Constitution which establishes India as a ‘Sovereign Socialist Secular Democratic Republic’ with a Parliamentary form of Government. Other key features: Federal system of governance between the Union and the States; Separation of powers between the three organs of the Government; free and fair elections; Equality before the law; A secular state that recognizes freedom of conscience and religion."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-5",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are INCORRECT vis-à-vis features of the Indian Constitution? 1) The Constitution empowers the Prime Minister to proclaim three types of emergencies. 2) A reservation policy is there to uplift the disadvantaged sections of society. 3) The Supreme Court has no power of judicial review. 4) The Constitution provides for universal adult suffrage.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 and 3",
            "B": "1 and 2",
            "C": "2 and 4",
            "D": "3 and 4"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1 and 3",
        "explanation": "1 and 3. The Constitution empowers the President to proclaim three types of emergencies. National Emergency (Article 352), President’s Rule (State Emergency) (Article 356), Financial Emergency (Article 360)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-6",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are INCORRECT vis-a-vis features of the Indian Constitution? 1) Though India has a federal system, the Constitution does not mention the word 'federation'. 2) Article 5 of the Constitution says that the Parliament by law can create a new state. 3) On the subjects in the Union list, each State Legislature can enact laws for the State. 4)Both the Parliament and State Legislature can pass laws on subjects in concurrent list.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 and 4",
            "B": "2 and 3",
            "C": "Only 1",
            "D": "1 and 3"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "2 and 3",
        "explanation": "2 and 3. Article 1 of the Indian Constitution defines India, also known as Bharat, as a union of states. Although the term \"federation\" is not explicitly used, India functions as a holding-together type of federation where power distribution among states can be unequal. The Parliament has exclusive authority to legislate on Union List subjects. Article 2 allows for the admission or establishment of new states, while Article 3 provides for the formation of new states and the alteration of existing states' areas, boundaries, or names."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-7",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian Constitution came into force on ___ and is celebrated as Republic Day.",
        "options": {
            "A": "26 Jan 1950",
            "B": "26 Jan 1951",
            "C": "26 Feb 1950",
            "D": "26 Jan 1948"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "26 Jan 1950",
        "explanation": "26 Jan 1950. The Constitution of India was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on 26th November 1949. The Drafting Committee, chaired by Dr. Bhimrao Ambedkar, was established on 29th August 1947. A total of 284 members signed the Constitution, which took 2 years, 11 months, and 18 days to draft."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-8",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Secularism is a feature of the Indian Constitution, which means:",
        "options": {
            "A": "The State does not promote any religion.",
            "B": "The State promotes the religion of the minority community.",
            "C": "The State promotes the religion of the majority community.",
            "D": "The State can promote any religion."
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "The State does not promote any religion.",
        "explanation": "In India, the term 'secularism' was introduced in the year 1976 of the 42nd Amendment of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-9",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did the Indian Constitution declare Hindi in Devanagari script to be the official language of the Union?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1952",
            "B": "1951",
            "C": "1949",
            "D": "1955"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1949",
        "explanation": "1949. Under Article 343(1), the official language of the Union shall be Hindi in Devanagari script, while Section 3 of the Official Language Act, 1963 talks about the continuance of the English language for official purposes of the Union and for use in Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-10",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Preamble of the Constitution describes India as:",
        "options": {
            "A": "an atheist state",
            "B": "a unitary state",
            "C": "a secular state",
            "D": "a federal state"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "a secular state",
        "explanation": "A secular state. It does not consider anyone's religion as an official religion. India is a Sovereign Socialist Secular Democratic Republic with a Parliamentary form of government which www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity is federal in structure with unitary features. Atheist State - No belief in Gods. Unitary State - Central government holds complete authority. Federal State - Central and state governments share autonomy."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-11",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following word sequences is correct as per the Preamble to the Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sovereign, socialist, secular, democratic, republic",
            "B": "Secular, democratic, secular, socialist, sovereign",
            "C": "Sovereign, secular, socialist, democratic, republic",
            "D": "Socialist, secular, democratic, republic, sovereign"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Sovereign, socialist, secular, democratic, republic",
        "explanation": "The words \"Socialist\" and \"Secular\" were added to the Preamble of the Indian Constitution by the 42nd Amendment in 1976. Before this, India was described as a Sovereign, Democratic, Republic, and after the amendment, it was changed to Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic, Republic."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-12",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years was the National Anthem adopted in its Hindi version by the Constituent Assembly ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1947",
            "B": "1950",
            "C": "1954",
            "D": "1942"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1950",
        "explanation": "1950. The National Anthem of India, \"Jana-Gana-Mana,\" was originally composed in Bengali by Rabindranath Tagore and titled \"Bharoto Bhagyo Bidhata.\" It was first publicly sung on December 27, 1911, at the Calcutta (now Kolkata) Session of the Indian National Congress. It was translated into Hindi by Captain Abid Ali and set to music by Captain Ram Singh."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-13",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the ‘The Objective Resolution’ moved by Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "13 December 1946",
            "B": "17 November 1946",
            "C": "15 August 1947",
            "D": "16 November 1948"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "13 December 1946",
        "explanation": "13 December 1946. The Objective Resolution outlines the fundamental ideas and philosophy of our Constitution, defining the goals of the Constituent Assembly. It serves as the basis for the preamble of the Constitution. This important resolution was adopted by the Assembly on January 22, 1947."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-14",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a basic feature of the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Parliamentary system",
            "B": "Blend of rigidity and flexibility",
            "C": "Lengthiest written Constitution",
            "D": "Drawn from one source"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Drawn from one source",
        "explanation": "Drawn from one source. The salient features of the Indian Constitution include: the lengthiest written constitution, drawn from various sources, a blend of rigidity and flexibility, a federal system with a unitary bias, a parliamentary form of government, a synthesis of parliamentary sovereignty and judicial supremacy, rule of law, an integrated and independent judiciary, fundamental rights, directive principles of state policy, fundamental duties, secularism, single citizenship, judicial review, and the basic structure doctrine."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-15",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct in the context of the Indian Constitution? 1.There are three major organs of the government, namely Legislature, Executive and Judiciary. 2. A separation of functions rather than powers is followed. 3.All organs of the government are independent.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 and 3 only",
            "B": "1 and 2 only",
            "C": "2 and 3 only",
            "D": "1, 2 and 3"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1 and 2 only",
        "explanation": "1 and 2 only. In the context of the Indian Constitution: Legislative Function - Parliament (Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha) makes laws, with the President giving assent to bills. Executive Function - The Prime Minister and the Council of Ministers execute laws and are also part of the legislature, linking the two branches. Judicial Function - The judiciary interprets laws and administers justice, reviewing legislative and executive actions for constitutional compliance. This system fosters collaboration and interdependence among branches, with distinct functions but not complete separation of powers."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-16",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who called the preamble of the Indian Constitution 'The Political Horoscope of our Constitution' ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Dr. KM Munshi",
            "B": "Sir Alladi Krishnaswamy Iyer",
            "C": "M. Hidayatullah",
            "D": "Sir Ernest Baker"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Dr. KM Munshi",
        "explanation": "Dr. KM Munshi. He was a member of the Drafting Committee of the Indian Constitution. Other names for the preamble: Soul of the Constitution: By Thakurdas Bhargav. Identity card of the Constitution: By N.A. Palkhiwala. Keynote to the Constitution: By Sir Ernest Barker."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-17",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the preamble to the Indian Constitution amended ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1981",
            "B": "1976",
            "C": "1974",
            "D": "1980"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1976",
        "explanation": "1976. The Preamble of the Constitution was amended only once, in 1976, by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment. The terms 'Socialist', 'Secular', and 'Integrity' were added to the preamble. 'Socialist' and 'Secular' were added between 'Sovereign' and 'Democratic'. 'Unity of the Nation' was changed to 'Unity and Integrity of the Nation'."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-18",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When is Constitution Day observed in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "12 January",
            "B": "26 November",
            "C": "26 January",
            "D": "31 October"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "26 November",
        "explanation": "26 November. The ‘Purna Swaraj’ resolution, meaning total independence, was passed by the Indian National Congress on 19 December 1929, during the Lahore session presided by Jawaharlal Nehru. The pledge for independence was publicly announced on 26 January 1930. Nehru, along with Congress members, marched to the banks of the Ravi, taking an oath not to rest until Purna Swaraj was achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-19",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following is called 'Father of Indian constitution'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "B": "P Subbarayan",
            "C": "Gopinath Bordoloi",
            "D": "Rajendra Prasad"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
        "explanation": "Bhim Rao Ambedkar. He played a pivotal role in drafting the Constitution of India, serving as the Chairman of the Constitution Drafting Committee. Gopinath Bordoloi was the first Chief Minister of Assam. Rajendra Prasad served as the first President of India. Paramasivan Subbarayan was the first Minister of Madras Presidency."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-20",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the designer of India’s national flag?",
        "options": {
            "A": "BN Rau",
            "B": "KM Munshi",
            "C": "Pingali Venkayya",
            "D": "Prem Behari Narain Raizada"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Pingali Venkayya",
        "explanation": "Pingali Venkayya : www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity He presented the original design of the Indian flag with red and green colors to Mahatma Gandhi in 1921. The National Flag was adopted by the Constituent Assembly of India on 22 July 1947."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-21",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following personalities was appointed as the legal advisor of the Constituent Assembly that drafted the document of the Constitution",
        "options": {
            "A": "HVR Iyengar",
            "B": "SN Mukherjee",
            "C": "BR Ambedkar",
            "D": "BN Rau"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "BN Rau",
        "explanation": "BN Rau. On 9 December 1946, the Constituent Assembly of India met for the first time. Temporary President of constituent assembly - Dr. Sachchidananda Sinha. Permanent President - Dr. Rajendra Prasad. Vice - President - H C Mukherjee."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-22",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The original Constitution of India was hand written in English by:",
        "options": {
            "A": "HVR Iyenger",
            "B": "Prem Behari Narayan Raizada",
            "C": "Vasant Krishan Vaidya",
            "D": "SN Mukherjee"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Prem Behari Narayan Raizada",
        "explanation": "Prem Behari Narayan Raizada - The calligrapher of the Indian Constitution. The original constitution was handwritten by him in a flowing italic style. The original Indian Constitution was made up of 117,369 words with 251 pages."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-23",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following personalities was the chief draftsman of the constituent assembly that drafted the document of the Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "KM Munshi",
            "B": "Vasant Krishan Vaidya",
            "C": "SN Mukherjee",
            "D": "HVR Iyenger"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "SN Mukherjee",
        "explanation": "SN Mukherjee. The drafting committee was formed under the chairmanship of Dr B R Ambedkar by the Constituent Assembly on 29th August 1947. The other six members of the committee were K.M. Munshi, Muhammed Sadullah, Alladi Krishnaswamy Iyer, N. Gopalaswami Ayyangar, Devi Prasad Khaitan and BL Mitter."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-24",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following wrote in calligraphic style the Hindi version of the original Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "SN Mukherjee",
            "B": "Prem Behari Narain Raizada",
            "C": "Vasant Krishan Vaidya",
            "D": "Nand Lal Bose"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Vasant Krishan Vaidya",
        "explanation": "Vasant Krishan Vaidya. The original version of the constitution was beautified and decorated by artists from Shantiniketan including Nand Lal Bose and Beohar Rammanohar Sinha."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-25",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The structural part of the Indian Constitution is, to a large extent, derived from the Act of _____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1909",
            "B": "1935",
            "C": "1947",
            "D": "1919"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1935",
        "explanation": "1935. Government of India Act, 1935 provides the establishment of an All India federation consisting of provinces and princely states as units. It divided the powers between the centre and units in terms of three lists- Federal list, provincial list and the concurrent list. Jawaharlal Nehru called it a “machine with strong brakes but no engine”. He also called it a “Charter of Slavery”."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-26",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which is NOT a unitary feature of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Bicameral Legislature",
            "B": "Integrated Judicial System",
            "C": "Single Citizenship",
            "D": "Appointment of the Governor by the President"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Bicameral Legislature",
        "explanation": "Bicameral Legislature. (legislative body with two houses). At the central level (Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha). Other Unitary features of Indian Constitution: Single Constitution for Union and States, Common All-India Services, Inequality of Representation in the Council of States, Centralised Electoral Machinery, Special Powers of Council of State over State List, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-27",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a federal feature of the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Dual Government",
            "B": "Division of Powers",
            "C": "All India Services",
            "D": "Written Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "All India Services",
        "explanation": "All India Services. Federal Features of the Indian Constitution - Division of powers, Supremacy of the constitution, Written constitution, Rigid constitution, Independent Judiciary, Bi-cameral Legislature."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-28",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "With reference to the Constituent Assembly, which of the following statements is Correct ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Constituent Assembly ratified India’s membership of the Commonwealth in May 1947.",
            "B": "The Constituent Assembly adopted the National Anthem in January 1950.",
            "C": "The Constituent Assembly adopted the National Song in January 1948.",
            "D": "The Constituent Assembly adopted the National Flag in July 1949."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The Constituent Assembly adopted the National Anthem in January 1950.",
        "explanation": "The National Anthem of India was adopted by the constituent assembly on 24th January 1950. It was first sung on 27 December 1911 in the Kolkata session of INC. India joined the Commonwealth in May 1949. The Constituent Assembly adopted the Indian National Flag On July 22, 1947 and On January 24, 1950, \"Vande Mataram\" was adopted as the national song."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-29",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many female members were part of the Constituent Assembly that framed the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "12",
            "B": "10",
            "C": "14",
            "D": "15"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "15",
        "explanation": "15. The Constituent Assembly was formed on 6 December 1946. The idea for a Constituent Assembly was proposed in 1934 by M. N. Roy."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-30",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the chairman of the House Committee of the Constituent Assembly of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "B Pattabhi Sitaramayy",
            "B": "AV Thakkar",
            "C": "JB Kripalani",
            "D": "K.M. Munshi"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "B Pattabhi Sitaramayy",
        "explanation": "B Pattabhi Sitaramayya. In 1922, AV Thakkar founded the Bhil Seva Mandal. JB Kripalani was the president of Indian National Congress during Independence. K M Munshi - Founder of Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan (1938), Member of the Constituent Assembly of India, Minister for Agriculture & Food (1952–53)"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-31",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "GV Mavalankar was the Chairman of the ______ of the Constituent Assembly of India.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Advisory Committee on Fundamental Rights, Minorities and Tribal and Excluded Areas",
            "B": "Committee on the Functions",
            "C": "Order of Business Committee",
            "D": "Ad hoc Committee on the National Flag"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Committee on the Functions",
        "explanation": "Committee on the Functions. GV Mavalankar was the first speaker of Lok Sabha. Advisory Committee on Fundamental Rights, Minorities and Tribal and Excluded Areas - Vallabhbhai Patel. Ad hoc Committee on the National Flag - Rajendra Prasad. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-32",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The total membership of the Constituent Assembly was 389, of which ______ were representatives of princely states.",
        "options": {
            "A": "84",
            "B": "102",
            "C": "109",
            "D": "93"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "93",
        "explanation": "93. The total membership of the Constituent Assembly was 389, of which 292 were representatives of the provinces, 93 represented the princely states and 4 were from the chief commissioner provinces of Delhi, Ajmer-Merwara, Coorg and British Baluchistan."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-33",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The members of the Constituent Assembly signed the Constitution of India on ______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "26 November 1948",
            "B": "24 January 1950",
            "C": "26 November 1949",
            "D": "24 January 1952"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "24 January 1950",
        "explanation": "24 January 1950. On that day, the last meeting of the Constituent Assembly was held and the 'Constitution of India' ( with 395 Articles, 8 schedules, 22 parts) was signed and accepted by all."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-34",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did Motilal Nehru (Chairman) and eight other Congress leaders draft a constitution for India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1925",
            "B": "1950",
            "C": "1928",
            "D": "1930"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1928",
        "explanation": "1928. The Motilal Nehru Report 1928 was made by a committee headed by Pt. Motilal Nehru. This committee was created when Lord Birkenhead, Secretary of State of India asked the Indian leaders to draft a constitution for the country. Sources of Indian Constitution"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-35",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which country has the Republic feature of the Indian Constitution been borrowed from?",
        "options": {
            "A": "French Constitution",
            "B": "Irish Constitution",
            "C": "British Constitution",
            "D": "Australian Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "French Constitution",
        "explanation": "French Constitution. Borrowed Features of Indian Constitution: France - Ideals of liberty, equality, and fraternity in Preamble. Australia - Concurrent list, Freedom of trade, commerce, and intercourse, Joint - sitting of Parliament. UK - Parliamentary government, Rule of Law, Legislative procedure, Single Citizenship, Cabinet system, Prerogative writs, Parliamentary privileges, Bicameralism. Ireland - Directive Principles of State Policy, Nomination of members to Rajya Sabha, Method of election of the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-36",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutions inspired the law-making process in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Irish Constitution",
            "B": "British Constitution",
            "C": "US Constitution",
            "D": "Canadian Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "British Constitution",
        "explanation": "British Constitution. Borrowed features of Indian Constitution: British - Parliamentary government, Rule of Law, legislative procedure, single citizenship, cabinet system, prerogative writs. US - Fundamental rights, independence of judiciary, judicial review, impeachment of the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-37",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of ‘Independence of judiciary’ in the Indian Constitution is taken from the Constitution of:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ireland",
            "B": "France",
            "C": "The USA",
            "D": "Britain"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "The USA",
        "explanation": "The USA. Some features of the Indian Constitution borrowed - From USA: Fundamental Rights, President’s impeachment process, Office of the Vice-President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-38",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "From which of the following Constitutions has the India Constitution adopted the system of ‘First Past the Post’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Irish Constitution",
            "B": "French Constitution",
            "C": "United States Constitution",
            "D": "British Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "British Constitution",
        "explanation": "British Constitution. The First Past the Post (FPTP) system, also known as the simple majority system, is used in India for elections to the Lok Sabha and State Legislative Assemblies. Irish Constitution: Ireland uses the Single Transferable Vote (STV) system, a form of proportional representation. French Constitution: France employs a two-round system, where a candidate must win an absolute majority (over 50%) in the first round or a relative majority in the second round."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-39",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Judicial Review, a salient feature of the Constitution of India, has been borrowed from which of the following countries?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The U.S.",
            "B": "Ireland",
            "C": "South Africa",
            "D": "Canada"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "The U.S.",
        "explanation": "The U.S. Borrowed Features of Indian Constitution: US - Impeachment of the president, Functions of president and vice president, Removal of Supreme Court and High court judges."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-40",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian Constitution borrowed the concept of concurrent list from _____.",
        "options": {
            "A": "USSR",
            "B": "Japan",
            "C": "Germany",
            "D": "Australia"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Australia",
        "explanation": "Australia. Borrowed Features of Indian Constitution: Australia - Freedom of trade, commerce and intercourse, Joint-sitting of the two Houses of Parliament. Japan - Concept of Procedure established by law. Germany - Suspension of Fundamental Rights during emergency."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-41",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "From which of the following Constitutions is the idea of ‘Charter of Fundamental Rights’ adopted in the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Brazilian Constitution",
            "B": "Spanish Constitution",
            "C": "United States of America’s Constitution",
            "D": "French Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "United States of America’s Constitution",
        "explanation": "United States of America’s Constitution. Borrowed Features of Indian Constitution: US (United States) - Independence of judiciary, Judicial review, Impeachment of the President, Removal of Supreme Court and High Court judges, Post of vice-president. France - Republic, Ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity in the Preamble."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-42",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "From which country were the ideals of justice of the Indian Constitution borrowed ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The USSR",
            "B": "The UK",
            "C": "The US",
            "D": "Japan"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "The USSR",
        "explanation": "The USSR. Borrowed features of the Constitution : USSR (Now Russia) - Fundamental duties, and The ideals of justice (social, economic, and political), expressed in the Preamble."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-43",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The emergency provisions of the Indian Constitution are borrowed from the Government of India Act,____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1931",
            "B": "1940",
            "C": "1935",
            "D": "1933"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1935",
        "explanation": "1935. The Emergency www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity provisions are enshrined in Part XVIII of the Constitution, from Articles 352 to 360. The Indian Constitution also borrowed various features from the Government of India Act of 1935, including the federal scheme, the office of the governor, the judiciary, and the public service commissions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-44",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "From which country has the concept of Martial Law, which restricts Fundamental rights, borrowed ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "China",
            "B": "The UK",
            "C": "Japan",
            "D": "The USSR"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The UK",
        "explanation": "The UK. The expression ‘martial law’ has not been defined anywhere in the Constitution. It refers to the suspension of ordinary law and the government by military tribunals."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-45",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "India is a parliamentary democracy based on the Westminster model of _________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "the United States of America",
            "B": "South Africa",
            "C": "France",
            "D": "the United Kingdom"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "the United Kingdom",
        "explanation": "The United Kingdom. Countries where the Westminster model is used - Britain, Canada, New Zealand as well as in many parts of Asia and Africa. British - Parliamentary form of government, The idea of single citizenship, The idea of the Rule of law, Writs, Institution of Speaker and his role, Law making procedure, The Political Part of the Indian Constitution, Bicameralism."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-46",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of \"Amendment of the Constitution\" in the Indian Constitution was borrowed from the constitution of which of the following countries?",
        "options": {
            "A": "South Africa",
            "B": "Germany",
            "C": "Canada",
            "D": "Australia"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "South Africa",
        "explanation": "South Africa. Article 368 of Part XX - \"Constitutional Amendment\". Indian Constitution Sources: South Africa - Election of members of Rajya Sabha."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-47",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following provisions of the Indian constitution is borrowed from the Constitution of Canada?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Independence of judiciary",
            "B": "Concept of Republic",
            "C": "Advisory jurisdiction of the Supreme court",
            "D": "Concept of concurrent list"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Advisory jurisdiction of the Supreme court",
        "explanation": "Advisory jurisdiction of the Supreme court. Borrowed Features of Indian Constitution from Canada - Centrifugal form of federalism where the center is stronger than the states, To provide residuary powers to the Centre, Supreme Court’s advisory jurisdiction, and Appointment of state governors by the Centre. Article, Schedule, Parts and list"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-48",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Articles of the Constitution of India provide for a parliamentary form of government at the Centre ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Articles 74 and 75",
            "B": "Articles 71 and 72",
            "C": "Articles 79 and 80",
            "D": "Articles 76 and 77"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Articles 74 and 75",
        "explanation": "Articles 74 and 75. Article 74: Council of Ministers to aid and advise President.-[(1) There shall be a Council of Ministers with the Prime Minister at the head to aid and advise the President who shall, in the exercise of his functions, act in accordance with such advice. Article 75 - Other provisions as to Ministers.-(1) The Prime Minister shall be appointed by the President and the other Ministers shall be appointed by the President on the advice of the Prime Minister."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-49",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following articles of the Constitution of India mentions that every Minister and the Attorney-General of India shall have the right to speak in and participate in the proceedings of either House of Parliament ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 86",
            "B": "Article 87",
            "C": "Article 89",
            "D": "Article 88"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 88",
        "explanation": "Article 88. Ministers and the Attorney - General of India shall not be entitled to vote in either House of the Parliament. Article 86 : Right of President to address and send messages to Houses. Article 87 : Relates to the special address by the President to the Houses of Parliament at the commencement of the first session after each general election."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-50",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution explains that the executive power of every state shall be so exercised as not to impede or prejudice the exercise of the executive power of the Union, and the executive power of the union shall extend to the giving of such directions to a state as may appear to the Government of India to be necessary for that purpose?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 261",
            "B": "Article 247",
            "C": "Article 257",
            "D": "Article 123"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 257",
        "explanation": "Article 257 - Control of the Union over States in certain cases. Article 261 - Public acts, records and judicial proceedings."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-51",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 77 of the Indian Constitution deals with the __________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "term of office of the Vice-President",
            "B": "Vice - President of India",
            "C": "oath of office by the Vice-President",
            "D": "conduct of business of the Government of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "conduct of business of the Government of India",
        "explanation": "The President shall make rules for the more convenient transaction of the business of the Government of India, and for the allocation among Ministers of the said business. Article 67 - Term of office of Vice - President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-52",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution mentions, about the organisation of 'Village Panchayats'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 31",
            "B": "Article 38",
            "C": "Article 36",
            "D": "Article 40"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 40",
        "explanation": "Article 40 : This article directs the state to organise village panchayats and empower them to function as self-governing units. Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSPs): Outlined in Part IV (Articles 36 - 51) of the Constitution, inspired by the Irish Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-53",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India deals with the conduct of business of the Government of a state ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 177",
            "B": "Article 167",
            "C": "Article 164",
            "D": "Article 166"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 166",
        "explanation": "Article 166. Article 164 (1) - The Chief Minister shall be appointed by the Governor and the other Ministers shall be appointed by the Governor on the advice of the Chief Minister, and the Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-54",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution provides that the State must secure a social order to promote the welfare of people?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 37",
            "B": "Article 38",
            "C": "Article 39",
            "D": "Article 36"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 38",
        "explanation": "Article 38. Other Articles: Article 36 : Defines the Directive Principles of State Policy. Article 37: States that DPSPs are not enforceable by courts but are fundamental in governance, and the state is expected to www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity apply them in making laws. Article 39: Outlines specific principles for state policy that promote social and economic welfare, such as equal pay for equal work, protection of children, and equitable distribution of resources."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-55",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which article of the Constitution of India lays down that it shall be the duty of the Advocate-General to give advice to the Government of the State upon legal matters?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 168",
            "B": "Article 165",
            "C": "Article 167",
            "D": "Article 166"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 165",
        "explanation": "Article 165. Other Important Articles: Article 167 - Duties of Chief Minister as respects the furnishing of information to the Governor, etc. Article 168 - Constitution of Legislatures in States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-56",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Articles 245 to 255 in Part XI of the Indian Constitution deal with the _______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "emergency provisions",
            "B": "financial relations between the Centre and the states",
            "C": "legislative relations between the Centre and the states",
            "D": "tribunals"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "legislative relations between the Centre and the states",
        "explanation": "legislative relations between the Centre and the states. Emergency Provisions - Part XVIII, Articles 352 - 360. Tribunals - Part XIV-A Article 323A, and Article 323B. Financial relations between the Centre and the states - Part XII, Articles 268 - 293."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-57",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘The State shall endeavour to promote cottage industries on an individual or co-operative basis in rural areas’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 44",
            "B": "Article 49",
            "C": "Article 43",
            "D": "Article 42"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 43",
        "explanation": "Article 43. Important Articles : Article 42 - Provision for just and humane conditions of work and maternity relief. Article 43A - Participation of workers in management of Industries. Article 43B - Promotion of co-operative societies."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-58",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Constitution deals with the Panchayats ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part IV",
            "B": "Part IX",
            "C": "Part VII",
            "D": "Part X"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Part IX",
        "explanation": "Part IX. The Panchayats (Articles 243-243O): This part was inserted by the 73rd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1992, and came into effect on April 24, 1993. Part IV: Directive Principles of State Policy. Part VII: States in the First Schedule (now repealed). Part X: The Scheduled and Tribal Areas."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-59",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Articles 52 to 78 in Part V of the Indian Constitution deal with __________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Finance Commission of India",
            "B": "Union Executive",
            "C": "Amendment of the Constitution",
            "D": "National emergency"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Union Executive",
        "explanation": "Union Executive. Important Articles: Article 52 - President of India. Article 53 - Executive power of the Union. Article 54 - Election of President. Article 63 - The Vice-President of India. Article 64 - The Vice-President to be the ex-officio Chairman of the Rajya Sabha. Article 72 - Power of President to grant pardons. Article 74 - Council of Ministers to aid and advise the President. Article 76 - Attorney-General for India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-60",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following articles of the Indian constitution deals with the parliament and its proceedings?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 51A",
            "B": "Article 36 to 51",
            "C": "Article 79 to 122",
            "D": "Article 12 to 35"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 79 to 122",
        "explanation": "Article 79 to 122. These articles in Part V of the Indian Constitution deal with the provisions related to the Parliament of India, including its organisation, composition, duration, officers, procedures, privileges, powers, and other related aspects."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-61",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution provides for protecting and improving the environment and safeguarding forests and wildlife?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 47-A",
            "B": "Article 47-B",
            "C": "Article 48-A",
            "D": "Article 49-C"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 48-A",
        "explanation": "Article 48-A, which is part of the Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSP) in the Indian Constitution, was added by the 42nd Amendment in 1976. The DPSP are guidelines in the Indian Constitution designed to establish a welfare state in India. They are borrowed from the Irish Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-62",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘The State shall, in particular, direct its policy towards securing that the ownership and control of the material resources of the community are so distributed as best to subserve the common good’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 39(a)",
            "B": "Article 39(b)",
            "C": "Article 39(c)",
            "D": "Article 39(d)"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 39(b)",
        "explanation": "Article 39(b). This article is part of the Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSP), which outlines the guiding principles for the state to follow while making policies. Article 39(a): Ensures citizens have equal rights to an adequate means of livelihood. Article 39(c): Prevents concentration of wealth and means of production. Article 39(d): Advocates for equal pay for equal work for men and women."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-63",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles and Parts of the Indian Constitution deal with the State Legislature ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Articles 214 to 231 in Part VI",
            "B": "Articles 168 to 212 in Part VI",
            "C": "Articles 243 to 243-O in Part IX",
            "D": "Articles 79 to 122 in Part V"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Articles 168 to 212 in Part VI",
        "explanation": "Articles 168 to 212 in Part VI. Other Articles : Articles 214 to 231 of the Indian Constitution cover the organisation, powers, and functions of the High Courts in India. Articles 243 to 243-O in Part IX pertain to Panchayats. Articles 79 to 122 in Part V focus on the Parliament of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-64",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the 'Promotion of educational and economic interests of Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and other weaker sections' ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 45",
            "B": "Article 48",
            "C": "Article 47",
            "D": "Article 46"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 46",
        "explanation": "Article 46. Article 45 directs the state to ensure early childhood care and education for children under the age of six. Article 48 provides guiding principles for organizing agriculture and animal husbandry in India. Article 47 outlines the state's duty to improve the standard of living and nutrition for its citizens."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-65",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution mentions that \"the Parliament consists of the President and two Houses known as the Council of States (Rajya Sabha) and the House of the People (Lok Sabha)\" ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "79",
            "B": "82",
            "C": "73",
            "D": "70"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "79",
        "explanation": "79. Parliament is India’s top legislative body, with its structure and functions defined as follows: Article 80: www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Composition of the Council of States. Article 81: Composition of the House of the People. Article 82: Readjustment after each census. Article 70 : President’s functions in contingencies. Article 73: Extent of Union's executive power."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-66",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In a situation wherein A (female) and B (male) are working in the same office, same designation, same nature of work but unequal payment, which of the following Articles of the Constitution be applicable?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 48A",
            "B": "Article 39",
            "C": "Article 21",
            "D": "(c) Article 21 (d) Article 18"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 39",
        "explanation": "Article 39(d) of the Constitution proclaims \"equal pay for equal work for both men and women\" as a Directive Principle of State Policy (DPSP). Article 21: Guarantees the fundamental right to protection of life and personal liberty. Article 18: Abolition of titles."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-67",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Articles of the Constitution deal with citizenship ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Articles 5 to 11",
            "B": "Articles 5 to 8",
            "C": "Articles 5 to 10",
            "D": "Articles 5 to 9"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Articles 5 to 11",
        "explanation": "Articles 5 to 11. Part II of the Constitution of India deals with Citizenship: Article 5 - Citizenship at the commencement of the Constitution. Article 6 - Rights of citizenship of certain persons who have migrated to India from Pakistan. Article 7 - Rights of citizenship of certain migrants to Pakistan. Article 8 - Rights of citizenship of certain persons of Indian origin residing outside India. Article 9 - Persons voluntarily acquiring citizenship of a foreign State not to be citizens. Article 10 - Continuance of citizenship rights. Article 11- Parliament to regulate the right of citizenship by law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-68",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under the discretionary power of which Article of the Indian Constitution did the SC of India recognise sex work as a profession ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 140",
            "B": "Article 142",
            "C": "Article 141",
            "D": "Article 143"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 142",
        "explanation": "Article 142. Other Articles: Article 140 - Ancillary powers of the Supreme Court. Article 141 - Law declared by the Supreme Court is binding on all courts. Article 143. Power of the President to consult the Supreme Court. Article 144 - Civil and judicial authorities must act in aid of the Supreme Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-69",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles in the Constitution of India provides protection to the President and Governors and Rajpramukhs ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 352",
            "B": "Article 356",
            "C": "Article 361",
            "D": "Article 370"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 361",
        "explanation": "Article 361. Other Articles: Article 352: Deals with the proclamation of Emergency due to war, external aggression, or internal disturbance. Article 356: Relates to the President's rule in a state, where the President takes over the governance of a state due to failure of the constitutional machinery. Article 370: Provided special status to the state of Jammu and Kashmir, which was repealed in 2019."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-70",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article provides that all minorities have the right to establish and administer educational institutions of their choice ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 26",
            "B": "Article 24",
            "C": "Article 32",
            "D": "Article 30"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 30",
        "explanation": "Article 30. Other important articles: Article 26 - It gives freedom to manage religious affairs. Article 24 - It prohibits the employment of children below the age of 14 years in any factory, mine, or hazardous occupation. Article 32 - It grants every individual the right to move the Supreme Court for the enforcement of their fundamental rights."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-71",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many languages are included in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution of India as scheduled languages?",
        "options": {
            "A": "22",
            "B": "24",
            "C": "23 d) 21",
            "D": ""
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "22",
        "explanation": "22. Part XVII of the Indian constitution deals with the official languages in Articles 343 to 351. Initially 14 were included in the Constitution. Sindhi language was added by the 21st Amendment Act of 1967. Konkani, Manipuri and Nepali were included by the 71st Amendment Act of 1992. Subsequently Bodo, Dogri, Maithili and Santhali were added by the 92nd Amendment Act of 2003."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-72",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 15 of the Constitution of India entails:",
        "options": {
            "A": "equality of opportunity for all citizens in matters relating to employment or appointment",
            "B": "prohibition of discrimination against any citizen on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth",
            "C": "cultural and educational rights",
            "D": "freedom of speech and expression"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "prohibition of discrimination against any citizen on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth",
        "explanation": "Other important articles: Article 16 - Equality of opportunity for all citizens in matters relating to employment or appointment. Articles 29 - The cultural and educational rights of minorities. Article 30 - The right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions of their choice. Article 19(1)(a) - Freedom of speech and expression."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-73",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution are related to Fundamental Rights ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "12-36",
            "B": "32-51",
            "C": "12-35",
            "D": "14-32"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "12-35",
        "explanation": "12-35. Fundamental Rights: Right to equality (Articles 14-18), Right to freedom (Articles 19-22), Right against exploitation (Articles 23-24), Right to freedom of religion (Articles 25-28), Cultural and educational rights (Articles 29-30), Right to constitutional remedies (Article 32). The Right to property was removed from the list of fundamental rights by the 44th Amendment Act, 1978 and it was made a legal right under Article 300-A in Part XII of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-74",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "'Reservation in promotion' comes under which Article of the Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 19 (2)",
            "B": "Article 14 (4A)",
            "C": "Article 16 (4A)",
            "D": "Article 15 (3B)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 16 (4A)",
        "explanation": "Article 16 (4A). Article 16(4) allows the state to provide reservations for appointments or posts for any backward class of citizens that is not adequately represented in state services. Article 16: Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment. The 77th Amendment Act introduced clause (4A) to Article 16, which specifically permits reservations in promotions for Scheduled Castes (SC) and Scheduled Tribes (ST) if they are underrepresented in the services."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-75",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Articles 344 (1) and 351 of the Constitution of India are related to the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Eighth Schedule",
            "B": "Third Schedule",
            "C": "Sixth Schedule",
            "D": "Fifth Schedule"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Eighth Schedule",
        "explanation": "Eighth Schedule. Article 344(1) provides for the constitution of a Commission by the President on expiration of five years. Article 351 - It provides for the spread of the Hindi language to develop it. The Eighth Schedule recognizes 22 official www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity languages. Schedule and subject: Third Schedule - Oaths or affirmations."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-76",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which Article does the Finance Commission of India find a mention ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 292",
            "B": "Article 375",
            "C": "Article 280",
            "D": "Article 370"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 280",
        "explanation": "Article 280. The Finance Commission is a constitutional body, it is constituted by the President of India every five years. The Commission consists of five members, including a chairperson. Article 292: Borrowing by the Government of India. Article 375: Courts, authorities and officers continue to function subject to the provisions of the Constitution. Article 370: Temporary provisions with respect to the State of Jammu and Kashmir."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-77",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per Article ____________ of the Indian Constitution, the Council of Ministers are collectively responsible to the Lok Sabha.",
        "options": {
            "A": "74(1)",
            "B": "72(1)",
            "C": "73(2)",
            "D": "75(3)"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "75(3)",
        "explanation": "75(3). Article 75 (1) - The Prime Minister shall be appointed by the President and the other Ministers shall be appointed by the President on the advice of the Prime Minister. Article 75(2) - The Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-78",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Biological Diversity Act 2002 was passed by the Government of India. It fulfilled ideals of which article of Directive Principles of State Policy in the Constitution of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 49",
            "B": "Article 48A",
            "C": "Article 48",
            "D": "Article 47"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 48A",
        "explanation": "Article 48A outlines the directive principle for environmental protection and safeguarding forests and wildlife. It was added through the 42nd Constitutional Amendment, 1976. The Biological Diversity Act, 2002, was enacted to fulfill India's obligations under the Convention on Biological Diversity. It established the National Biodiversity Authority (NBA), State Biodiversity Boards (SBB), and local Biodiversity Management Committees (BMC) to regulate access to biological resources and ensure equitable benefit-sharing."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-79",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the right of the Governor to address and to send messages to the House (or Houses) of the state legislature ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 171",
            "B": "Article 175",
            "C": "Article 172",
            "D": "Article 176"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 175",
        "explanation": "Article 175. Other Articles: Article 171 - Composition of the Legislative Councils. Article 172 - Duration of State Legislatures. Article 173 - Qualification for membership of the State Legislature. Article 174 - Sessions of the State Legislature, prorogation and dissolution. Article 176 - Special address by the Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-80",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following parts of the Indian Constitution is commonly referred to as the ‘Magna Carta of India’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part III",
            "B": "Part I",
            "C": "Part IV",
            "D": "Part II"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Part III",
        "explanation": "Part III - Fundamental Rights (Article 12 to 35). ‘Magna Carta’ is the Charter of Rights issued by King John of England in 1215 under pressure from the barons."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-81",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the salaries and allowances of the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of the Rajya Sabha and the Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 92",
            "B": "Article 97",
            "C": "Article 94",
            "D": "Article 95"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 97",
        "explanation": "Article 97. Other important Articles: Article 92 - The Chairman or the Deputy Chairman not to preside while a resolution for his removal from office is under consideration. Article 94 - Vacation and resignation of, and removal from, the offices of Speaker and Deputy Speaker. Article 95 - Power of the Deputy Speaker or other person to perform the duties of the office of, or to act as, Speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-82",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution mentions that the Vice - President of India shall be the ex officio Chairman of the Council of States?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 89",
            "B": "Article 90",
            "C": "Article 91",
            "D": "Article 92"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 89",
        "explanation": "Article 89. Article 64 and Article 89(1) state that the Vice President of India shall serve as the ex officio Chairman of the Council of States (Rajya Sabha). Other related articles include: Article 90 - Specifies the conditions for the vacation, resignation, and removal of the Deputy Chairman of the Council of States. Article 91- Grants the Deputy Chairman or another designated person the power to perform the duties of the Chairman in their absence."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-83",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the right of the Advocate - General of a state to speak in the State Legislature ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 183",
            "B": "Article 179",
            "C": "Article 177",
            "D": "Article 181"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 177",
        "explanation": "Article 177. Article 183 of the Indian Constitution addresses the resignation, vacation, and removal of the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council. Article 181 stipulates that neither the Speaker nor the Deputy Speaker should preside over the proceedings when their removal process is underway. These provisions ensure impartiality during key legislative processes."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-84",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to the Legislative Assembly of the state’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 164(3)",
            "B": "Article 164(1)",
            "C": "Article 164(2)",
            "D": "Article 164(4)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 164(2)",
        "explanation": "Article 164(2). Article 164(1) - The Chief Minister is appointed by the Governor, while other Ministers are appointed on the Chief Minister's advice, and they hold office at the Governor's pleasure. Article 164(3) - Before assuming office, a Minister must take the oaths of office and secrecy administered by the Governor, as specified in the Third Schedule. Article 164(4) - A Minister who is not a member of the State Legislature for six consecutive months will cease to hold office at the end of that period."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-85",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article specifies the procedure for amending the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 365",
            "B": "Article 366",
            "C": "Article 368",
            "D": "Article 367"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 368",
        "explanation": "Article 368 (Part XX) Parliament may amend the Constitution by way of addition, variation or repeal of any provision in accordance with the procedure laid down for the purpose. However, the Parliament cannot amend those provisions which form the ‘basic structure’ of the Constitution. This was ruled by the Supreme Court in the Kesavananda Bharati case (1973)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-86",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the salaries www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity and allowances of members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council of a state?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 195",
            "B": "Article 199",
            "C": "Article 198",
            "D": "Article 194"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 195",
        "explanation": "Article 195. Important Articles in Part VI (The States): Article 168 - Constitution of Legislatures in States. Article 169 - Abolition or creation of Legislative Councils in States. Article 170 - Composition of the Legislative Assemblies. Article 194 - Powers, privileges, etc., of the Houses of Legislatures and of the members and committees thereof. Article 199 - Definition of “Money Bills”."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-87",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that a person may be appointed as the Governor of two or more states?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 153",
            "B": "Article 152",
            "C": "Article 151",
            "D": "Article 150"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 153",
        "explanation": "Article 153. The Seventh Amendment Act, 1956, amended Article 153 to allow a governor to oversee two or more states. Other important articles : Article 150 - Form of Accounts of The Union and of The States. Article 151 - The audit reports of the Union and State by the Comptroller and Auditor General of India. Article 152 - States about the Definition of state."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-88",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution states that “There shall be a High Court for each state” ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 275",
            "B": "Article 245",
            "C": "Article 214",
            "D": "Article 125"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 214",
        "explanation": "Article 214. Other important Articles: Article 215 - Every High Court shall be a court of record and shall have all the powers of such a court including the power to punish for contempt of itself. Article 217 - Appointment and conditions of the office of a Judge of a High Court. Article 245 - Parliament may make laws for the whole or any part of the territory of India. Article 275 - provides for the grants from the Union to certain States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-89",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘All the executive action of the Government of a state shall be expressed to be taken in the name of the Governor’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 163(1)",
            "B": "Article 165(1)",
            "C": "Article 166(1)",
            "D": "Article 164(1)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 166(1)",
        "explanation": "Article 166(1). Other important Articles: Article 163(1) - There shall be a Council of Ministers with the Chief Minister at the head to aid and advise the Governor in the exercise of his functions. Article 164(1) - The Chief Minister shall be appointed by the Governor and the other Ministers shall be appointed by the Governor on the advice of the Chief Minister. Article 165(1) - The Governor of each State shall appoint a person who is qualified to be appointed a Judge of a High Court to be Advocate-General for the State."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-90",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions the qualification for membership of the State Legislature?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 171",
            "B": "Article 180",
            "C": "Article 173",
            "D": "Article 179"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 173",
        "explanation": "Article 173. The person must be at least 25 years old for a seat in the Legislative Assembly and at least 30 years old for a seat in the Legislative Council. Other important Articles : Article 171 - The total number of members in the Legislative Council of a State shall not exceed one-third of the total number of members in the Legislative Assembly of that State. Article 179 - Vacation and resignation of, and removal from, the offices of Speaker and Deputy Speaker. Article 180 - Power of the Deputy Speaker to perform the duties of Speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-91",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What Article of the Indian Constitution provides that the State Governor has the authority to reserve a bill for the consideration of the President",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 181",
            "B": "Article 200",
            "C": "Article 190",
            "D": "Article 267"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 200",
        "explanation": "Article 200. The Governor may also return the Bill with a message requesting reconsideration by the House or Houses. Article 201 - It states that when a Bill is reserved for the consideration of the President, the President may assent to or withhold assent from the Bill. Article 190 - A person cannot be a member of both houses of a state legislature. Article 181 - The Speaker or the Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution for his removal from office is under consideration. Article 267 - Contingency Fund."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-92",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution deals with the annual financial statement of the Government of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 120",
            "B": "Article 116",
            "C": "Article 112",
            "D": "Article 110"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 112",
        "explanation": "Article 112 - The President shall cause, in respect of each financial year, to be laid before each House of Parliament a statement of the estimated receipts and expenditure of the Government of India for that year, which is in this Part referred to as \"the annual financial Statement\". Other important Articles: Article 110 - Definition of \"Money Bills\". Article 116 - Votes on account, votes of credit and exceptional grants. Article 120 - Language to be used in Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-93",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "________ of the Indian Constitution sets qualifications for being a member of Lok Sabha.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 74",
            "B": "Article 84",
            "C": "Article 64",
            "D": "Article 76"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 84",
        "explanation": "Article 84 outlines the qualifications for being a member of the Lok Sabha. A person must: Be an Indian citizen; Take an oath or affirmation before an authorized person appointed by the Election Commission; Be at least 25 years old; Meet any other qualifications set by the Parliament of India. Article 74 : Council of Ministers to aid and advise the President. Article 64 : The Vice-President to be ex-officio Chairman of the Council of States (Rajya Sabha). Article 76 : It is to the appointment and responsibilities of the Attorney-General for India. Q. 94. Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution are related to the Comptroller and Auditor General of India? Higher Secondary 25/06/2024 (Shift - 2) (a) Article 147-150 (b) Article 148-154 (c) Article 148-152 (d) Article 148-151 Sol.94.(d) Article 148-151. The CAG handles the audit of the accounts of the Union and State governments. Article 148: Establishes the office of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India. Article 149: Duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor-General. Article 150: Form of accounts of the Union and of the States. Article 151: Mandates the presentation of audit reports by the Comptroller and Auditor General to the President of India, which are then laid before Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-94",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution makes it clear that Directive Principles of State Policy are www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity fundamental in the governance of the country and it shall be the duty of the state to apply these principles in making laws?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 46",
            "B": "Article 37",
            "C": "Article 44",
            "D": "Article 40"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 37",
        "explanation": "Article 37. Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSP) in Part IV of the Indian Constitution are based on the Irish Constitution, which in turn was based on the Spanish Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-95",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT come under the Concurrent List?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Artificial Habitats",
            "B": "Medical Education",
            "C": "Protection of Wildlife",
            "D": "Population Control"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Artificial Habitats",
        "explanation": "Artificial Habitats. The Parliament and state legislatures can both make laws on matters listed under the Concurrent List. As of now, the list includes 52 subjects (originally 47). Some Subjects in Concurrent list: Bankruptcy and insolvency, Forests, Factories, Boilers, Electricity, Newspapers, books and printing presses."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-96",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In respect of Arunachal Pradesh, the Governor has special responsibility under ________ of the Constitution of India with respect to law and order and in discharge of his functions in relation thereto.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 359 A",
            "B": "Article 380 A",
            "C": "Article 371 H",
            "D": "Article 361 H"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 371 H",
        "explanation": "Article 371 H. Under Article 359, during a national emergency, the President can suspend the right to move courts for Fundamental Rights enforcement, except for Articles 20 and 21. Article 380, which once addressed the President of India, was omitted by the Constitution (Forty-second Amendment) Act of 1976. Article 361 provides protection to the President, Governors, and Rajpramukhs from being held accountable in courts for actions taken while performing their duties."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-97",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Schedule of the Indian Constitution is the form of oath or affirmation for a Judge of the Supreme Court mentioned?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Fourth Schedule",
            "B": "Second Schedule",
            "C": "First Schedule",
            "D": "Third Schedule"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Third Schedule",
        "explanation": "Third Schedule. The Third Schedule of the Indian Constitution outlines the forms of oaths and affirmations for various constitutional offices : President, Vice-President, Union and State Ministers, Parliament and state legislature candidates, Judges, Comptroller and Auditor General. First Schedule : Names of the States and Union Territories, Second Schedule : Provisions for the emoluments, allowances, privileges of certain constitutional authorities, and Fourth Schedule : Allocation of seats in the Rajya Sabha and union territories."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-98",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘In the performance of his/her duties, the Attorney - General for India shall have the right of audience in all the courts in the territory of India’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 76(1)",
            "B": "Article 76(3)",
            "C": "Article 76(4)",
            "D": "Article 76(2)"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 76(3)",
        "explanation": "Article 76(3). Article 76 of the Indian Constitution addresses the Attorney General of India. Under Article 76(1), the President of India appoints the Attorney General. Article 76(2) states that it is the duty of the Attorney General to provide legal advice to the Government of India and perform other legal duties. Article 76(4) specifies that the Attorney General holds office at the pleasure of the President and receives remuneration as determined by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-99",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Match the following subject matters with their concerned Articles. a b 1. Superintendence, direction and control of elections to be Vested in an Election commission. A) Article 329 2. Power of parliament to make provision with respect to election to legislature. B) Article 324 3. Bar of interference by courts in electoral matters C) Article 327",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 - C, 2 - B, 3 - A",
            "B": "1 - A, 2 - C, 3 - B",
            "C": "1 - A, 2 - B, 3 - C",
            "D": "1 - B, 2 - C, 3 - A"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1 - B, 2 - C, 3 - A",
        "explanation": "1-B, 2-C, 3-A. Article 325 - No person to be ineligible for inclusion in, or to claim to be included in a special, electoral roll on grounds of religion, race, caste or sex. Article 328 - Power of Legislature of a State to make provision with respect to elections to such Legislature."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-100",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India mentions that “there shall be a Public Service Commission for the Union and a Public Service Commission for each State” ? SSC Stenographer 13/10/2023 (Morning)",
        "options": {
            "A": "315 (4)",
            "B": "315 (1)",
            "C": "315 (3)",
            "D": "315 (2)"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "315 (1)",
        "explanation": "Article 315 (1). Article 315 (2) - Two or more States may agree that there shall be one Public Service Commission for that group of States. Article 315 (3) - Any such law as aforesaid may contain such incidental and consequential provisions as may be necessary or desirable for giving effect to the purposes of the law. Article 315 (4) - UPSC can, if requested by a state government, conduct examinations and interviews to select candidates for state government jobs."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-101",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India provides that the Governor appoints the Chief Minister and later, the Chief Minister recommends the appointment of ministers to the Governor?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 163",
            "B": "Article 165",
            "C": "Article 164",
            "D": "Article 167"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 164",
        "explanation": "Article 164. Other Appointments by Governor: State Election Commissioner (Article 243 K), Vice-Chancellors of the universities in the state (University Grants Commission (UGC) Regulations, 2018), Advocate General for the State (Article 165) etc. Article 163 - Council of Ministers to aid and advise the Governor of the State."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-102",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution empowers the Parliament to restrict or abrogate the fundamental rights of the members of the armed forces, paramilitary forces, police forces, intelligence agencies and analogous forces ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 33",
            "B": "Article 31",
            "C": "Article 37",
            "D": "Article 35"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 33",
        "explanation": "Article 33. Fundamental rights are included in Part III (Article 12-35) of the Constitution. It is described as the Magna Carta of India. Article 35 - Power to make laws to give effect to certain specified fundamental rights shall vest only in the Parliament and not in the state legislatures."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-103",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per Article 361 of the Constitution of India, who among the following shall NOT be answerable to any court for the exercise and performance www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity of the powers and duties of his/her office?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Secretary",
            "B": "Chief Minister",
            "C": "Prime Minister",
            "D": "Governor"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. Article 361 - The President, or the Governor or Rajpramukh of a State, shall not be answerable to any court for the exercise and performance of the powers and duties of his office or for any act done or purporting to be done by him in the exercise and performance."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-104",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which schedule of the Constitution of India contains provisions for disqualification of legislators on the ground of defection?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Schedule - X",
            "B": "Schedule - XI",
            "C": "Schedule - VIII",
            "D": "Schedule - IX"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Schedule - X",
        "explanation": "Schedule-X: Popularly known as the Anti-Defection Act, was included in the Constitution via the 52nd Amendment Act, 1985. Schedule-IX (laws that are immune from judicial review) - It was added by the First Amendment Act, 1951."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-105",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that all the authorities— civil and judicial— in the territory of India shall act in aid of the Supreme Court ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 143",
            "B": "Article 141",
            "C": "Article 144",
            "D": "Article 142"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 144",
        "explanation": "Article 144. Article 142: Enforcement of decrees and orders of the Supreme Court and orders as to discovery, etc. Article 141: The law declared by the Supreme Court shall be binding on all courts within the territory of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-106",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 149 of the Constitution deals with ___________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "the qualifications required for the appointment of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India",
            "B": "the duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India",
            "C": "the term of office of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India",
            "D": "the appointment of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "the duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India",
        "explanation": "Part V (Chapter V) of the Indian Constitution (Articles 148-151) deals with the Comptroller and Auditor-General (CAG). Article 148: This article deals with the appointment, oath, tenure and removal of CAG of India. There are no specific qualifications required to become the CAG of India. The President of India appoints the CAG through a warrant under their hand and seal. The CAG serves a term of 6 years or until the age of 65, whichever comes first."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-107",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct about Article 129 of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It provides for the Supreme Court to give advisory opinions to the President.",
            "B": "It provides for the Supreme Court to be a court of original jurisdiction",
            "C": "It provides for the Supreme Court to be a court of record.",
            "D": "It provides for the Supreme Court to be the highest court of appeal."
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "It provides for the Supreme Court to be a court of record.",
        "explanation": "Article 143 - Power of the President to consult the Supreme Court. Article 132 - Appellate jurisdiction of the Supreme Court in appeals from High Courts in certain cases. Articles 133 and 134 grant the Supreme Court appellate jurisdiction in civil and criminal matters from High Courts."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-108",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many schedules are there in our Constitution as of June 2023?",
        "options": {
            "A": "8",
            "B": "9",
            "C": "12",
            "D": "10"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "12",
        "explanation": "12 Schedules in Indian Constitution: First - List of States and UT; Second - Emoluments, allowances, and privileges; Third - Oath and affirmation ; Fourth - Seat allocation of the Rajya Sabha; Fifth - Administration of Scheduled Areas and Scheduled Tribes; Sixth - Administration of Tribal Areas in the States of Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram; Seventh - Union list, State list and the concurrent list; Eight - List of recognized languages; Ninth - Land reforms and regulations; Tenth - Anti defection law; Eleventh - Panchayati Raj and Twelfth - Municipalities."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-109",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Clause of Article 19 of the Indian Constitution guarantees the 'right to move freely throughout the territory of India' ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Clause",
            "B": "(b) Clause",
            "C": "(c) Clause",
            "D": "(d) Clause (a)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "(c) Clause",
        "explanation": "Clause (d). Article 19 - Protection of certain rights regarding freedom of speech, etc. Other clauses of Article 19(1): Clause (a) grants the freedom of speech and expression; Clause (b) grants the right to assemble peaceably and without arms; Clause (c) grants the right to form associations, unions, or co-operative societies; Clause (d) grants the right to move freely throughout the territory of India; Clause (e) grants the right to reside and settle in any part of the territory of India; Clause (g) grants the right to practise any profession or to carry on any occupation, trade, or business."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-110",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Articles of the Constitution of India deal with the Union and its territory ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Articles 5-11",
            "B": "Articles 1-4",
            "C": "Articles 12-35",
            "D": "Article 36-51"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Articles 1-4",
        "explanation": "Articles 1-4. Article 1- Name and territory of the Union; Article 2 - Admission or Establishment of New States; Article 3 - Formation of New States and alteration of areas, Boundaries or Names of existing States; Article 4 : Laws made under articles 2 and 3 to provide for the amendment of the first and the fourth schedules and supplemental, incidental and consequential matters."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-111",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In India which of the following is a Gandhian principle of Directive Principles of State Policy ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To Separate judiciary from executive",
            "B": "To organise village panchayat",
            "C": "To secure uniform civil code",
            "D": "To provide equal pay for equal work"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "To organise village panchayat",
        "explanation": "To organise village panchayat. Article based on Gandhian principles: 40 - Organise village panchayats. 43 - Living wage, etc., for workers. 43B - To promote voluntary formation, autonomous functioning, democratic control of cooperative societies. 46 - promote educational and economic interests of the weaker sections. 47 - To improve public health. 48 - To prohibit the slaughter of cows, calves and other milch. Other Groups - Socialist Principle - Article (38, 39, 41, 42, 43, 43A, 47). Liberal - Intellectual Principle - Article (44, 45, 48, 48A, 49, 50, 51)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-112",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles says that double jeopardy which says that “no person shall be prosecuted or punished for the same offence more than once?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 21 (2)",
            "B": "Article 19 (1)",
            "C": "Article 20 (2)",
            "D": "Article 22 (2) www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 20 (2)",
        "explanation": "Article 20 (2). Article 21 - Protection of life and personal liberty. Article 19 (1) - The right to freedom of speech and expression. Article 22 - Protection Against Arrest and Detention in Certain Cases. Article 22(2) - A person who is arrested and detained must be produced before a magistrate within 24 hours."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-113",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Article of the Directive Principles of State Policy, a working woman on maternity leave, must receive all maternity benefits from the employer?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 42",
            "B": "Article 44",
            "C": "Article 45",
            "D": "Article 43"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 42",
        "explanation": "Article 42. Directive Principles of State Policies are non-justiciable rights (which means that they cannot be enforced by a Court of Law). Article 43 - The State shall endeavour to secure all workers a living wage and a decent standard of life. Article 44 - Uniform civil code for the citizens."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-114",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "'The state shall endeavour to secure to all workers a living wage and a decent standard of life'. Which of the following is correct about the given statement in the context of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is mentioned in the 43rd Article of the Constitution.",
            "B": "It is mentioned in the 44th Article of Constitution.",
            "C": "This is a Gandhian principle of Directive Principles of State Policy.",
            "D": "This is a liberal principle of Directive Principles of State Policy."
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "It is mentioned in the 43rd Article of the Constitution.",
        "explanation": "Article 43 (Living wage, etc., for workers). Directives based on Liberal-Intellectual Principles: Article 44, Article 45, Article 48, Article 48A, Article 49, Article 50, Article 51."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-115",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following articles is related to the provision of Co-operative Societies in the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "243 ZG to 243 ZJ",
            "B": "243 P to 243 ZG",
            "C": "243 ZH to 243 ZT",
            "D": "243 A to 243"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "243 ZH to 243 ZT",
        "explanation": "243 ZH to 243 ZT. Co - operative Societies - A form of business organisation that is formed with the objective of helping the society members. Under 97th Amendment Act 2011, the right to form cooperative societies was included as Right to Freedom {Article 19(1)(c)}. Promotion of Cooperation societies was inserted as one of the DPSPs (Article 43-B)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-116",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The government is bound to ensure observance of social welfare and labour laws enacted to secure for workmen a life compatible with human dignity, under _____ of the Indian Constitution.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 17",
            "B": "Article 15",
            "C": "Article 19",
            "D": "Article 21"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 21",
        "explanation": "Article 21. Article 15 - Prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth. Article 19: Protection of certain rights regarding freedom of Speech, etc. Article 17 - Abolition of Untouchability."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-117",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In the Indian Constitution which of the following Articles deals with the right to move to the Supreme Court for enforcement of Fundamental rights ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 30",
            "B": "Article 32",
            "C": "Article 33",
            "D": "Article 31"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 32",
        "explanation": "Article 32 (Right to Constitutional Remedies) - The ‘Heart and Soul of the Constitution’ by Dr. B.R. Ambedkar. Article 30 - Right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-118",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Poshan Abhiyaan is a programme to achieve nutritional status of children from 0 to 6 years. Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution provides for raising the nutrition level?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 47",
            "B": "Article 44",
            "C": "Article 46",
            "D": "Article 45"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 47",
        "explanation": "Article 47 - Duty of the State to raise the level of nutrition and the standard of living and to improve public health comes under Directive Principles of State Policy (Articles 36-51 under Part-IV)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-119",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution has the idea that 'No child below the age of fourteen years shall be employed to work in any factory or mine or engaged in any other hazardous employment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 22",
            "B": "Article 24",
            "C": "Article 19",
            "D": "Article 20"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 24",
        "explanation": "Article 24. Article 22 - Protection against arrest and detention in certain cases. Article 19 - Protection of certain rights regarding freedom of speech, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-120",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "KA Najeeb Vs Union of India case deals with violation of rights under_____",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 16",
            "B": "Article 21",
            "C": "Article 14",
            "D": "Article 19"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 21",
        "explanation": "Article 21 (Protection of life and personal liberty). Important Cases related to Article 21: A.K Gopalan vs the State of Madras 1950 : The Supreme court has taken a narrow interpretation of Article 21 in this case. Maneka Gandhi vs. Union of India, 1978: In this case, the SC overruled its judgement of the Gopalan Case by taking a wider interpretation of Article 21."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-121",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Constitution of India contains the provisions of the Union Executive?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part V",
            "B": "Part III",
            "C": "Part IV",
            "D": "Part VI"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Part V",
        "explanation": "Part V. Other parts of constitution: Part III - Fundamental Rights (Article 12 to 35), Part IV - Directive Principle of State Policy (Article - 36 to 51), Part VI - The States (Article 152 to 237)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-122",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Fundamental duties were not placed in Part III of the Indian Constitution because Part III is_________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "non-justiciable",
            "B": "justiciable",
            "C": "not enforceable",
            "D": "absolute"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "justiciable",
        "explanation": "Justiciable. Part III Article (12-35): Fundamental Rights. Fundamental duties (Part IVA Article 51A) added by the 42nd Amendment Act (1976). These duties are non-justiciable, meaning they are not enforceable by a court of law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-123",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution provides for a bicameral Parliament of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 49",
            "B": "Article 59",
            "C": "Article 79",
            "D": "Article 89"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 79",
        "explanation": "Article 79 :- Constitution of Parliament - There shall be a Parliament of the Union consisting of the President and two Houses known as the Council of States (Rajya Sabha, Article 80) and the House of the People (Lok Sabha, Article 81). Article 49 - Protection of monuments and places and objects of national importance. Article 59 - Conditions of the President's office."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-124",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per Article 172 (2)_______of a State shall NOT be subject to dissolution. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity",
        "options": {
            "A": "Legislative Assembly",
            "B": "Legislative Council",
            "C": "House of People",
            "D": "Council of States"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Legislative Council",
        "explanation": "Legislative Council (Saasana Mandali) - It is the upper house in those states of India that have a bicameral state legislature. Six States have a Legislative Council: Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Maharashtra, Karnataka."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-125",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 323 of the Indian Constitution deals with __________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "expenses of Public Services Commissions",
            "B": "reports of Public Services Commissions",
            "C": "functions of Public Services Commissions",
            "D": "power to extend functions of Public Services Commissions"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "reports of Public Services Commissions",
        "explanation": "reports of Public Services Commissions. Articles 315 to 323 (Part XIV) of the Constitution of India establish the Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) and State Public Service Commissions (SPSC). The UPSC Chairman is appointed by the President for a term of six years or until the age of 65, whichever is earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-126",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution empowers the Supreme Court to review its own judgements or orders ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 138",
            "B": "Article 135",
            "C": "Article 136",
            "D": "Article 137"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 137",
        "explanation": "Article 137. Article 138 - Enlargement of the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court. Article 135 - Jurisdiction and powers of the Federal Court under existing law to be exercisable by the Supreme Court. Article 136 - Special leave to appeal by the Supreme Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-127",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution empowers the Parliament to establish additional courts for better administration of laws made by it",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 246",
            "B": "Article 248",
            "C": "Article 253",
            "D": "Article 247"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 247",
        "explanation": "Article 247. Article 246 - Subject-matter of laws made by Parliament and by the Legislatures of States. Article 248 - Residuary powers of legislation. Article 253 - Legislation for giving effect to international agreements."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-128",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution deals with the removal and suspension of a member of the Public Service Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 320",
            "B": "Article 324",
            "C": "Article 317",
            "D": "Article 315"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 317",
        "explanation": "Article 317. Part XIV (Articles 315 to 323) - Establishment of UPSC for Union and Public Service Commission for each state. Article 320 - Functions of Public Service Commissions. Article 315 - Public Service Commissions for the Union and for the States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-129",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution deals with the organisation, composition and powers of the state legislature?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part IV",
            "B": "Part VI",
            "C": "Part III",
            "D": "Part V"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Part VI",
        "explanation": "Part VI Article (152 to 237). Article 168 Constitution of Legislatures in States. Article 169 deals with abolition or creation of Legislative Councils in states. Article 170 - Composition of the Legislative Assemblies. Article 171 - Composition of the legislative Councils. Article 172 - Duration of State Legislatures."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-130",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India provides that there shall be a Legislative Assembly for the National Capital Territory of Delhi?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 231AA",
            "B": "Article 239AA",
            "C": "Article 233AA",
            "D": "Article 237AA"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 239AA",
        "explanation": "Article 239AA. The 69th Amendment Act (1991) - A special status to the Union Territory of Delhi by designing it as the National Capital Territory of Delhi. Brahm Prakash was the first chief minister of Delhi."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-131",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which among the following is a subject of Union Lists in the Constitution of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Liquor",
            "B": "Social planning",
            "C": "Extradition",
            "D": "Boilers"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Extradition",
        "explanation": "Extradition.The 7th Schedule of the Indian Constitution consists of three lists: Union List: 100 items (e.g., Defence, Army, International Relations). State List: 61 items (e.g., Local Government, Public Health, Prisons). Concurrent List: 52 items (e.g., Education, Forest, Trade Unions)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-132",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Provisions related to the seat of the \"Supreme Court of India\" is mentioned in which Article?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 132",
            "B": "Article 131",
            "C": "Article 130",
            "D": "Article 129"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 130",
        "explanation": "Article 130. The Federal Court of India was established on 1 October 1937. After Independence, the Federal Court was replaced as the Supreme Court of India (28 January 1950). Other related Articles : Article 124: Establishment and Constitution of Supreme Court. Article 129: Supreme Court to be a Court of Record. Article 131: Original Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court. Article 132: Appellate Jurisdiction of Supreme Court in appeals from High Court in certain cases."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-133",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Part XVI of the Indian constitution deals with ___________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "Elections",
            "B": "Special provisions related to certain classes",
            "C": "Constitutional amendments",
            "D": "Special provisions related to municipal corporation"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Special provisions related to certain classes",
        "explanation": "Special provisions related to certain classes (Article 330 to 342A). Article 330 - Reservation of seats for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the House of the People. Part XV (Article 324-329): Elections. Part XX (Article 368): Amendment of the Constitution. Part IXA (Article 243P-243ZG): The Municipalities."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-134",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian constitution provides for the National commission for Scheduled Castes ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 337",
            "B": "Article 344",
            "C": "Article 343",
            "D": "Article 338"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 338",
        "explanation": "Article 338. National commission for Scheduled Castes is a constitutional body.Other Commissions - National Commission for Scheduled Tribes (Article 338A inserted by the 89th Amendment Act 2003) and National Commission for Backward Classes (Article 338B). Article 343 - Official language of the Union. Article 344 - Commission and Committee of Parliament on Official Language. Article 337 - Special provisions in terms of educational grants/subsidies provided to the Anglo-Indian population of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-135",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Provisions related to the www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Municipalities are mentioned under which part of the Indian constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part IXA",
            "B": "Part VII",
            "C": "Part V",
            "D": "Part XII"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Part IXA",
        "explanation": "Part IXA. The Municipalities (Urban Local Governments) is a system of Democratic Decentralisation. It was added through the 74th Constitutional Amendment Act of 1992. Part VII - Repealed by the Constitution (Seventh Amendment Act, 1956). Part V - Provisions for the functioning of the Union Government. Part XII - Laws pertaining to Finance, Property, Contracts and Suits for Republic of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-136",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian constitution mentions that it is duty of the Union government to protect States against external aggression and internal disturbance?",
        "options": {
            "A": "353",
            "B": "356",
            "C": "355",
            "D": "358"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "355",
        "explanation": "Article 355. Other Articles - Article 353 - States about the Effect of the proclamation of emergency. Article 356 - States about the Provision in case of failure of constitutional machinery in the state (president rule). Article 358 - It deals with the suspension of fundamental rights guaranteed under Article 19 of the constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-137",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the constitution of India is related to the Comptroller and Auditor General of India Audit reports?",
        "options": {
            "A": "148",
            "B": "150",
            "C": "151",
            "D": "149"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "151",
        "explanation": "151. Part V: The Union, Chapter V : Comptroller and Auditor - General (CAG) of India (Article 148 - 151). Article 150: Form of accounts of the Union and of the States. Article 149: Duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor-General. Article 148: Comptroller and Auditor-General of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-138",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Central Bureau of Intelligence and Investigation comes under which list of the seventh schedule of the Indian constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Union list",
            "B": "Concurrent list",
            "C": "State list",
            "D": "Transferred list"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Union list",
        "explanation": "Union list (100) - Defence, Army, International Relations, Ports, Railways, Census, Communication, Central Bureau of Investigation etc. State list (61) - Public order, Police, Public health and sanitation, Hospitals and dispensaries, Agriculture, State Public Service Commission, etc. Concurrent list (52) - Education, Forest, Trade unions, population control and family planning, Marriage, Adoption, etc. Seventh schedule under Article 246 of the constitution deals with the division of powers between the union and the states."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-139",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The part VII of the Indian constitution has been omitted. It is related with which of the following?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Provision relating to property",
            "B": "States in part B of the first schedule",
            "C": "Armed forces in states in part A of the second schedule",
            "D": "Reservation for Anglo - Indian communities in parliament"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "States in part B of the first schedule",
        "explanation": "States in part B of the first schedule. Provision relating to property - constitutional right under Part XII, Article 300A (Added by 44th Amendment Act, 1978). The 104th Constitutional Amendment Act of 2019 abolished the reservation of seats for Anglo-Indians in the Parliament and State Legislatures of India in January 2020. The amendment also extended reservations for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes for up to ten years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-140",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian parliament has power to impose restrictions on trade, commerce and intercourse through which Article of the Indian constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "304",
            "B": "300 A",
            "C": "303",
            "D": "302"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "302",
        "explanation": "Article 302. Part XIII (Article 301-307) - Trade, Commerce and Intercourse within the Territory of India. Article 304: Restrictions on trade, commerce and intercourse among States. Article 303: Restrictions on the legislative powers of the Union and of the States with regard to trade and commerce. Article 300A: Persons not to be deprived of property save by authority of law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-141",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian constitution states that \"Governor has power to promulgate ordinances during recess of legislature\"?",
        "options": {
            "A": "212",
            "B": "214",
            "C": "213",
            "D": "210"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "213",
        "explanation": "Article 213.The governor can issue an ordinance when the state legislature is not in session, which must be approved by the state legislature within 6 weeks of its reassembly. Article 210 - Language to be used in the Legislature. Article 212 - Courts not to inquire into proceedings of the Legislature. Article 214 - High Courts for States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-142",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Part V chapter II of the Indian constitution does not include which of the following provisions?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Joint sitting of both house of Parliament in certain cases",
            "B": "Power of President to promulgate Ordinances during recess of Parliament",
            "C": "Language to be used in Parliament",
            "D": "Restriction on discussion in Parliament"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Power of President to promulgate Ordinances during recess of Parliament",
        "explanation": "Article 123 - Power of President to promulgate Ordinances during recess of Parliament. It is included under chapter III of part V of Indian constitution. Article 108 - Joint sitting of both Houses in certain cases. Article 120 - Language to be used in Parliament. Article 121 - Restriction on discussion in Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-143",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 243K of the Indian constitution is related with which of the following ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Durations of panchayat, etc.",
            "B": "Grounds of disqualification from membership of Panchayat.",
            "C": "Reservation of seats in Panchayat.",
            "D": "Election to the Panchayats."
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Election to the Panchayats.",
        "explanation": "Election to the Panchayats. Panchayati Raj is a three-tiered administrative framework in India that focuses on rural development. It consists of Gram Panchayats at the village level, Panchayat Samitis at the block level, and Zila Parishads at the district level. Article 243E - Duration of Panchayats. Article 243D - Reservation of seats in Panchayat. Article 243F - Grounds of disqualification from membership of Panchayat."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-144",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 350A of the Indian constitution is related with______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Special officers for linguistic minorities",
            "B": "Facilities for instruction in mother-tongue at primary stage",
            "C": "Direction for development of the Hindi language",
            "D": "Language to` be used in Supreme Court and High Courts of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Facilities for instruction in mother-tongue at primary stage",
        "explanation": "Article - 350 : Language to be used in representations for redress of grievances. Article - 350B: Special Officer www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity for linguistic minorities. Article- 351: Directive for development of the Hindi language. Article 348 (1)(a): All proceedings in the Supreme Court and in every High Court, shall be in English language."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-145",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Constitution of India consists of the idea of a Welfare State?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "B": "Fundamental Duties",
            "C": "Fundamental Rights",
            "D": "Preamble"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
        "explanation": "Directive Principles of State Policy is mentioned in Part IV, Article 36–51. Article 38 gives the idea of a Welfare State."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-146",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution does India mention that business in Parliament shall be transacted in Hindi or English?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 120",
            "B": "Article 121",
            "C": "Article 122",
            "D": "Article 119"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 120",
        "explanation": "Article 120. Article 121 - Restriction on discussion in Parliament. Article 122 - Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Parliament. Article 119 - Regulation by law of procedure in Parliament in relation to financial business."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-147",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of Indian constitution is related with the Special provisions with respect to the State of Sikkim?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 371C",
            "B": "Article 371",
            "C": "Article 371F",
            "D": "Article 371A"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 371F",
        "explanation": "371 F - Sikkim (36th Amendment Act, 1975). Article 371 of the Constitution includes special provisions for 11 states (6 states of the Northeast). Article 371 - provisions for Maharashtra and Gujarat. Article 371 A - Nagaland (13th Amendment Act, 1962). 371 B - Assam (22nd Amendment Act, 1969). 371 C - Manipur (27th Amendment Act, 1971). 371 D - Andhra Pradesh and Telangana (32nd. Amendment Act, 1973). 371 E - To establish Central University in Andhra Pradesh. 371 G - Mizoram (53rd. Amendment Act, 1986). 371 H - Arunachal Pradesh (55th Amendment Act, 1986). 371 I - Goa."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-148",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India deals with the appointment of ad - hoc judges?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 126",
            "B": "Article 127",
            "C": "Article 128",
            "D": "Article 125"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 127",
        "explanation": "Article 127. Article 125: talks about the financial privileges and allowances that are defined for the judges of the Supreme Court. Article 126: Appointment of acting Chief Justice of India. Article 128: Attendance of retired judges at sitting of the Supreme Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-149",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India deals with the Sessions of the Parliament?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 85",
            "B": "Article 89",
            "C": "Article 90",
            "D": "Article 101"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 85",
        "explanation": "Article 85 - Sessions of Parliament, prorogation, and dissolution. A session is a period during which a House meets almost every day uninterruptedly to manage the business. Article 90 - Vacation and resignation of (and removal from) the office of Deputy Chairman. Article 101- Vacation of seats in Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-150",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which chapter of the Constitution of India, discusses the Articles of Parliament ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Chapter III",
            "B": "Chapter I",
            "C": "Chapter II",
            "D": "Chapter IV"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Chapter II",
        "explanation": "Chapter II (79-122). Part V - The Union of Indian Constitution Chapter II deals with the Articles of Parliament . Chapter I (The Executive; Articles 52 to 78); Chapter III: Legislative powers of the President; Article 123); Chapter IV (The Union Judiciary; Articles 124 - 147). Chapter V (Comptroller and Auditor - General of India (CAG); Articles 148 to 151)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-151",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Article of the Indian Constitution that deals with all the executive powers of the Governor is ____",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 150",
            "B": "Article 157",
            "C": "Article 154",
            "D": "Article 156"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 154",
        "explanation": "Article 154- Executive power of Governor. Article 150 - Form of accounts of the Union and of the States. Article 157 - Qualifications for appointment as Governor. Article 156 - Term of office of Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-152",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Part of the Indian Constitution provides for the Union Public Service Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part X",
            "B": "Part VIII",
            "C": "Part XIV",
            "D": "Part XVI"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Part XIV",
        "explanation": "Part XIV. Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) is an independent constitutional body. The provisions regarding the composition of UPSC, the appointment, and removal of its members, and the powers and functions of UPSC are provided in Part XIV of the Indian Constitution under Article 315 to Article 323."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-153",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article ______ of the Indian Constitution states that ‘there shall be a Commission for the socially and educationally backward classes to be known as the National Commission for Backward Classes’.",
        "options": {
            "A": "124 A (1)",
            "B": "243S (1)",
            "C": "243Y (1)",
            "D": "338B (1)"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "338B (1)",
        "explanation": "Article 338B (1). Article 243S(1) - There shall be constituted Wards Committees, consisting of one or more wards, within the territorial area of a Municipality having a population of three lakhs or more."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-154",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India states that Hindi in Devanagari script shall be the official language of the Union?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 343(2)",
            "B": "Article 354(2)",
            "C": "Article 343(1)",
            "D": "Article 343(3)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 343(1)",
        "explanation": "Article 343(1). Article 343(2) -The Constitution adopted in 1950 stipulated that English and Hindi would be used for the Union's official business for a period of fifteen years. Article 354 deals with the application of provisions related to the distribution of revenues while a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-155",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the constitution of India provides for the creation of a GST Council ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 246A",
            "B": "Article 279A",
            "C": "Article 269A",
            "D": "Article 323A"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 279A",
        "explanation": "Article 279A. It empowers the president to constitute a joint forum of the central and states namely, Goods and Services Tax Council. The GST Council is a constitutional body for making recommendations to the union and state government on issues related to Goods and Service Tax."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-156",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "According to which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India shall a Money Bill NOT be introduced in the Council of States ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 109",
            "B": "Article 354",
            "C": "Article 298",
            "D": "Article 193"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 109",
        "explanation": "Article 109. Rajya Sabha (Council of States), the upper house of the Parliament of India. A money bill is a specific type of financial legislation that exclusively deals with matters related to taxes, government revenues, or expenditures."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-157",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per Article ______ of the Constitution of India, English is the official language for all the high courts in the country.",
        "options": {
            "A": "329 (1)",
            "B": "336 (1)",
            "C": "315 (1)",
            "D": "348 (1)"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "348 (1)",
        "explanation": "Article 348 (1). 329(a) the validity of any law relating to the delimitation of constituencies or the allotment of seats to such constituencies, made or purporting to be made under Article 327 or Article 328, shall not be called in question in any court"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-158",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India defines for a separate secretarial staff for each House of the Parliament?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 98",
            "B": "Article 123",
            "C": "Article 155",
            "D": "Article 34"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 98",
        "explanation": "Article 98. Article 155- Appointment of the Governor. Article 34- Restriction on rights conferred by third Part while martial law is in force in any area."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-159",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India states that there would be no tax levied or collected EXCEPT by the authority of law?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 107",
            "B": "Article 123",
            "C": "Article 265",
            "D": "Article 301"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 265",
        "explanation": "Article 265. Article 107- Provisions as to introduction and passing of Bills. Article 301- Freedom of trade, commerce and intercourse."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-160",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution are special provisions provided to language spoken in a section of the population?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 337",
            "B": "Article 357",
            "C": "Article 347",
            "D": "Article 374"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 347",
        "explanation": "Article 347 Under part XVII, of the Indian constitution : Special Provision Relating to Language Spoken by a Section of the Population of a State. Amendments"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-161",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per the Constitution (Ninety - First Amendment) Act, 2003, the total number of ministers, including the Prime Minister, shall NOT exceed:",
        "options": {
            "A": "20% of the total number of members of the Lok Sabha",
            "B": "15% of the total number of members of the Lok Sabha",
            "C": "10% of the total number of members of the Lok Sabha",
            "D": "25% of the total number of members of the Lok Sabha"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "15% of the total number of members of the Lok Sabha",
        "explanation": "91st Amendment Act 2003: The total number of ministers in the Council of Ministers, including the Prime Minister, cannot exceed 15% of the total number of members in the Lok Sabha. The total number of ministers in a State Council of Ministers, including the Chief Minister, cannot exceed 15% of the total number of members in the Legislative Assembly of that State."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-162",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Part IV A of the Indian Constitution was inserted in the Indian Constitution through______ Constitutional Amendment Act.",
        "options": {
            "A": "44th",
            "B": "46th",
            "C": "48th",
            "D": "42nd"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "42nd",
        "explanation": "42nd. The fundamental duties were incorporated in Part IV-A of the Constitution by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976 on the recommendations of the Swaran Singh Committee. Initially, there were 10 duties, but an additional duty was added by the 86th Constitutional Amendment Act, 2002, bringing the total to 11 duties."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-163",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "____________ Directive principles of State Policy were added to the Indian Constitution by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act of 1976.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Two",
            "B": "Three",
            "C": "Five",
            "D": "Four"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Four",
        "explanation": "Four. These Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSP) are: Article 39(f) which provided that “the State shall direct its policy towards securing for the children opportunities and facilities to develop in a healthy manner and in conditions of freedom and dignity and for protecting children and youth from exploitation and against material abandonment”; Article 39(A) promotes equal justice and free legal aid for the poor; Article 43(A) secures workers' participation in industry management; and Article 48(A) protects the environment and wildlife."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-164",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitution Amendment Bills is related to the provision of modifying the list of Scheduled Caste in Tamil Nadu ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order (Amendment) Bill, 2019",
            "B": "The Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order Amendment Act, 2013",
            "C": "The Constitution (Scheduled Caste) Order (Amendment) Bill, 2015",
            "D": "The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order (Amendment) Bill, 2021"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order (Amendment) Bill, 2021",
        "explanation": "The Bill amends the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 1950. The Constitution empowers the President to specify the Scheduled Castes (SCs) in various states and union territories. Further, it permits Parliament to modify this list of notified SCs. The Statement of Objects and Reasons of the Bill states that the Bill has been introduced to give effect to modifications proposed by the state of Tamil Nadu."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-165",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendment Acts led to formation of the Goods and Services Tax Council ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "102nd Constitutional Amendment Act",
            "B": "100th Constitutional Amendment Act",
            "C": "101st Constitutional Amendment Act",
            "D": "103rd Constitutional Amendment Act"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "101st Constitutional Amendment Act",
        "explanation": "101st Constitutional Amendment Act, 2016. Article 279A of the Indian Constitution establishes the Goods and Services Tax Council (GST Council) chaired by the finance minister of India. 100th Constitutional Amendment Act, 2015: Ratified the land boundary agreement between India and Bangladesh. The 102nd Constitutional Amendment Act: Enhanced regulations to support backward classes in India. The 103rd Constitutional Amendment Act: Established a 10% reservation for Economically Weaker Sections."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-166",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India CANNOT be amended with a simple majority ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "169",
            "B": "2",
            "C": "21",
            "D": "3"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "21",
        "explanation": "21. Article 21 asserts that no person shall be deprived of their life except according to the procedure established by law. This means that www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity every individual has the right to live, and their life cannot be taken away except in accordance with the prescribed legal procedures. It is a part of Fundamental rights (Part III). It can be amended only by a special majority in both houses of Parliament by two-thirds of members present and voting."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-167",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles was amended by The Constitution Fiftieth Amendment Act, 1984?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 78",
            "B": "Article 99",
            "C": "Article 33",
            "D": "Article 56"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 33",
        "explanation": "Article 33 - the Power of Parliament to modify the rights conferred by this Part in their application to Forces, etc. Article 78 - Duties of the Prime Minister as respects the furnishing of information to the President, etc. Article 99 - Oath or affirmation by members of the Parliament. Article 56 - Term of office of President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-168",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On 9 August 2021, the Parliament had passed the Limited Liability Partnership (Amendment) Bill, 2021. It amended the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2004",
            "B": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008",
            "C": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2012",
            "D": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2016"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008",
        "explanation": "Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008. It was published in the official Gazette of India on 9 January 2009 and has been in effect since 31 March 2009. LLP Amendment Bill, 2021 passed on 28th July 2021 by both house of Parliament. 29 amendments were made to LLP Act 2008 by LLP Amendment Bill 2021."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-169",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On 7 November 2022, the Supreme Court of India upheld the reservations for the weaker sections (EWS). Which of the following amendments brought this reservation in the first place ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "101st Amendment of the Constitution",
            "B": "102nd Amendment of the Constitution",
            "C": "103rd Amendment of the Constitution",
            "D": "104th Amendment of the Constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "103rd Amendment of the Constitution",
        "explanation": "103rd Amendment to the Constitution. The 103rd Amendment Act of the Constitution, 2019 was enacted to introduce reservation for the economically weaker sections (EWS). Under this amendment, Articles 15(6) and 16(6) of the Constitution were amended. Through this amendment, 10% reservation was provided in educational institutions and government jobs for the economically weaker sections of the country."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-170",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years did the Constitution (One Hundredth Amendment) Act come into force ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2015",
            "B": "2020",
            "C": "2009",
            "D": "2001"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "2015",
        "explanation": "2015. The Constitution (100th Amendment) Act of 2015 ratified the Land Boundary Agreement between India and Bangladesh. This amendment gave effect to the acquisition and transfer of territories between the two countries, pursuant to the Land Boundary Agreement of 1974 and its protocol of 2011."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-171",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles was amended in the Constitution (Fifth Amendment Act), 1955 ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 3",
            "B": "Article 45",
            "C": "Article 17",
            "D": "Article 34"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 3",
        "explanation": "Article 3 deals with the formation of new states and the alteration of areas, boundaries, or names of existing states. Article 45 was amended by the Constitution (Eighty-sixth Amendment) Act of 2002. The amendment changed the subject matter of Article 45 and made elementary education a fundamental right under Article 21."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-172",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Amendment Acts led to the insertion of Article 21 A ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Eighty-seventh Amendment Act, 2003",
            "B": "Eighty-fourth Amendment Act, 2002",
            "C": "Eighty-sixth Amendment Act, 2002",
            "D": "Eighty-fifth Amendment Act, 2002"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Eighty-sixth Amendment Act, 2002",
        "explanation": "Eighty-sixth Amendment Act, 2002. This Amendment Act, 2002 made the Right to Education a fundamental right for children aged 6-14 by adding Article 21A in Part III of the Constitution. The 87th Amendment Act, 2003 involved readjusting electoral constituencies based on the 2001 census. The 85th Amendment Act, 2002 provided for promotion with consequential seniority for government employees from Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-173",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The 42nd Amendment of the Indian Constitution (1976) states that India is a/an ______ nation.",
        "options": {
            "A": "secular",
            "B": "capitalist",
            "C": "aristocratic",
            "D": "oligarchic"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "secular",
        "explanation": "secular. The term means that all the religions in India get equal respect, protection and support from the state. The Preamble was amended only once by the 42nd Amendment Act to add ‘Socialist’, ‘Secular’ and Integrity terms."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-174",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "73rd Amendment Act 1992 makes provisions for a 3 - tier system of Panchayati Raj for all the states having population of above:",
        "options": {
            "A": "20 lakh",
            "B": "10 lakh",
            "C": "15 lakh",
            "D": "5 lakh"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "20 lakh",
        "explanation": "20 lakh. 73rd Constitutional Amendment Act of 1992, enacted by the Narasimha Rao government and effective from April 24, 1993, aimed to strengthen local self-governance by establishing democracy at the grassroots level. Part IX of the Constitution outlines the Panchayati Raj system, with Rajasthan implementing it first in Nagaur district on October 2, 1959. The Balwant Rai Mehta Committee recommended a three-tier structure: Zilla Parishad (district level), Panchayat Samiti (block level), and Gram Panchayat (village level). Q.176 In which year did the 44th Amendment remove the right to property from the list of fundamental rights? SSC CPO 03/10/2023 (Evening) (a) 1978 (b) 1975 (c) 1973 (d) 1981 Sol.176.(a) 1978. The right to property was listed under Article 31 before its deletion. At present the right to property is listed under Article 300A as a legal right."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-175",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which among the following is INCORRECT about the salient features of the 73rd Amendment Act ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Act corresponds to Part III of the Constitution of India.",
            "B": "The Act gives a Constitutional status to the Panchayati Raj Institutions.",
            "C": "The Act has added the Eleventh Schedule to the Constitution of India.",
            "D": "It contains 29 functional items of the Panchayats and deals with Article 243 to 243(O)."
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "The Act corresponds to Part III of the Constitution of India.",
        "explanation": "The 73rd Amendment Act - It was enacted in 1992 and came into force from April 1993. It added Part IX (Article 243 - 243O) to the constitution. It was enacted to implement the Directive www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Principles of State Policy under Article 40 on the recommendation of L.M. Singhvi Committee."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-176",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many types of the amendment are mentioned by the Indian Constitution as per Article 368 ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Four",
            "B": "Two",
            "C": "Five",
            "D": "Three"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Two",
        "explanation": "Two. Article 368 (Part XX) grants Parliament the power to amend the Constitution. Amendments require either (1) a special majority or (2) a special majority with ratification by at least half of the state legislatures by a simple majority. The amendment procedure is inspired by the South African Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-177",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, which provides for the more effective prevention of certain unlawful activities of individuals and associations dealing with terrorist activities, was first put into effect in India in the year.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1991",
            "B": "1967",
            "C": "2014",
            "D": "1947"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1967",
        "explanation": "1967. Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act - Its main objective is dealing with activities directed against the integrity and sovereignty of India. It assigns absolute power to the central government and provides for death penalty and life imprisonment of culprits. Related acts - Armed Forces Special Powers Act (AFSPA) 1958; Prevention of Terrorism Act, 2002; The National Investigation Agency Act, 2008; The Anti - Hijacking Act, 2016."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-178",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Family Courts (Amendment) Act 2022 has amended the Family Courts Act, 1984. The Act allows ________ to establish Family Courts.",
        "options": {
            "A": "District Courts",
            "B": "State Governments",
            "C": "Union Government",
            "D": "District Collector"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "State Governments",
        "explanation": "State Governments. Purpose of establishment of family court - To promote conciliation and secure speedy settlement of disputes relating to marriage and family affairs and for related matters. This bill was passed by Lok Sabha on 26th July 2022. This bill has granted statutory cover to already established family courts in Himachal Pradesh and Nagaland."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-179",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In August 2021, Ram Nath Kovind granted assent to which Constitution Amendment Act empowering states and UTs to identify and specify Socially and Educationally Backward Classes?",
        "options": {
            "A": "105th",
            "B": "104th",
            "C": "103rd",
            "D": "102nd"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "105th",
        "explanation": "105th. Reservation in India: Other Backward Class (OBCs) were included in the ambit of reservation in 1991 on the recommendations of the Mandal Commission. It recommended a 27% reservation quota for OBC. Constitutional Provisions: Part XVI deals with reservation of SC and ST in Central and State legislatures. 342A - Socially and educationally backward classes."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-180",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Andhra Pradesh Reorganisation Act passed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2013",
            "B": "2012",
            "C": "2014",
            "D": "2015"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "2014",
        "explanation": "2014. The States Reorganisation Act (1956), under the provisions of Part I (Article 3). The State Reorganisation Commission (SRC) was constituted in 1953 appointed by Jawahar Lal Nehru. It was headed by Sir Fazal Ali. The first state formed on the linguistic basis is Andhra Pradesh (1 October 1953). Formation of other states: Gujarat and Maharashtra (1960), Karnataka (1956), Nagaland (1963), Haryana (1966), Sikkim (1975)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-181",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many Directive Principles of the original list in the Indian Constitution were amended by the 44th Amendment Act of 1978 ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Three",
            "B": "One",
            "C": "Two",
            "D": "Four"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "One",
        "explanation": "One (Article 38(2): Requires the state to reduce inequalities in income, status, facilities, and opportunities). Directive Principles of State Policy: Part IV of the Constitution of India (Article 36–51). It was borrowed from the Irish Constitution. Article 38 (1) - The State shall strive to promote the welfare of the people by securing and protecting as effectively as it may a social order in which justice, social, economic and political, shall inform all the institutions of national life."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-182",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which among the following Constitutional Amendment Act of the Indian constitution reduced the age of voting from 21 to 18 for elections to the Lok Sabha and to the Legislative Assemblies of states?",
        "options": {
            "A": "81st",
            "B": "61st",
            "C": "52nd",
            "D": "72nd"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "61st",
        "explanation": "61st. It was done by amending Article 326 of the constitution in 1988. 81st Constitutional Amendment Act 2000 was inserted to protect the reservation for SCs and STs in backlog of vacancies. 52nd Constitutional Amendment Act 1985, known as anti-defection law and 10th schedule added in the Indian constitution. 72nd Constitutional Amendment Act 1992 provides reservation to Scheduled Tribes in Tripura State Legislative Assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-183",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which amendment in the Indian constitution is related to extension of jurisdiction of High Courts to Union territories ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "9th Amendment",
            "B": "7th Amendment",
            "C": "1st Amendment",
            "D": "13th Amendment"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "7th Amendment",
        "explanation": "7th Amendment. This constitutional amendment was done in 1956 to reorganise the classes of states in the country and to change the powers and functions of the state governors. 1st Amendment (1951) - The rights of property owners and made it more difficult for the government to enact land reform measures. It also added the Ninth Schedule, which protected certain laws from being challenged in the courts. 9th Amendment (1960) - Facilitate the cession of the Berubari union. 13th Amendment (1962) - Nagaland was formed with special status under Article 371A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-184",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Seventy - First Amendment to the Indian Constitution included Konkani, Manipuri, and Nepali languages in the Schedule.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Eighth",
            "B": "Sixth",
            "C": "Fifth",
            "D": "Seventh"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Eighth",
        "explanation": "Eighth Schedule. 22 languages in this schedule. 21st Amendment Act (1967) - Include Sindhi language. 92nd Amendment Act (2003) - Include Bodo, Dogri, Maithili and Santhali language. 5th schedule - The President can declare any such area or the whole state as a scheduled area. 6th schedule - Deals with administration of tribal areas in Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura, Mizoram. 7th Schedule - Deals with the division of powers between the Union government and State governments"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-185",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Eighty - ninth Amendment Act, 2003 of the Indian Constitution established which of the following Commission ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Competition Commission of India",
            "B": "National Commission for Backward www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Classes",
            "C": "National Commission for Woman",
            "D": "National Commission for Scheduled Tribes"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "National Commission for Scheduled Tribes",
        "explanation": "The National Commission for Scheduled Tribes (NCST) was established by amending Article 338 and inserting a new Article 338A in the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-186",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which among the following constitutional amendments of the Indian Constitution deals with the formation of Sikkim as a state?",
        "options": {
            "A": "36th",
            "B": "51th",
            "C": "42nd",
            "D": "30th"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "36th",
        "explanation": "36th. 51st amendment: Reservation of seats in the Lok Sabha for Scheduled Tribes in Meghalaya, Arunachal Pradesh, Nagaland and Mizoram as well as in the Legislative Assemblies of Meghalaya and Nagaland. 30th amendment: Abolished provision to appeal to the Supreme Court on a civil case related to a certain amount."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-187",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Amendment to the Constitution Act was the reservation for OBCs in educational institutions made?",
        "options": {
            "A": "95th Amendment",
            "B": "94th Amendment",
            "C": "93rd Amendment",
            "D": "96th Amendment"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "93rd Amendment",
        "explanation": "93rd Amendment 2005. 95th (2009): Extended the reservation of seats for the SCs and STs and special representation for the Anglo-Indians in the Lok Sabha and the state legislative assemblies for a further period of ten years i.e., up to 2020 (Article 334). 96th (2011): Substituted “Odia” for “Oriya”. Consequently, the “Oriya” language in the Eighth Schedule shall be pronounced as “Odia”. 94th (2006), made provisions for the appointment of a Minister in charge of tribal welfare in the states of Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-188",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Amendment to the Constitution Act led to establishment of National Judicial Appointments Commission in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "95th Amendment",
            "B": "99th Amendment",
            "C": "96th Amendment",
            "D": "97th Amendment"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "99th Amendment",
        "explanation": "99th Amendment 2014. 97th amendment 2011- It gave special constitutional status and protection to all the cooperative societies (Part IX-B) prevailing in India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-189",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendments incorporated Dadra and Nagar Haveli in the Union of India as a Union Territory ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "19th",
            "B": "14th",
            "C": "12th",
            "D": "10th"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "10th",
        "explanation": "The 10th Amendment (1961) added Dadra and Nagar Haveli as India’s seventh Union Territories. The 12th Amendment (1962) incorporated Goa, Daman, and Diu as the eighth Union Territory, while the 14th Amendment (1962) included Pondicherry as the ninth. The 19th Amendment (1966) abolished Election Tribunals, assigning election petition trials to High Courts."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-190",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following presidents of India gave assent to the 100th Amendment of the Constitution of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Pranab Mukherjee",
            "B": "Ram Nath Kovind",
            "C": "APJ Abdul Kalam",
            "D": "Pratibha Devisingh Patil"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Pranab Mukherjee",
        "explanation": "Pranab Mukherjee. The 100th amendment in the Indian Constitution provides for the acquisition of territories by India and transfer of certain territories to Bangladesh. Constitution (100th Amendment) Act 2015 ratified the land boundary agreement between India and Bangladesh."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-191",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi (Amendment) Bill, 2021, which was passed in March 2021 amended the Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, ___",
        "options": {
            "A": "1998",
            "B": "1994",
            "C": "1996",
            "D": "1991"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1991",
        "explanation": "1991. Delhi became the capital of India on 12 December 1911."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-192",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Amendments of the Constitution of India gave the status of state to Goa?",
        "options": {
            "A": "52nd Amendment",
            "B": "56th Amendment",
            "C": "59th Amendment",
            "D": "48th Amendment"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "56th Amendment",
        "explanation": "56th Amendment. The 59th Amendment Act, 1988- It empowered the Central Government to impose Emergency in Punjab when deemed necessary. Under the amendment, the President's rule can be extended up to three years. 48th Amendment Act passed in 1984 with respect to the State of Punjab, Parliament may pass any resolution with respect to the continuance in force of the Proclamation for a period up to two years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-193",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "An amendment to the Hindu Succession Act, 1956 was passed in the year ______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "2012",
            "B": "2005",
            "C": "2010",
            "D": "2008"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "2005",
        "explanation": "2005. The Hindu Succession Act, 1956 is an Act of the Parliament of India enacted to amend and codify the law relating to intestate or unwilled succession, among Hindus, Buddhists, Jains, and Sikhs."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-194",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The 60th Amendment to the Constitution of India increased the ceiling of profession tax from ₹ 250 p.a. to ______ p.a.",
        "options": {
            "A": "₹7,000",
            "B": "₹5,000",
            "C": "₹1,000",
            "D": "₹2,500"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "₹2,500",
        "explanation": "₹2,500 . The Sixtieth Amendment of the Constitution of India Act, 1988, amended Article 276 of the Constitution relating to taxes on professions, trades, callings and employments."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-195",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The 40th Amendment Act of 1976 was applied to which Article of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "297",
            "B": "248",
            "C": "245",
            "D": "226"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "297",
        "explanation": "40th amendment was proposed to amend Article 297 of the Constitution so as to provide that all lands, minerals, and other things of value underlying the ocean within the exclusive economic zone of India and all other resources of the exclusive economic zone of India shall also vest in the Union."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-196",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Amendment Acts of the Constitution of India abolished the privy purses and privileges of former rulers of princely states?",
        "options": {
            "A": "25th Amendment Act 1971",
            "B": "26th Amendment Act 1971",
            "C": "28th Amendment Act 1972",
            "D": "27th Amendment Act 1971"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "26th Amendment Act 1971",
        "explanation": "26th Amendment Act 1971. 25th Amendment Act 1971- Restrict property rights and compensation in case the state takes over private property. 28th Amendment Act 1972, abolished the special privileges of ICS officers and empowered the Parliament to determine their service conditions. 27th Amendment Act 1971- Reorganisation of Mizoram into a Union www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Territory with a legislature and council of ministers."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-197",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which amendment to the Constitution of India added a new subject in the Union List called 'taxes on services’",
        "options": {
            "A": "56th",
            "B": "62nd",
            "C": "78th",
            "D": "88th"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "88th",
        "explanation": "88th constitutional amendment 2003. 62nd Amendment Act, 1989 - Extend reservation for SCs and STs and nomination of Anglo Indian members in Parliament and State Assemblies for another ten years i.e. up to 2000. 78th Amendment Act, 1995 - Place land reform acts and amendments to these acts under Schedule 9 of the constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-198",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Amendments of the Constitution of India amended Article 19 and inserted provisions fully securing the constitutional validity of zamindari abolition laws in general and certain specified State Acts in particular?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Fourth Amendment",
            "B": "First Amendment",
            "C": "Third Amendment",
            "D": "Second Amendment"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "First Amendment",
        "explanation": "The First Amendment (1951) introduced provisions for advancing socially and educationally backward classes, SCs, and STs, added the Ninth Schedule to secure zamindari abolition laws, and allowed reasonable restrictions on freedom of speech (Article 19) by adding grounds such as public order, friendly relations with foreign states, and incitement to an offence. It also upheld the state’s right to nationalise businesses without violating the right to trade. Fundamental Rights and Duties"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-199",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following duties is specified as the 10th Fundamental Duty in the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To strive towards excellence in all spheres of individual and collective activity",
            "B": "To provide opportunities for education to his child or as the case may be, ward between the age of six and fourteen years",
            "C": "To cherish and follow the noble ideals which inspired our national struggle for freedom",
            "D": "To develop the scientific temper, humanism and the spirit of inquiry and reform"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "To strive towards excellence in all spheres of individual and collective activity",
        "explanation": "The idea of Fundamental Duties is inspired from the Constitution of Russia. These were incorporated in Part IV-A (Article 51A) of the Constitution by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976 on the recommendations of the Swaran Singh Committee. Originally 10 in number. The 86th Amendment Act of 2002 added another duty (Article 51A(k)) related to providing educational opportunities for children between the ages of 6 and 14."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-200",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT the feature of Fundamental Duties provided under the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Duties are inspired from erstwhile USSR",
            "B": "Duties are non- justiciable in nature",
            "C": "Duties are enforceable by the law",
            "D": "Duties are intended to secure the country"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Duties are enforceable by the law",
        "explanation": "Duties are enforceable by the law. Fundamental Duties are a set of moral and ethical obligations that are enshrined in Part IV-A (Article 51A) of the Constitution of India. These duties are non-justiciable, meaning they are not enforceable by any court of law (unlike Fundamental Rights)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-201",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Right of a prisoner to speedy trial will be categorised in which of the following Fundamental Rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Right against Exploitation",
            "B": "Right to Life",
            "C": "Right to Constitutional Remedies",
            "D": "Right to Equality"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Right to Life",
        "explanation": "Right to Life. Speedy trial is an inalienable right under Article 21 of the constitution and hence no person shall be deprived of his life and liberty without the procedure of law and the procedure of law must be 'fair', 'reasonable', and 'just'."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-202",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which article has a similar provision to that of Article 32 and deals with writ jurisdiction?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 227",
            "B": "Article 228",
            "C": "Article 225",
            "D": "Article 226"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 226",
        "explanation": "Article 226. In India, writs are issued by the Supreme Court under Article 32 of the Constitution of India and by the High Courts under Article 226 of the Constitution of India. There are 5 types of writs issued in India - Habeas Corpus (to have the body of), Mandamus (we command), Certiorari (to be certified or to be informed), Prohibition (to forbid) and Quo-Warranto (by what authority or warrant)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-203",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution prohibits providing of any religious instruction in the educational institutions maintained by the State?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 29",
            "B": "Article 28",
            "C": "Article 30",
            "D": "Article 31"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 28",
        "explanation": "Article 28. Other Important Articles of Fundamental Rights (Part III, Articles 12-35) : Article 29 - Protects the cultural and educational rights of minorities in India. Article 30 - The Rights of Minorities to establish and administer educational institutions. Article 31 (Right to Property) - The 44th Amendment Act of 1978 repealed it and made it a constitutional right under Article 300A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-204",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution contains Fundamental Duties?",
        "options": {
            "A": "32A",
            "B": "45A",
            "C": "62B",
            "D": "51A"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "51A",
        "explanation": "51A. Fundamental Duties (Part IV - Article 51A): Ten duties were included by the 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 based on the Swaran Singh Committee's recommendations, and the 11th duty was added by the 86th Amendment Act of 2002."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-205",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A student, on his school assignment, is taking a session on how to make compost at home for using it at a park. Which fundamental duty is he performing?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To strive towards excellence in all spheres of individual and collective activity",
            "B": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence",
            "C": "To develop the scientific temper, humanism and the spirit of inquiry",
            "D": "To protect and improve the natural environment"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "To protect and improve the natural environment",
        "explanation": "Fundamental Duty (Part IVA - Article 51A). Related Article: Article 51A(g) - To protect and improve the natural environment. Article 51A (h): To develop the scientific temper, humanism and the spirit of inquiry and reform; Article 51A(i): To safeguard public property and to abjure violence; Article 51A(j): To strive towards excellence in all spheres of individual and collective activity so that the nation constantly rises to higher levels of endeavour and achievement. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-206",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article in the fundamental duty applies, when a construction worker takes his 8-year son to the site rather than sending him to school?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 51A (h)",
            "B": "Article 51A (k)",
            "C": "Article 51A (j)",
            "D": "Article 51A (i)"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 51A (k)",
        "explanation": "Article 51A (k) states that \"Who is a parent or guardian, to provide opportunities for education to his child or, as the case may be, ward between the age of six and fourteen years.\" It was added by the 86th Amendment Act, 2002. The Right to Education (RTE) Act, 2009, makes education compulsory for children between 6-14 years. Child labor is prohibited under the Child Labour (Prohibition and Regulation) Act, 1986."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-207",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following duties has been NOT prescribed by the Indian Constitution as Fundamental Duties? 1. To defend the country 2. To pay income tax 3. To cast the vote in election 4. To safeguard the public property",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 only",
            "B": "2 only",
            "C": "2 and 3 both",
            "D": "2 and 4 both"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "2 and 3 both",
        "explanation": "2 and 3 both. Fundamental duties were incorporated into the Constitution by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act of 1976 on the recommendations of the Swaran Singh Committee. Article 51-A (d) states the duty to defend the country and render national service when called upon to do so, while Article 51-A (i) emphasises the duty to safeguard public property and abjure violence."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-208",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which fundamental duty applies on you when you see a few school students, on their educational trip to Humayun’s tomb, writing their names on the walls?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To safeguard public property",
            "B": "To defend the country and render national service",
            "C": "To uphold and protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India",
            "D": "To protect and improve the natural environment"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "To safeguard public property",
        "explanation": "To safeguard public property. Article 51A —It shall be the duty of every citizen of India—(a) to abide by the Constitution and respect its ideals and institutions, the National Flag and the National Anthem; (b) to cherish and follow the noble ideals which inspired our national struggle for freedom; (c) to uphold and protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India; (d) to defend the country and render national service when called upon to do so."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-209",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution CANNOT be suspended even during an emergency declared on the grounds of war or external aggression ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Articles 15 and 17",
            "B": "Articles 20 and 21",
            "C": "Articles 14 and 16",
            "D": "Articles 30 and 32"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Articles 20 and 21",
        "explanation": "Articles 20 and 21. Article 14 - Equality before law. Article 15 - Prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth. Article 16 - Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment. Article 17 - Abolition of Untouchability. Article 20 - Protection in respect of conviction for offences. Article 21 - Protection of life and personal liberty. Article 30 - Right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-210",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which fundamental duty applies to you when you see your college friends start fighting with the canteen person when he passes a few anti-religious statements?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To promote harmony and spirit of brotherhood",
            "B": "To value and preserve the rich heritage",
            "C": "To develop the scientific temper, humanism, and the spirit of inquiry",
            "D": "To protect and improve our natural environment"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "To promote harmony and spirit of brotherhood",
        "explanation": "This fundamental duty encourages citizens to maintain harmony and foster a spirit of brotherhood among all people, transcending religious, linguistic, or regional differences. It applies in situations where religious sentiments might cause conflicts."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-211",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is INCORRECT regarding Fundamental Rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Fundamental Rights can be enforced by Law.",
            "B": "Fundamental rights are derived from the Britain Constitution.",
            "C": "The Fundamental Rights are mentioned in the constitution from article 12 to 35.",
            "D": "Article 21 provides the right to life."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Fundamental rights are derived from the Britain Constitution.",
        "explanation": "Fundamental Rights is derived from the Constitution of the USA. Enshrined in Part III (Article 12 to 35) of the Indian Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-212",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "If a 12-year-old is found to be working in a factory manufacturing carpets, which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India will be violated?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 24",
            "B": "Article 25",
            "C": "Article 23",
            "D": "Article 26"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 24",
        "explanation": "Article 24 - “No child below the age of fourteen years shall be employed to work in any factory or mine or engaged in any other hazardous employment”. Other Articles: Article 23 - Prohibition of traffic in human beings and forced labour. Article 25 - Freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion. Article 26 - Freedom to manage religious affairs."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-213",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which part of the Constitution will you find the six broad categories of Fundamental Rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part I",
            "B": "Part IV",
            "C": "Part II",
            "D": "Part III"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Part III",
        "explanation": "Part III (Articles 12 to 35). Six broad categories of Fundamental Rights : Right to Equality (Articles 14-18), Right to Freedom (Articles 19-22), Right against Exploitation (Articles 23-24), Right to Freedom of Religion (Articles 25-28), Cultural and Educational Rights (Articles 29-30), Right to Constitutional Remedies (Article 32)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-214",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Writ of Mandamus is a Fundamental Right classifiable under:",
        "options": {
            "A": "cultural and educational rights",
            "B": "the right to freedom of religion",
            "C": "constitutional remedies",
            "D": "the right to equality"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "constitutional remedies",
        "explanation": "Constitutional remedies. Right to Constitutional Remedies (Article 32) : This allows Indian citizens to approach the Supreme Court to enforce their fundamental rights. B.R. Ambedkar described it as the \"heart and soul\" of the Constitution. The writ in the Indian Constitution is borrowed from England. There are five types of writs : ‘Habeas Corpus’, ‘Mandamus’, ‘Prohibition’ , ‘Certiorari’ , and ‘Quo Warranto’ ."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-215",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles prohibits traffic in human beings and forced labour ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 25",
            "B": "Article 23 www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity",
            "C": "Article 22",
            "D": "Article 28"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 23 www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity",
        "explanation": "Article 23. Article 22 - Protection against arrest and detention in certain cases. Article 24 - Prohibition of employment of children in factories, etc. Article 25 - Freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion. Article 28 - Freedom as to attendance at religious instruction or religious worship in certain educational institutions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-216",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Clause of Article 20 incorporates the doctrine of double jeopardy?",
        "options": {
            "A": "3",
            "B": "2",
            "C": "1",
            "D": "4"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "2",
        "explanation": "2. Double Jeopardy is a legal term and it means that a person can not be punished for the same offence more than once. Article 20(2) of the Constitution of India and Section 300 of the Criminal Procedure Code say that no person shall be prosecuted and punished for the same offence more than once."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-217",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 20 of the Constitution of India is related to _____.",
        "options": {
            "A": "equality of opportunities in matters of public employment",
            "B": "protection in respect of conviction for offenses",
            "C": "freedom to manage religious affairs",
            "D": "abolition of titles"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "protection in respect of conviction for offenses",
        "explanation": "Article 20 provides three key protections: Ex-Post Facto Laws: No punishment for acts not punishable at the time they were committed, nor penalties exceeding those in force. Self-Incrimination: Individuals cannot be compelled to confess or make self-harming statements; includes the right to remain silent. Double Jeopardy: No one can be punished twice for the same offense."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-218",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Constitution states that ‘It shall be the duty of every citizen of India to promote harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood amongst all the people of India transcending religious, linguistic and regional or sectional diversities; to renounce practices derogatory to the dignity of women.’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "51 A",
            "B": "(b) 51 A",
            "C": "(c) 51 A (e)",
            "D": "51 A (d)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "(c) 51 A (e)",
        "explanation": "51 A (e). Fundamental Duties, outlined in Part IVA, Article 51A of the Indian Constitution, include: Abiding by the Constitution and respecting its ideals, as well as the National Flag and National Anthem. Cherishing and following the noble ideals that inspired India's struggle for freedom. Upholding and protecting the sovereignty, unity, and integrity of India. Defending the country and serving the nation when required."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-219",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "___________ has called the Right to Constitutional Remedy as the ‘Soul of the Constitution’.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "B": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "C": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "D": "Dr. BR Ambedkar"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Dr. BR Ambedkar",
        "explanation": "Dr. BR Ambedkar - the chief architect of the Indian Constitution. Article 32 grants every individual the right to move the Supreme Court for the enforcement of their fundamental rights. The Supreme Court has ruled that Article 32 is a basic feature of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-220",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Certiorari comes under the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "right to religious freedom",
            "B": "right to constitutional remedies",
            "C": "right against exploitation",
            "D": "right to equality"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "right to constitutional remedies",
        "explanation": "right to constitutional remedies. Certiorari is a writ issued by the Supreme Court or a High Court to review the decision or action of a lower court or tribunal. Article 32 of the Indian Constitution is a fundamental right that guarantees the right to constitutional remedies. This right allows individuals to seek redressal from the judiciary when their fundamental rights are violated."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-221",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "_______ Fundamental Duties were added in Part-IV of the Constitution under Article 51-A in the year 1976 through the 42nd Constitutional Amendment.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Nine",
            "B": "Eight",
            "C": "Ten",
            "D": "Twelve"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Ten",
        "explanation": "Ten. The Swaran Singh Committee in 1976 recommended Fundamental Duties, the necessity of which was felt during the internal emergency of 1975-77. The 11th Fundamental Duty, which is the provision of educational opportunities for children between the ages of six and fourteen years, was added by the 86th Amendment Act of 2002."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-222",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are INCORRECT vis-à-vis Fundamental Duties? 1) The 44th amendment Act introduced Fundamental duties in the Constitution. 2) Fundamental Duties were expanded by the 86th amendment act. 3) Article 51A",
        "options": {
            "A": "entails respect for its ideals and institutions, national flag and the national anthem. 4) Fundamental Duty obliges parents to provide opportunities for education to their child between 6-14 years of age. SSC CHSL 04/07/2024 (1st shift) (a) 1",
            "B": "2 and 3",
            "C": "2 and 4",
            "D": "Only 3"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "entails respect for its ideals and institutions, national flag and the national anthem. 4) Fundamental Duty obliges parents to provide opportunities for education to their child between 6-14 years of age. SSC CHSL 04/07/2024 (1st shift) (a) 1",
        "explanation": "1. The 44th Constitutional Amendment Act of 1978 was enacted to undo many changes made by the 42nd Amendment during the Emergency in India. Key provisions include restoring judicial review, protecting civil liberties, and ensuring that the right to property is no longer a fundamental right but a legal right."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-223",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many fundamental duties were recommended to be inserted in the Indian Constitution by the Swarna Singh Committee?",
        "options": {
            "A": "9",
            "B": "7",
            "C": "6",
            "D": "8"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "8",
        "explanation": "8. The idea of Fundamental Duties (Article 51-A) is inspired from the Constitution of the USSR (Russia). These were incorporated in Part IV-A of the Constitution by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-224",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A ________ is issued to prevent an inferior court or tribunal from exceeding its jurisdiction, which is not legally vested, or acting without jurisdiction or acting against the principles of natural justice.",
        "options": {
            "A": "writ of quo-warranto",
            "B": "writ of habeas corpus",
            "C": "writ of prohibition",
            "D": "writ of mandamus"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "writ of prohibition",
        "explanation": "Writ of prohibition. The Supreme Court and High Courts in India have the power to issue the writs under Article 32 (Supreme Court) and Article 226 (High Courts) of the Constitution, respectively. The Constitution of India provides for five types of writs: Habeas Corpus (To have the body), Mandamus (We Command), Prohibition (To forbid), Certiorari (To be certified), and Quo Warranto (By what authority)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-225",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A housemaid gets her 12-year-old daughter to help in her work as a house cleaner at a residential colony instead of sending her to school. Which www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity fundamental duty is violated by the housemaid ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To provide opportunities for education to his/her child",
            "B": "To promote harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood",
            "C": "To defend the country and render national service",
            "D": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "To provide opportunities for education to his/her child",
        "explanation": "To provide opportunities for education to his/her child. Fundamental duty (Part IV-A, Article 51-A) incorporated by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976 on the recommendations of the Swaran Singh Committee. It mandates that parents should provide educational opportunities for their children between the ages of six and fourteen years (added by the 86th Constitutional Amendment Act, 2002)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-226",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Citizens are NOT discriminated against on the basis of religion, caste or sex because of:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Right to Freedom",
            "B": "Right against Exploitation",
            "C": "Right to Freedom of Religion",
            "D": "Right to Equality"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Right to Equality",
        "explanation": "Right to Equality. The Fundamental Rights (Part III, Articles 12-35). Right to equality (Articles 14–18). Article 14: Equality before the law. Article 15: Prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex, or place of birth. Article 16: Equality of opportunity in public employment. Article 17: Abolition of untouchability. Article 18: Prohibition of titles, except for military or academic distinctions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-227",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many Fundamental Rights were initially provided in the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Seven",
            "B": "Eight",
            "C": "Nine",
            "D": "Six"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Seven",
        "explanation": "Seven. Currently there are 6 Fundamental Rights in the Indian Constitution. The 44th Amendment of 1978 removed the right to property from the list of fundamental rights, making it a legal right under Article 300A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-228",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "______ of the Constitution of India has provisions for legal enforcement of the fundamental rights.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 32",
            "B": "Article 19",
            "C": "Article 29",
            "D": "Article 28"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 32",
        "explanation": "Article 32. It grants every individual the right to move the Supreme Court for the enforcement of their fundamental rights. The five types of writs that can be issued in India are: Habeas corpus, Mandamus, Certiorari, Prohibition, Quo-warranto."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-229",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Fundamental Rights has been deleted from the original list of fundamental rights provided in the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Right to property",
            "B": "Cultural and educational rights",
            "C": "Right to constitutional remedies",
            "D": "Right to freedom of religion"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Right to property",
        "explanation": "Right to property. It was deleted by the 44th Constitutional amendment act 1978 from the list of Fundamental Rights (FR) and was listed under Article 300A as a legal right in Part XII."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-230",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Fundamental Rights is available for Indians as well as foreigners?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Right to protection of language, script and culture of minorities",
            "B": "Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment",
            "C": "Right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions",
            "D": "Right to elementary education"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Right to elementary education",
        "explanation": "Right to elementary education. Fundamental rights available to both citizens and foreigners (except enemy aliens) include: Article 14, Article 20, Article 21, Article 21A, Article 22, Article 23, Article 24, Article 25, Article 26, Article 27, and Article 28. Fundamental Rights Available Only to Citizens of India: Article 15, Article 16, Article 19, Article 29, and Article 30."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-231",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "All historical monuments have signages with instructions that public should not write on the walls. To which fundamental duty does the given statement belong?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To defend the country and render national service",
            "B": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence",
            "C": "To develop the scientific temper",
            "D": "To promote harmony and spirit of common brotherhood"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence",
        "explanation": "Fundamental Duties outline the responsibilities of every citizen of India. These duties include: (a) to abide by the Constitution and respect its ideals and institutions, the National Flag and the National Anthem; (c) to uphold and protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India; (f) to value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture. Article 49 - Protection of monuments and places and objects of national importance."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-232",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT mentioned in fundamental duties provided under the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To safeguard public property",
            "B": "To develop scientific temper",
            "C": "To join Defence forces",
            "D": "To respect the national flag"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "To join Defence forces",
        "explanation": "To join Defence forces. The Fundamental Duties, listed in Part IVA (Article 51A) of the Indian Constitution, were added by the 42nd Amendment in 1976 based on the Swaran Singh Committee's recommendations. Initially there were 10 fundamental duties, and by the 86th Amendment of 2002 one more fundamental duty (to provide right to education to all children of the age of 6 to 14 years) was added."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-233",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which writ literally means 'what is your authority’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Quo-Warranto",
            "B": "Prohibition",
            "C": "Habeas Corpus",
            "D": "Mandamus"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Quo-Warranto",
        "explanation": "Quo-Warranto. The Supreme Court and High Courts in India have the power to issue writs under Article 32 and Article 226 of the Constitution, respectively. Five types of writs - Habeas Corpus (To have the body); Mandamus (We Command); Prohibition (To forbid); Certiorari (To be certified)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-234",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The original constitution did NOT mention any fundamental duty because:",
        "options": {
            "A": "initially fundamental duties were not expected to be performed",
            "B": "initially fundamental duties were punishable as per the constitution",
            "C": "it was expected that the citizens of the country would perform their duties willingly",
            "D": "it was expected that the citizens of the country would perform their duties forcefully"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "it was expected that the citizens of the country would perform their duties willingly",
        "explanation": "The fundamental duties were incorporated in Part IV-A of our constitution through the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976. At present, there are eleven fundamental duties under article 51 A of the www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-235",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a fundamental duty of an Indian citizen?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To uphold and protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India",
            "B": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence",
            "C": "To vote in public elections",
            "D": "To value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "To vote in public elections",
        "explanation": "To vote in public elections. The 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 added 10 Fundamental Duties to the Indian Constitution, based on the recommendations of the Swaran Singh Committee. The 86th Amendment Act of 2002 introduced the 11th Fundamental Duty, requiring parents or guardians to provide educational opportunities to children aged 6 to 14. These duties are outlined in Article 51A, under Part IV-A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-236",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Abolition of titles is mentioned in which Article of the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 24",
            "B": "Article 18",
            "C": "Article 23",
            "D": "Article 13"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 18",
        "explanation": "Article 18 - Abolition of titles—(1) No title, not being a military or academic distinction, shall be conferred by the State. (2) No citizen of India shall accept any title from any foreign State. Other important Articles: Article 13: Laws inconsistent with or in derogation of the fundamental rights. Article 23: Prohibition of traffic in human beings and forced labour. Article 24: Prohibition of employment of children in factories, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-237",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Article 21 is related to which of the following fundamental rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Freedom to Manage Religious Affairs",
            "B": "Protection of Language, Culture of Minorities",
            "C": "Protection of Life and Personal Liberty",
            "D": "Freedom of Speech"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Protection of Life and Personal Liberty",
        "explanation": "Protection of Life and Personal Liberty. Fundamental Rights (Part III) : Right to Equality (Article 14 - 18), Right to Freedom (Article 19 - 22), Right against Exploitation (23 - 24), Right to Freedom of Religion (Article 25 - 28), Cultural and Educational Rights (Article 29 - 30), Article 31 (now repealed) - Saving of Certain Laws related to property rights, Right to Constitutional Remedies (Article 32)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-238",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "If a person who is arrested, is NOT produced before the Magistrate within 24 hours from the time of arrest, he will be entitled to be released on the writ of ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Habeas Corpus",
            "B": "Prohibition",
            "C": "Quo-warranto",
            "D": "Mandamus"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Habeas Corpus",
        "explanation": "Habeas Corpus. The Supreme Court and High Courts in India have the power to issue writs under Article 32 and Article 226 of the Constitution, respectively. Five types of writs - Habeas Corpus (To have the body); Mandamus (We Command); Prohibition (To forbid); Certiorari (To be certified) and Quo Warranto (By what authority)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-239",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of limited government is a major advancement to protect the _______ of the citizens from the ruling governments.",
        "options": {
            "A": "separation of power",
            "B": "fundamental duties",
            "C": "fundamental rights",
            "D": "check and balance"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "fundamental rights",
        "explanation": "fundamental rights are enshrined in Part III of the Constitution (Articles 12-35). Right to equality (Articles 14–18); Right to freedom (Articles 19–22); Right against exploitation (Articles 23–24); Right to freedom of religion (Articles 25–28); Cultural and educational rights (Articles 29–30); Right to constitutional remedies (Article 32).The Right to property (Article 31) was removed by the 44th Amendment Act, 1978, and is now a legal right under Article 300-A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-240",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following articles guarantees the Right to Equality before the Law and the Right to Equal Protection of the Laws ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 14",
            "B": "Article 16",
            "C": "Article 17",
            "D": "Article 15"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 14",
        "explanation": "Article 14. The right to equality (Articles 14–18) is a fundamental right (Part III , Articles 12-35). Article 15 prohibits discrimination against citizens on the grounds of religion, race, caste, sex, or place of birth. Article 16 provides for equality of opportunity for all citizens in matters of employment. Article 17 abolishes the practice of untouchability in any form."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-241",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The 11th Fundamental Duty was added by which Amendment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "42nd Amendment 1976",
            "B": "86th Amendment 2002",
            "C": "84th Amendment 2000",
            "D": "44th Amendment 1978"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "86th Amendment 2002",
        "explanation": "86th Amendment 2002. Fundamental Duties (Part IV A, Article 51A): The 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 added the first 10 Fundamental Duties to the Indian Constitution, following the recommendation of the Swaran Singh Committee. The 11th Fundamental Duty states that parents and guardians must provide opportunities for education to their children between the ages of six and fourteen."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-242",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that every religious denomination or section shall have the right to own and acquire movable and immovable property?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 26",
            "B": "Article 26",
            "C": "(b) Article 26",
            "D": "(c) Article 26(b) (d) Article 26(a)"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 26",
        "explanation": "Article 26(c). Article 26 of the Constitution of India guarantees the freedom to manage religious affairs as a fundamental right, part of the right to religion outlined in Articles 25 to 28. Articles 26 - This freedom is subject to public order, morality, and health, allowing every religious denomination or any section thereof the right to: (a) establish and maintain institutions for religious and charitable purposes, (b) manage its own affairs in matters of religion, (c) own and acquire movable and immovable property, and (d) administer such property according to law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-243",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘No person shall be prosecuted and punished for the same offence more than once’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 20(3)",
            "B": "Article 20(2)",
            "C": "Article 20(4)",
            "D": "Article 20(1)"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 20(2)",
        "explanation": "Article 20(2). This clause is known as the doctrine of \"double jeopardy,\" which ensures that no individual is tried twice for the same crime. Other clauses: Article 20(1) : This provision ensures that a person cannot be convicted of any offense which was not in force at the time. Article 20(3) ensures that no person accused of an offense shall be compelled to be a witness against themselves."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-244",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Committee had suggested www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity a penalty or punishment for the non - performance of Fundamental Duties ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Indira Gandhi Committee",
            "B": "Morarji Desai Committee",
            "C": "Verma Committee",
            "D": "Swaran Singh Committee"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Swaran Singh Committee",
        "explanation": "Swaran Singh Committee. The Swaran Singh Committee recommended that the duty to pay taxes to be included in the fundamental duties. The committee also recommended that the legislatures should prescribe a law for imposing a penalty for violation of the duties. But these recommendations were not included in Article 51A."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-245",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution clarifies that policies like 'reservation' is not a violation of the right to equality?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 16 (4)",
            "B": "Article 15 (2)",
            "C": "Article 14 (1)",
            "D": "Article 21"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 16 (4)",
        "explanation": "Article 16 (4). Article 15 (2) - No citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, place of birth, be subject to any disability, liability, restriction or condition with regard to. Article 21 - Protection of life and personal liberty."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-246",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the purpose of the Cultural and Educational Rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To promote a particular religion",
            "B": "To protect the language, culture, and religion of the minority communities",
            "C": "To protect the majority community",
            "D": "To prevent exploitation"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "To protect the language, culture, and religion of the minority communities",
        "explanation": "Cultural and Educational Right (Article 29 - 30) : Article 29 - Guarantees the Protection of Interests of Minorities. Article 30 - Guarantees the right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions of their choice."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-247",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is enforceable by the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Preamble",
            "B": "Fundamental rights",
            "C": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "D": "Fundamental duties"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Fundamental rights",
        "explanation": "Fundamental Rights (Part III, Articles 12-35)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-248",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is FALSE about the right to freedom of religion mentioned in the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It provides freedom to manage religious affairs.",
            "B": "It provides freedom of worship.",
            "C": "It is mentioned in Articles 25 to 28.",
            "D": "It mentions that the state has its own religion."
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "It mentions that the state has its own religion.",
        "explanation": "The Right to Freedom of Religion (Fundamental Right under Part III) - Article 25 - Freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion. Article 26 - Freedom to manage religious affairs. Article 27 - Freedom as to payment of taxes for promotion of any particular religion. Article 28 - Freedom as to attendance at religious instruction or religious worship in certain educational institutions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-249",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which statement is FALSE regarding fundamental rights mentioned in the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Only Article 20 and 21 can be suspended during emergency",
            "B": "They are justiciable",
            "C": "Some fundamental rights are negative in nature",
            "D": "Can be suspended during emergency"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Only Article 20 and 21 can be suspended during emergency",
        "explanation": "44th Amendment Act, 1978 limits the scope of Article 359 (suspension of the enforcement of the rights conferred by Part III during emergencies). All fundamental rights except articles 20 and 21 can be suspended only on the basis of National Emergency (Article 352)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-250",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The celebration of Christmas, Eid and Holi in school is an example of making children learn fundamental duties as well. Which of the following fundamental duties advocates about this type of ideals ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To defend the country and render national service",
            "B": "To develop the scientific temper",
            "C": "To safeguard public property and to abjure violence",
            "D": "To promote harmony and spirit of common brotherhood"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "To promote harmony and spirit of common brotherhood",
        "explanation": "Fundamental Duties: Part IV-A of the Indian constitution in Article 51A. Article 51A(e) refers to the duty of every citizen to promote harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood amongst all the people of India. '"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-251",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the aim of fundamental rights mentioned in the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To establish a welfare state",
            "B": "To have an absolute independence",
            "C": "To promote economic justice",
            "D": "To establish political democracy"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "To establish political democracy",
        "explanation": "To establish political democracy. The fundamental rights in the Indian Constitution aim to build a democratic society by safeguarding individual liberty, equality, and protection against discrimination based on race, caste, sex, religion, or birthplace."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-252",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Fundamental duties are ______ and not enforceable by law but are taken into account by the courts while adjudicating any matter.",
        "options": {
            "A": "regulatory",
            "B": "non - statutory",
            "C": "statutory",
            "D": "common"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "statutory",
        "explanation": "Statutory. Fundamental Duties (Part IVA, Article 51A):- Adopted from the Constitution of Russia (erstwhile Soviet Union). Fundamental duties - Non - justiciable in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-253",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution mentions the fundamental duty \"sovereignty, unity and integrity of India\" is mentioned ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 51A",
            "B": "(b) Article 51A (e)",
            "C": "Article 51A (c)",
            "D": "Article 51A (d)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 51A (c)",
        "explanation": "Article 51A(c). The 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 added 10 Fundamental Duties to the Indian Constitution and created Part IVA. Committee Reports"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-254",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The central bank of India or Reserve Bank of India was created before Independence, in the year 1934. The recommendation to create a central bank was made by a commission called:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Dr. Raja Chelliah Committee",
            "B": "Kothari Commission",
            "C": "Narasimham Committee",
            "D": "Hilton Young Commission"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Hilton Young Commission",
        "explanation": "Hilton Young Commission. It is also known as the Royal Commission on Indian Currency and Finance, was established in 1926. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) is India's central bank and regulatory body overseeing the Indian banking system. It manages the control, issuance, and supply of the Indian rupee. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) was established on April 1, 1935, in accordance with the provisions of the www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-255",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which committee recommended Constitutional recognition for the local government bodies in 1989?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ashok Mehta Committee",
            "B": "PK Thungon Committee",
            "C": "Balwant Rai Committee",
            "D": "Verma Committee"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "PK Thungon Committee",
        "explanation": "P.K. Thungan Committee recommended a constitutional amendment for regular elections, specific functions, and funding for local government institutions. Ashok Mehta Committee: It was set up in 1977 by the Janata government, studied the Panchayat Raj system in India. Balwant Rai Mehta Committee: It recommended decentralizing power and functions at the divisional and sub-divisional levels. Justice Verma Committee: It was formed to suggest changes to criminal law for faster trials and tougher punishments for those accused of sexual assault against women."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-256",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following commissions/committees identified the existence of legal provisions for implementation of some of the Fundamental Duties?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Vasantrao Naik Committee",
            "B": "Sarkaria Commission",
            "C": "Rajamannar Commission",
            "D": "Justice Verma Committee"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Justice Verma Committee",
        "explanation": "Justice Verma Committee. The committee was set up in 1999. It identified the existence of following legal provisions - Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act (1971), Protection of Civil Right Act (1955), Representation of People Act (1951), Wildlife Protection Act (1972) and Forest Conservation Act (1980)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-257",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following committees had recommended the inclusion of a chapter on the Fundamental Duties in the Constitution of India and stressed that the citizens should become conscious that, in addition to the enjoyment of rights, they also have certain duties to perform ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "JR Varma Committee (1996)",
            "B": "Ashok Mehta Committee (1977)",
            "C": "Swaran Singh Committee (1976)",
            "D": "Balwant Rai Mehta Committee (1976)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Swaran Singh Committee (1976)",
        "explanation": "Swaran Singh Committee (1976) originally recommended eight Fundamental Duties under Article 51A of the Indian Constitution. However, at the time of incorporation, ten duties were added to Part IV-A by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1976. Initially, there were 10 duties, and one more was added by the 86th Constitutional Amendment Act, 2002, making a total of 11 duties."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-258",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following committees was associated with Industrial Licensing Policy Inquiry?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Hazari Committee",
            "B": "Sen Committee",
            "C": "Gadgil Committee",
            "D": "Dutt Committee"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Dutt Committee",
        "explanation": "Dutt Committee. The Hazari Committee was a committee in India that studied the industrial licensing procedure under the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951. Abhijit Sen Committee (2002) - Long Term Food Policy. The Gadgil commission was formed to study the impact of population pressure, climate change and development activities on the Western Ghats."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-259",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In November 2022, the Supreme Court upheld the 10% reservation of EWS quota. This EWS reservation was granted on the basis of recommendations from which of the following commissions ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sarkaria commission",
            "B": "Kelkar commission",
            "C": "Mandal commission",
            "D": "Sinho commission"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Sinho commission",
        "explanation": "Sinho commission: Constituted in 2005, and submitted its report in 2010. In 2019, the Cabinet decided to amend the Constitution (103rd Amendment) to provide reservation to EWS. Sarkaria Commission (1983) - Reviewed center-state relations. Kelkar Commission (1953) - Also known as the First Backward Classes Commission. Mandal Commission (1979) - The Second Socially and Educationally Backward Classes Commission."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-260",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following persons was appointed Chairman of the Second National Judicial Pay Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Justice PV Reddi",
            "B": "Justice JS Verma",
            "C": "Justice R Basant",
            "D": "Justice AS Anand"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Justice PV Reddi",
        "explanation": "Justice PV Reddi. The second National judicial Pay Commission was formed in 2017 due to the supreme court’s order in the all India judges association case, under article 32, i.e., constitutional remedies. Justice Verma Committee was constituted to recommend amendments to the Criminal Law so as to provide for quicker trial and enhanced punishment for criminals accused of committing sexual assault against women. The Committee submitted its report on January 23, 2013."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-261",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which report is NOT associated with Fundamental Rights?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Tej Bahadur Sapru Report",
            "B": "Motilal Nehru Report",
            "C": "Sarkaria Commission Report",
            "D": "JB Kripalani Report"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Sarkaria Commission Report",
        "explanation": "Sarkaria Commission Report - This Commission is to examine and review the working of the existing arrangements between the Union and States as per the Constitution of India. Tej Bahadur Sapru Report (1945) - It related to political and civil rights of the minorities."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-262",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Rangarajan Committee is associated with _______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Election reforms",
            "B": "Educational reform",
            "C": "Environmental protection",
            "D": "Estimation of poverty"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Estimation of poverty",
        "explanation": "Estimation of poverty. Rangarajan Committee - To Review the Methodology for Measurement of Poverty in the country constituted by the Planning Commission in June 2012 has submitted its report on 30th June 2014. As per the report submitted by C Rangarajan Committee: Persons spending below Rs. 47 a day in cities should be considered poor. Committee related to poverty: Planning Commission Expert Group (1962), VM Dandekar and N Rath committee (1971), Y.K. Alagh Committee (1979), Lakdawala Committee (1993), Suresh Tendulkar Committee (2005)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-263",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following commissions recommended that “the appointment of Governor should be non - partisan” ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Fazal Ali Commission",
            "B": "Rajmannar commission",
            "C": "Sarkaria commission",
            "D": "Mandal commission"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Sarkaria commission",
        "explanation": "Sarkaria commission (1983). www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity The States Reorganisation Commission (Fazal Ali Commission, 1953). Rajmannar commission set up by the then DMK Government of Tamil Nadu in 1969 under the Chairmanship of Dr P.V. Rajamanar."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-264",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Constitution Review Commission chaired by______recommended some initiatives to be taken by the government for successful implementation of Fundamental Duties.",
        "options": {
            "A": "PK Joshi",
            "B": "MN Venkatachaliah",
            "C": "UC Banerjee",
            "D": "Michael G Aguinaldo"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "MN Venkatachaliah",
        "explanation": "MN Venkatachaliah Commission was set up by Government resolution in 2000 to Review the Working of the Constitution. He got Padma Vibhushan In 2004. Justice U.C.Banerjee headed the Commission report on Godhra incident."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-265",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many members are there in the Committee on Public Undertakings in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "22",
            "B": "15",
            "C": "35",
            "D": "30"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "22",
        "explanation": "22. Financial Committees:- Public Accounts Committee - 1921, Members (22) (15 from Lok Sabha and 7 from Rajya Sabha), Term of Office (One year), Function - to examine the annual audit reports of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India (CAG). Estimates Committee (Post Independence) - 1950, Members (30) All from Lok Sabha , Term of Office (One Year), Function - to examine the estimates included in the budget. Committee on Public Undertakings – 1964, Members-22 (15 from Lok Sabha and 7 from Rajya Sabha), Term of Office (One Year), Function – to examine the reports and accounts of the Public Sector Undertakings."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-266",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Commission recommended 27% reservation for OBC candidates in all levels of government services ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sarkaria Commission",
            "B": "Mandal Commission",
            "C": "Balwant Commission",
            "D": "Kothari Commission"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Mandal Commission",
        "explanation": "The Mandal Commission (Second Backward Class Commission) recommended that members of OBCs be given 27 percent reservations for jobs under the Central government and public sector undertakings. This commission was established in India in 1979 by the Janata Party government under Prime Minister Morarji Desai. It was headed by BP Mandal. Parliament"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-267",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following options is the legislative organ of the Union government?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Judiciary",
            "B": "Legislative assembly",
            "C": "Executive",
            "D": "Parliament"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "explanation": "Parliament. The Indian Parliament is a bicameral legislature, consisting of two houses : the Lok Sabha (House of the People) and the Rajya Sabha (Council of States), along with the President. The three organs of the Union Government of India are the legislative, executive (Implements the laws enacted by the legislature), and judiciary (interprets the laws made by Parliament)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-268",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a device of parliamentary proceedings?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Half - an - hour discussion",
            "B": "Zero - hour discussion",
            "C": "Two - hour (short) discussion",
            "D": "Full - day discussion"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Full - day discussion",
        "explanation": "Full-day discussion. In parliamentary proceedings, there are various devices used to facilitate discussions and manage time effectively. These include: Half-an-hour discussion - A device used to discuss matters of urgent public importance. It usually lasts for 30 minutes. Zero-hour discussion - A device where members can raise issues without prior notice, typically after the Question Hour, which allows for unscheduled discussions. Two-hour (short) discussion - This is also a formal discussion where specific issues are debated for two hours."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-269",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who has the power to regulate the right of citizenship in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Parliament",
            "B": "President",
            "C": "Supreme Court",
            "D": "Governor"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "explanation": "Parliament. Citizenship (Part II, Articles 5 to 11) : Article 5 - Citizenship at the commencement of the Constitution. Article 6 - Rights of citizenship of certain persons who have migrated to India from Pakistan. Article 11 - Parliament to regulate the right of citizenship by law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-270",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The parliamentary standing committees have a tenure of _____ years.",
        "options": {
            "A": "four",
            "B": "two",
            "C": "three",
            "D": "one"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "one",
        "explanation": "one. Parliamentary committees are of two types—Standing Committees and Ad Hoc Committees. Standing Committees are permanent and function on a continuous basis. In contrast, Ad Hoc Committees are temporary and cease to exist once they complete the task assigned to them. Examples - The Joint Committee on Bofors Contract and the Joint Committee on Fertilizer Pricing."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-271",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding State Legislatures? A. Notwithstanding anything in part XVII, but subject to the provisions of Article 348, business in the Legislature of a State shall be transacted in the official language or languages of the State or in Hindi or in English. B. The Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or Chairman of the Legislative Council can permit any member to speak in his mother tongue. C. Only the Supreme Court is entitled to inquire into the proceedings of the State Legislature.",
        "options": {
            "A": "B and C only",
            "B": "A and C only",
            "C": "A, B and C",
            "D": "A and B only"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "A and B only",
        "explanation": "A and B only. State Legislature is mentioned in Chapter III of Part VI (The States) of the Indian Constitution. Related Articles: Article 178 - The Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly. Article 179 - Vacation and resignation of, and removal from, the offices of Speaker and Deputy Speaker. Article 180 - Power of the Deputy Speaker or other person to perform the duties of the office of, or to act as, Speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-272",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Jammu and Kashmir Legislative Council abolished?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2018",
            "B": "2020",
            "C": "2019",
            "D": "2017"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "2019",
        "explanation": "2019. The Jammu & Kashmir Legislative Council was abolished through the Jammu and Kashmir Reorganisation Act, 2019, which reduced the State of Jammu and Kashmir to the Union Territories of Jammu and Kashmir and Ladakh. The Act also repealed Article 370, which had granted Jammu and Kashmir unique status."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-273",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many Members of Parliament were elected to the 17th Lok Sabha from Odisha?",
        "options": {
            "A": "22",
            "B": "24",
            "C": "21",
            "D": "20"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "21",
        "explanation": "21.The 2024 Indian general election was held in Odisha in 4 phases from 13 May 2024 to 1 June 2024 to elect 21 members of the 18th Lok Sabha. Bharatiya Janata Party clean sweeped the state by winning 20 out of 21 seats."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-274",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "One-third of the members of the State Legislature Council retire every _____years.",
        "options": {
            "A": "sixth",
            "B": "fourth",
            "C": "fifth",
            "D": "second"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "second",
        "explanation": "Second. The Legislative Council (Vidhan Parishad) has a permanent structure and is not subject to dissolution. The Legislative Assembly (Vidhan Sabha) of a state consists of not more than 500 and not less than 60 members. It may be dissolved after five years or earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-275",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When a non-minister proposes a bill, it is called :",
        "options": {
            "A": "Money Bill",
            "B": "Government Bill",
            "C": "Private Member’s Bill",
            "D": "Non - Money Bill"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Private Member’s Bill",
        "explanation": "Private Member’s Bill. It can be introduced only on Fridays. Money Bill: This type of bill deals specifically with financial matters, such as taxation or government spending. Money bills are introduced by ministers only in the Lok Sabha. Government Bill: A bill introduced by a minister on behalf of the government. It typically reflects the government's policies."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-276",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many Lok Sabha seats are there for the state of Meghalaya?",
        "options": {
            "A": "One",
            "B": "Two",
            "C": "Three",
            "D": "Four"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Two",
        "explanation": "Two. Meghalaya has two Lok Sabha seats, namely Shillong and Tura. The state also has one Rajya Sabha seat. Additionally, Meghalaya has 60 legislative assembly seats. Other states and their Lok Sabha seats: Manipur (2), Nagaland (1), Mizoram (1), Assam (14), Arunachal Pradesh (2), Tripura (2), Sikkim (1)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-277",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the first speaker of the Lok Sabha after India’s Independence?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ganesh V Mavalankar",
            "B": "Meira Kumar",
            "C": "M Ananthasayanam",
            "D": "MA Ayyangar"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Ganesh V Mavalankar",
        "explanation": "Ganesh V Mavalankar was the Chairman of the Committee on the Functions of the Constituent Assembly of India. Ganesh Vasudev Mavalankar has been conferred the title of 'Father of Lok Sabha' by Jawaharlal Nehru. M. A. Ayyangar was the first deputy speaker of the Lok Sabha. Meira Kumar was the first woman speaker of Lok Sabha (2009 - 2014)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-278",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following options is INCORRECT? In order to become a member of Vidhan Sabha, a person must:",
        "options": {
            "A": "have his/her name in the voters’ list",
            "B": "have attained the age of 21 years",
            "C": "be a citizen of India",
            "D": "not hold any office of profit"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "have attained the age of 21 years",
        "explanation": "The minimum age to be a member of the Legislative Assembly ( Vidhan Sabha) is 25 years. Legislative Assembly of a state consists of not more than 500 and not less than 60 members (Legislative Assembly of Sikkim has 32 members vide Article 371F of the Constitution) chosen by direct election from territorial constituencies in the state."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-279",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many state Legislative Council members are elected by graduates of three years standing and residing within the state?",
        "options": {
            "A": "th",
            "B": "th",
            "C": "th",
            "D": "rd 1 4 1 6 1 12 1 3"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "th",
        "explanation": "1/12th. In the legislative council, members are elected as follows: One-sixth by the governor from individuals with knowledge in science, art, literature, the co-operative movement, and social service; One-third by local body members (corporations, municipalities, and Zila Parishads); one-third shall be elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly of the State from amongst persons who are not members of the Assembly; one-twelfth by graduates residing in the state for three years; and One twelfth are elected by teachers who had spent at least three years in teaching in educational institutions within the state not lower than secondary schools, including colleges and universities."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-280",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Members of the Rajya Sabha are elected for a term of how many years ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "5 years",
            "B": "3 years",
            "C": "6 years",
            "D": "4 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "6 years",
        "explanation": "6 years. The Rajya Sabha is a permanent body and is not subject to dissolution. However, one-third of its members retire every two years. The Vice-President of India serves as the ex-officio Chairman of the Rajya Sabha. The House has a maximum of 250 members, with 238 elected members from states and union territories, and 12 nominated by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-281",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who elects the Presiding Officer (the speaker) in the State legislature?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Council of Minsters",
            "B": "Members of Vidhan Sabha",
            "C": "Member of Vidhan Parishad",
            "D": "Chief Minster"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Members of Vidhan Sabha",
        "explanation": "Members of Vidhan Sabha. There is a Legislative Assembly (Vidhan Sabha) in every State. It represents the people of the State. The members of Vidhan Sabha are directly elected by people on the basis of universal adult franchise. The Speaker presides over the meetings of the House and conducts its proceedings. He maintains order in the House, allows the members to ask questions and speak. Article 178 - The Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-282",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The First hour of a sitting of the House allotted for asking and answering of questions is called as __________ . SSC Stenographer 12/10/2023 (Afternoon)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Censure motion",
            "B": "Zero hour",
            "C": "Privilege motion",
            "D": "Question hour"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Question hour",
        "explanation": "Question hour. Censure motion - A motion to express disapproval of the conduct of the government or a minister. Zero hour - The first hour of a sitting of the House, when MPs can raise matters of urgent public importance without notice. Privilege motion - A motion to protect the privileges of the House or its members."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-283",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A money bill under Article 111 of the Constitution of India, presented to the President for assent, has to be endorsed by a Certificate of the ________signed by him/her that it is a money bill.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Secretary General of the Lok Sabha",
            "B": "Secretary General of the Rajya Sabha",
            "C": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
            "D": "Deputy Chairman of the Rajya Sabha"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
        "explanation": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha. Articles related to Money Bill: Article 107 - Provisions as to introduction and www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity passing of Bills. Article 108 - Joint sitting of both Houses in certain cases. Article 109 - Special procedure in respect of Money Bills. Article 110 - Definition of “Money Bills”. Article 197 - Restriction on powers of Legislative Council as to Bills other than Money Bills."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-284",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "After how many days of absence from Parliament without permission will a Member of Parliament be disqualified?",
        "options": {
            "A": "60 days",
            "B": "30 days",
            "C": "50 days",
            "D": "20 days"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "60 days",
        "explanation": "60 days. Disqualifications of Members of parliament : Article 101 - Vacation of seats. Article 102 - Disqualifications for membership. Article 103 - Decision on questions as to disqualifications of members. Article 104 - Penalty for sitting and voting before making oath or affirmation under article 99 or when not qualified or when disqualified."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-285",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the bicameral legislature of the Indian Constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is a legislative body with four houses.",
            "B": "It is a legislative body with two houses.",
            "C": "It is a legislative body with one house.",
            "D": "It is a legislative body with three houses."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "It is a legislative body with two houses.",
        "explanation": "The bicameral legislature of the Indian Constitution refers to a legislative body with two houses: the Lok Sabha (House of the People) and the Rajya Sabha (Council of States). Lok Sabha: The lower house, consisting of directly elected members. Rajya Sabha: The upper house, consisting of representatives elected by the members of the state legislative assemblies and by members of the Lok Sabha, along with nominated members."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-286",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the most powerful weapon that enables the Parliament to ensure executive accountability ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Approval or refusal of laws",
            "B": "The no-confidence motion",
            "C": "Confirmation of treaties",
            "D": "Deliberation and discussion"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The no-confidence motion",
        "explanation": "The no-confidence motion. It moved in the Lok Sabha (and not in the Rajya Sabha) to test the confidence of the government. It needs the support of 50 members to be admitted. Other ways to ensure executive accountability: Question-hour, zero hour, calling attention motion, adjournment motion, censure motion, and other discussions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-287",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the maximum time gap between two sessions of the State Legislature ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Three months",
            "B": "Two months",
            "C": "Six months",
            "D": "One year"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Six months",
        "explanation": "Six months. Article 174 (1) - The Governor shall from time to time summon the House or each House of the State Legislature to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit. Article 85 (1) of the Constitution empowers the President to summon and prorogue either house of Parliament or to dissolve the Lok Sabha. Three types of Sessions in the Parliament of India: Budget session (February - May), Monsoon session (July - September) and Winter session (November - December) are held in a calendar year."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-288",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the first general election for Lok Sabha held in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1950 - 51",
            "B": "1949 - 50",
            "C": "1948 - 49",
            "D": "1951 - 52"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1951 - 52",
        "explanation": "1951-52. First Lok Sabha: Jawaharlal Nehru (Indian National Congress) became India’s first democratically elected Prime Minister. 18th Lok Sabha Election (2024): Narendra Modi (Bharatiya Janata Party) became Prime Minister. Lok Sabha Seat: 543 Parliamentary Constituencies (At present). First Panchayati Raj Election in India was held on 2nd of Oct 1959 in the Nagaur district of Rajasthan."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-289",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How long can a person remain a minister without being a member of either House of the State Legislature ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "15 days",
            "B": "6 months",
            "C": "1 year",
            "D": "2 months"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "6 months",
        "explanation": "6 months. Articles 163-164 deals with the Council of Ministers (CoM) in states. The articles 75 (5) and 164 (4) state that a minister who for any period of six consecutive months is not a member of either house of Parliament or state legislature respectively shall cease to be such minister at the expiration of that period."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-290",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is/are correctly matched regarding the terminology used in the Parliament? A. Appropriation Bill - A Money Bill passed for providing for the withdrawal or appropriation from and out of the Consolidated Fund of India B. Demand for Grants - Earmarking of budgetary allocation for meeting only planned expenditure of a Ministry/Department C. Short Duration Discussion - For raising a discussion on a matter of urgent public importance for which a notice has to be given by a Member and supported by 50 Members.",
        "options": {
            "A": "A, B and C",
            "B": "B and C only",
            "C": "A only",
            "D": "A and C only"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "A only",
        "explanation": "A only. Demand for Grants is the form in which estimates of expenditure from the Consolidated Fund (included in the annual financial statement and required to be voted upon in the Lok Sabha) are submitted in pursuance of Article 113 of the Constitution. Short Duration Discussion is a procedural device to enable members to raise discussion on matters of urgent public importance without a formal motion on a matter of urgent public importance. The Speaker can allot two days in a week for such discussions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-291",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following can make provisions for Ancillary powers of the Supreme Court?",
        "options": {
            "A": "President of India",
            "B": "Law Commission of India",
            "C": "Minister of Law & Justice",
            "D": "Parliament of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Parliament of India",
        "explanation": "Parliament of India. Ancillary powers of the Supreme Court (Article 140): The Parliament, through legislation, can grant the Supreme Court additional powers that are in line with the Constitution's provisions. These extra powers should help the Court better fulfill its constitutional jurisdiction. President of India : Articles 52 - 62 (Part V), Parliament of India : Articles 79-122 (Part V), Supreme Court : Articles 124-147 (Part V)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-292",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In India, during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly or Council, if there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of the ________ to adjourn the House or suspend the meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Chairman/Governor",
            "B": "Speaker/Chairman",
            "C": "Governor/Chief Minister",
            "D": "Speaker/Chief Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Speaker/Chairman",
        "explanation": "Speaker/Chairman. Article 100 - Voting in Houses, power of www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Houses to act notwithstanding vacancies and quorum. Quorum - It refers to the number of members that must be present for a house meeting to take place. Article 189 (3) - The quorum to constitute a meeting of the state legislature shall be ten members or one-tenth of the total number of members of the house whichever is greater."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-293",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A Money Bill should be returned to the Lok Sabha within ___ days by Rajya Sabha, either with recommendations or without recommendations.",
        "options": {
            "A": "8",
            "B": "21",
            "C": "14",
            "D": "10"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "14",
        "explanation": "14. Money Bill (Article 110) - It is involved with tax collection, public expense bills, and other significant costs associated with running the government. Money Bill Types - Financial Bill and Appropriation Bill. The Speaker has the authority to determine whether or not a specific bill is a money bill."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-294",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Archana wishes to contest for Lok Sabha elections in India. What is the maximum limit of constituencies that can she contest?",
        "options": {
            "A": "One",
            "B": "Four",
            "C": "Three",
            "D": "Two"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Two",
        "explanation": "Two. Candidates were allowed to contest more than Two seats until 1996. As per, Section 33 (7) of the RPA (Representation of the People Act) 1951, one candidate can contest from a maximum of two constituencies. Section 70 bars candidates from representing two constituencies in the Lok Sabha/state, which means candidates have to vacate one seat in case of winning both the seats."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-295",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the term of the State legislative assembly in India as per Indian constitution ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "3 years",
            "B": "5 years",
            "C": "4 years",
            "D": "7 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "5 years",
        "explanation": "5 years. State Legislature (Article 168 - 212) comprises Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council. Legislative Council members are elected for a term of 6 years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-296",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Lok Sabha (House of the People) was duly constituted for the first time on _______ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "26 April 1950",
            "B": "17 April 1952",
            "C": "18 January 1950",
            "D": "20 April 1951"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "17 April 1952",
        "explanation": "17 April 1952. The First Lok Sabha lasted for a full five years tenure and was dissolved on 4 April 1957. Article 79 of the Constitution deals with the Parliament consisting of the President, Lok Sabha, and Rajya Sabha. First Lok Sabha Speaker - GV Mavlankar."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-297",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who runs the government at the national level under the parliamentary system?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The President and Council of Ministers",
            "B": "The Prime Minister and Council of Ministers",
            "C": "The Prime Minister",
            "D": "The President"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The Prime Minister and Council of Ministers",
        "explanation": "The Prime Minister and the Council of Ministers run the Parliamentary system (cabinet system or the Responsible government, Prime Minister Model) at the National level. Articles 74 and 75 (Part V) provide the parliamentary system for the centre. Article 163 and 164 (Part VI) provides the parliamentary system for the states."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-298",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Constitution provides for reservation of seats in the Lok Sabha and State Legislative Assemblies for the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "scheduled tribes",
            "B": "other backward classes",
            "C": "differently abled",
            "D": "women"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "scheduled tribes",
        "explanation": "Scheduled tribes. Article 366(25) of the Constitution deals with Scheduled Tribes. There are over 705 tribes which have been notified. The largest number of tribal communities are found in Odisha. Related Committees to Schedule tribes: Xaxa Committee (2013), Bhuria Commission (2002-2004), Lokur Committee (1965). The Fifth Schedule of the Constitution deals with Administration and Control of Scheduled Areas and Scheduled Tribes in states other than Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram. The Sixth Schedule deals with the administration of the tribal areas in Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-299",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a kind of question related to Indian Parliamentary Proceedings ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Starred Question",
            "B": "Unstarred Question",
            "C": "Short Notice Question",
            "D": "Long Notice Question"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Long Notice Question",
        "explanation": "Long Notice Question. Starred Questions are those for which an oral answer is expected. Non-starred questions are those for which a written reply is expected. Short notice questions are those which are asked on matters of urgent public importance and can be asked on a shorter notice, less than 10 days."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-300",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is called 'the temple of the country's democracy'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Raj Ghat",
            "B": "Supreme Court",
            "C": "Ashok Pillar",
            "D": "Parliament"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "explanation": "Parliament (Article 79) consists of the President (Article 52), Council of States (Article 80 - Rajya Sabha) and House of the People (Article 81 - Lok Sabha)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-301",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The state legislative assembly has a strength of ____, with exceptions for smaller states.",
        "options": {
            "A": "600 to 1000",
            "B": "60 to 500",
            "C": "50 to 400",
            "D": "10 to 100"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "60 to 500",
        "explanation": "60 and 500 members . However an exception may be granted in the states of Goa, Sikkim, Mizoram, and the union territory of Puducherry which have fewer than 60 members. Maximum seats (Uttar Pradesh; 403) and least number of seats (Puducherry; 30)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-302",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "According to the Indian Constitution, the House of People shall consist of not more than ______ members to represent the Union territories.",
        "options": {
            "A": "thirty",
            "B": "twenty",
            "C": "fifteen",
            "D": "Thirty-five"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "twenty",
        "explanation": "Twenty. The Lok Sabha is composed of representatives of people chosen by direct election on the basis of adult suffrage. The maximum strength of the House envisaged by the Constitution is now 550 (530 members to represent States, 20 to represent Union Territories)"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-303",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many organs of government are there according to the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Two",
            "B": "Four",
            "C": "One",
            "D": "Three"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Three",
        "explanation": "Three Organs: the Legislature consists of the President and two Houses, known as Council of States (Rajya Sabha) and House of the People (Lok Sabha), the Executive consists of the President, the Vice-President, and the Council of Ministers with the Prime www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Minister as the head to aid and advise the President. and the Judiciary consists of the Supreme Court, High Court, District Court or Subordinate Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-304",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "__________ is a motion moved by a member to cut short the debate on a matter before the House.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Closure",
            "B": "No-Confidence",
            "C": "Privilege",
            "D": "Censure"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Closure",
        "explanation": "‘Closure Motion’ . No Confidence Motion’ also called as Motion of No Confidence: A Vote of No Confidence is a formal proposal in Lok Sabha to evoke a decision of the house."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-305",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "According to the Indian Constitution, what is the tenure of the members of the State Legislative Council in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "10 years",
            "B": "3 years",
            "C": "4 years",
            "D": "6 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "6 years",
        "explanation": "6 years. It is a permanent body and is not subject to dissolution. The tenure of a Member of the Legislative Council (MLC) is six years, with one-third of the members retiring every two years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-306",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who has the power to abolish or create a legislative council in the state?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Parliament",
            "B": "High court of the concerned State",
            "C": "President",
            "D": "Chief minister of the concerned state"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "explanation": "Parliament. According to the Article 169 of the Constitution of India, the Parliament of India can create or abolish the State Legislative Council of a state if that state's legislature passes a resolution for that with a special majority."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-307",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a feature of parliamentary government in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Membership of the ministers in the legislature,",
            "B": "Undissolvable lower house",
            "C": "Presence of nominal and real executives",
            "D": "Collective responsibility of the executive to the legislature"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Undissolvable lower house",
        "explanation": "Undissolvable lower house. Features of Parliamentary Government : Nominal and Real Executives, Double Membership, Collective Responsibility, Secrecy of procedure, Prime Ministerial Leadership, Majority Party Rule, Bicameral Legislature, Political Homogeneity, No fixed term."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-308",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "An alliance formed by political parties after elections when no party has been able to get adequate seats to form a clear majority is called_____.",
        "options": {
            "A": "coalition",
            "B": "appropriation",
            "C": "allegiance",
            "D": "prorogation"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "coalition",
        "explanation": "A coalition government is a form of government in which political parties cooperate to form a government. Appropriation is when money is set aside for a specific and particular purpose or purposes. Prorogation means the termination of a session of the House by an order made by the President under Article 85(2)(a) of the Constitution. Allegiance, the tie that binds an individual to another individual or institution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-309",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The period between prorogation of Parliament and re-assembly in a new session is called______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "adjournment",
            "B": "recess",
            "C": "dissolution",
            "D": "cut motion"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "recess",
        "explanation": "Recess. An adjournment suspends the work in a sitting for a specified time, which may be hours, days or weeks. A dissolution ends the very life of the existing House, and a new House is constituted after general elections are held. Cut motion is a power given to the members of the Lok Sabha that enables its members to oppose any demand in a Finance Bill proposed by a government"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-310",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In the absence of the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha, who presides over the joint sitting of the two houses of Parliament?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Chairman of Rajya Sabha",
            "B": "Any senior member of Rajya Sabha",
            "C": "Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha",
            "D": "Any senior member of Lok Sabha"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha",
        "explanation": "Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha. Article 93 - The Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the House of the People . Article 95 - Power of the Deputy Speaker or other person to perform the duties of the office of, or to act as, Speaker. Article 96 - The Speaker or the Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution for his removal from office is under consideration."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-311",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The salary and allowances of leaders of opposition in parliament are governed by the Act passed for the first time by the parliament in the year ______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1972",
            "B": "1982",
            "C": "1977",
            "D": "1979"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1977",
        "explanation": "1977. Second Schedule of the Indian Constitution deals with the provisions in relation to allowances, privileges, emoluments of : The President of India, Governors of Indian States, Speaker of Lok Sabha & Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha etc. The leader of the largest Opposition party having not less than one-tenth of the seats of the total strength of the House is recognized as the leader of the Opposition in that House opposition cabinet. President, Vice President and Prime Minister"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-312",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a condition for the President’s office in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "He shall not be entitled, without payment of rent, to use his official residence",
            "B": "He shall not be a member of either House of the Parliament.",
            "C": "The allowances shall not be diminished during his term of office.",
            "D": "He shall not hold any office of profit."
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "He shall not be entitled, without payment of rent, to use his official residence",
        "explanation": "Article 59 of the Constitution of India outlines the conditions for the office of the President of India. Article 59 (3) - The President shall be entitled without payment of rent to the use of his official residences and shall be also entitled to such emoluments, allowances and privileges as may be determined by Parliament by law."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-313",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India expressly provides that the President is eligible for re-election?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 58",
            "B": "Article 56",
            "C": "Article 59",
            "D": "Article 57"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 57",
        "explanation": "Article 57. Important articles related to the President of India : Article 52 - The President of India. Article 53 - Executive power of the Union. Article 54 - Election of President. Article 55 - Manner of election of President. Article 56 - Term of office of President. Article 58 - Qualifications for election as President. Article 59 - Conditions of President’s office. Article 60 - Oath or affirmation by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-314",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In the state legislative assembly, the Money bill can be introduced with the prior permission of __________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Governor",
            "B": "Auditor General",
            "C": "Finance Minister",
            "D": "CAG"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. Money Bills in State Legislatures : A Money Bill is a special type of financial bill that deals with matters like taxation, borrowing, or expenditure from the state's Consolidated Fund. Article 198 of the Constitution of India deals with the special procedure for money bills in state legislatures. Article 148 : Provision for the appointment of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India (CAG) by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-315",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per article 123, the ordinance making power is the most important legislative power of ____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "President",
            "B": "Rajya Sabha",
            "C": "Legislative council",
            "D": "Chief Justice of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "President",
        "explanation": "President. Article 123 of the Indian Constitution allows the President to issue ordinances when Parliament is not in session, with approval required within six weeks of reassembly. The maximum life of an ordinance is six months and six weeks. Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed issued the most ordinances in India. Article 213 : Power of Governor to promulgate Ordinances during recess of Legislature."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-316",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India provides that ‘there shall be a Vice President of India’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 61",
            "B": "Article 63",
            "C": "Article 65",
            "D": "Article 62"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 63",
        "explanation": "Article 63. The Vice President of India is the second-highest constitutional office in India, after the President. Important Articles related to Vice President: Article 64 - The Vice-President to be ex officio Chairman of the Council of States. Article 65 - The Vice-President to act as President or to discharge his functions during casual vacancies in the office, or during the absence, of President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-317",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many members are nominated by the President to the Rajya Sabha?",
        "options": {
            "A": "12",
            "B": "10",
            "C": "20",
            "D": "15"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "12",
        "explanation": "12. This right is granted to the President under the Fourth Schedule (Articles 4(1) and 80(2)) of the Constitution of India. Every two years, one - third of the members retire, and at the beginning of every third year, vacancies are filled through fresh elections and presidential nominations."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-318",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The ________ of every state unfurls the flag in its capital on the Republic Day.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Judge of High Court",
            "B": "Chief Minister",
            "C": "Governor",
            "D": "Speaker"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor is the constitutional head of a state in India, appointed by the President. They represent the central government at the state level. Article 153 - Governors of States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-319",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Articles states that the Prime Minister should be appointed by the President?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 71",
            "B": "Article 66",
            "C": "Article 75",
            "D": "Article 62"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Article 75",
        "explanation": "Article 75. Article 62 - Time of holding the election to fill the vacancy in the office of President and the term of office of the person elected to fill the casual vacancy. Article 66 - Election of Vice-President. Article 71 - Matters relating to, or connected with, the election of a President or Vice-President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-320",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is the most controversial Article in the Indian Constitution, which provides for President’s rule in any state?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 358",
            "B": "Article 356",
            "C": "Article 360",
            "D": "Article 352"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 356",
        "explanation": "Article 356. Other Articles : Article 352 - Proclamation of Emergency. Article 358 - Suspension of provisions of article 19 during emergencies. Article 360 - Provisions as to financial emergency."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-321",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is considered the highest law officer of the state in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Advocate general",
            "B": "Attorney general",
            "C": "Chief justice of high court",
            "D": "Auditor general"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Advocate general",
        "explanation": "Advocate general. It is a Constitutional post and its authority is mentioned in article 165 of the Indian Constitution. Appointment: The Governor of each State shall appoint a person qualified to be a High Court Judge as the Advocate-General for the State. Term and Remuneration: The Advocate-General holds office at the pleasure of the Governor and receives remuneration as determined by the Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-322",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article deals with the election of the President ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 72",
            "B": "Article 54",
            "C": "Article 74",
            "D": "Article 66"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 54",
        "explanation": "Article 54 - The President shall be elected by the members of an electoral college consisting of: (a) the elected members of both Houses of Parliament; and (b) the elected members of the Legislative Assemblies of the States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-323",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per article 158, the Governor shall NOT be a member of either House of Parliament or of a House of the Legislature of any State specified in ___________ Schedule.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Seventh",
            "B": "Fifth",
            "C": "First",
            "D": "Third"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "First",
        "explanation": "First. If a member of either House of Parliament or of a House of the Legislature of any such State be appointed Governor, he shall be deemed to have vacated his seat in that House on the date on which he enters upon his office as Governor. First Schedule - The list of names of states and union territories and their extent and territorial jurisdictions."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-324",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution deals with the election of the Vice President?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part IV",
            "B": "Part III",
            "C": "Part VI",
            "D": "Part V"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Part V",
        "explanation": "Part V (Article 52- 151). Article 66 - Election of Vice President. The Vice-President shall be elected by the members of an electoral college consisting of the members of both Houses of Parliament in accordance with the system of proportional representation by means of the single transferable vote and the voting at such election shall be by secret ballot."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-325",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following was the shortest-serving Prime Minister of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Chandra Shekhar",
            "B": "Gulzarilal Nanda",
            "C": "Charan Singh",
            "D": "Atal Bihari Vajpayee"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Gulzarilal Nanda",
        "explanation": "Gulzarilal Nanda www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity was an Indian politician and economist specializing in labor issues. He served as the Acting Prime Minister of India twice, for 13 days each, following the deaths of Jawaharlal Nehru in 1964 and Lal Bahadur Shastri in 1966. Chandra Shekhar, known as Jananayak, was Prime Minister from 10 November 1990 to 21 June 1991. Chaudhuri Charan Singh briefly served as Prime Minister from 1979 to 1980. Atal Bihari Vajpayee, an Indian politician and poet, was Prime Minister first for 13 days in 1996, then for 13 months from 1998 to 1999, and finally for a full term from 1999 to 2004."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-326",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In case the President is satisfied with the Governor’s report, he may declare President’s Rule under Article 356 but such proclamation is initially for a period of ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "two months",
            "B": "one month",
            "C": "six months",
            "D": "three months"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "six months",
        "explanation": "Six months. Article 356 allows the President to issue a proclamation if a state's government cannot function according to the Constitution. The President can act based on the governor's report or independently. This proclamation must be approved by both Houses of Parliament within two months. It can be extended for a maximum of three years, with parliamentary approval every six months."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-327",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Among the following, which is not a qualification for membership in the Vidhan Sabha",
        "options": {
            "A": "Not hold any office of profit",
            "B": "Have attained the age of 25 Years",
            "C": "Citizen of India",
            "D": "Knowledge of Politics"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Knowledge of Politics",
        "explanation": "Knowledge of Politics. The Legislative Assembly, also known as the Vidhan Sabha, consists of a maximum of 500 members and a minimum of 60. Its tenure is five years, but the Governor can dissolve it before the completion of the period."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-328",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The minimum strength of the Council of Ministers in a state as per the Indian Constitution is ________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "12 persons",
            "B": "13 persons",
            "C": "15 persons",
            "D": "14 persons"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "12 persons",
        "explanation": "12 persons. As per the Constitution (91st Amendment) Act, 2003, clause 1A was inserted into Article 164, which states: \"The total number of Ministers, including the Chief Minister, in the Council of Ministers of a State shall not exceed 15% of the total number of members of the Legislative Assembly of that State.\""
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-329",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who has the power to prorogue the House or either House of State Legislature from time to time ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Speaker",
            "B": "Governor",
            "C": "Chief Minister",
            "D": "Chairman"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. According to Article 174 (1) The Governor shall from time to time summon the House or each House of the Legislature of the State to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit, but six months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one session and the date appointed for its first sitting in the next session. Article 174 (2): The Governor may from time to time—(a) prorogue the House or either House; (b) dissolve the Legislative Assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-330",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is considered as the ‘linchpin of the Government’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "President",
            "B": "Vice - President",
            "C": "Chief Justice of the Supreme Court",
            "D": "Prime Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Prime Minister",
        "explanation": "The Prime Minister acts as a link between the Council of Ministers on the one hand and the President as well as the Parliament on the other. It is this role of the Prime Minister which led Pt. Nehru described him as 'the linchpin of Government'."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-331",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which option is NOT correct in case of appointment of a Governor ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Citizen of India",
            "B": "Cannot hold any office of profit during his tenure",
            "C": "Appointed for six years",
            "D": "Should be at least 35 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Appointed for six years",
        "explanation": "Appointed for six years. Governors in India are appointed by the President under Article 155 of the Constitution, with a tenure of five years. However, they serve at the President's pleasure and can be removed at any time."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-332",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On whose advice does the Governor appoint the ministers ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Prime Minister",
            "B": "President",
            "C": "Chief Minister",
            "D": "Vice-President"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Chief Minister",
        "explanation": "Chief Minister. According to Article 164, the Governor appoints the Chief Minister, who in turn advises the Governor on appointing other Ministers. The Ministers hold office at the pleasure of the Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-333",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who unfurls the flag at Rajpath on the Republic Day?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Chief of Defence Staff",
            "B": "The President of India",
            "C": "The Chief Minister of Delhi",
            "D": "The Prime Minister of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The President of India",
        "explanation": "The President of India takes the salute from various units of the Army, Navy, Air force, Para-military, and Police forces during the parade. This ceremony commemorates the adoption of the country's Constitution on January 26, 1950. The Prime Minister of India, on the other hand, hoists the national flag on Independence Day at the Red Fort."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-334",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Governor’s emoluments are decided by the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Prime Minister",
            "B": "President",
            "C": "State Legislature",
            "D": "Parliament"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "explanation": "Parliament. The Governor (Part VI, Article 153 -167) serves as a titular or constitutional head and acts as the agent of the central government. The Governor of State is appointed by the President. Article 158 (4) - The emoluments and allowances of the Governor cannot be diminished during his term of office. Article 158(3A) - When the same person is appointed as the Governor of two or more States, the emoluments and allowances payable to him are shared by the States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-335",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The ministers in the state hold office during the pleasure of the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Deputy Chief Minister",
            "B": "Speaker of the Legislative Assembly",
            "C": "Chief Minister",
            "D": "Governor"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. Under Article 164 (1) The Chief Minister shall be appointed by the Governor and the other Ministers shall be appointed by the Governor on the advice of the Chief Minister, and the Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the Governor."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-336",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan assume office as the first Vice-President of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1954",
            "B": "1951",
            "C": "1952",
            "D": "1950 www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1952",
        "explanation": "1952. Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan served as first vice president of India from 1952 to 1962 and the second president of India from 1962 to 1967. He received Bharat Ratna in 1954. Teachers' Day is celebrated on September 5 in India to honor him."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-337",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that ‘The President shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his/her term, continue to hold office until his successor enters upon his/her office’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 61",
            "B": "Article 56",
            "C": "Article 58",
            "D": "Article 50"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 56",
        "explanation": "Article 56. The President shall hold office for a term of five years. The President may, by writing under his hand addressed to the Vice-President, resign his office. Other important Articles: Article 61 - Procedure for impeaching the President of India. Article 58 - Qualifications for election as a President of India. Article 50 - The separation of the judiciary from the executive."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-338",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that an election to fill a vacancy caused by the expiration of the term of office of the President shall be completed before the expiration of the term?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 59",
            "B": "Article 62",
            "C": "Article 61",
            "D": "Article 60"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Article 62",
        "explanation": "Article 62. This article also covers the scenario where a vacancy arises due to the President's death, resignation, or removal, requiring the election to be held within six months. Other articles: Article 59: Conditions of President’s office. Article 61: Procedure for impeachment of the President. Article 60: Oath or affirmation by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-339",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the second vice - President of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "VV Giri",
            "B": "Krishna Kant",
            "C": "Dr Zakir Hussain",
            "D": "Dr S Radhakrishnan"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Dr Zakir Hussain",
        "explanation": "Dr Zakir Hussain (1962 -1967) - He was the third President of India from 1967-1969, and the first Indian President to die in office in 1969. He was awarded Bharat Ratna in 1963. First five vice presidents of India : First - Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan (1952-1962). Third - Sh. V.V. Giri (1967-1969). Fourth - Sh. Gopal Swarup Pathak (1969-1974). Fifth - Sh. B.D.Jatti (1974-1979)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-340",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who will cause every year, annual financial statements to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the State? SSC Stenographer 13/10/2023 (Afternoon)",
        "options": {
            "A": "President",
            "B": "Governor",
            "C": "Deputy Chief Minister",
            "D": "Chief Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor: Financial Powers - Money bill can only be introduced in the state legislature on his prior recommendation. No demand for grant can be made except on his recommendation. Money from the contingency fund can be withdrawn after his recommendation for meeting the unforeseen expenditures. He constitutes a finance commission for every 5 years to review the financial situation of municipalities and panchayats. Article 112 - Annual financial statement. Article 200 - Assent to Bills."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-341",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When the President of India keeps a bill (except money bill and constitutional amendment bill) pending for an indefinite period, it is called______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "absolute veto of the President",
            "B": "amendatory veto of the President",
            "C": "pocket veto of the President",
            "D": "suspensive veto of the President"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "pocket veto of the President",
        "explanation": "Pocket veto of the President. Veto Power of the President of India is guided by Article 111. Three types of Veto Power: Absolute veto, Suspensive veto and Pocket veto. Absolute Veto: It refers to the power of the President to withhold his assent to a bill passed by the Parliament. The bill then ends and does not become an act. Suspensive Veto: The President uses a suspensive veto when he returns the bill to the Indian Parliament for its reconsideration."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-342",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The President of India decides on the question as to the disqualification of Members of Parliament in consultation with the ____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Vice President",
            "B": "Supreme Court of India",
            "C": "Parliament",
            "D": "Election Commission of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Election Commission of India",
        "explanation": "Election Commission of India. Article 103 - It deals with the decisions of disqualifications of members of Parliament. Article 102 - It provides for Disqualification for membership of Parliament If he holds any office of profit, unsound mind, undischarged insolvent, Not a citizen of India. Other provisions: Anti-Defections (10th Schedule), Section 8 of Representation of People Act 1951."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-343",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the Prime Minister of India when the Fundamental Duties were first incorporated in the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "B": "Indira Gandhi",
            "C": "Atal Bihari Vajpayee",
            "D": "Rajiv Gandhi"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi",
        "explanation": "Indira Gandhi : 3rd Prime Minister of India and first and, to date, only female prime minister of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-344",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who holds the authority of transferring judges from one High court to another High Court?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The senior most judge of Supreme Court",
            "B": "The chief justice of india",
            "C": "The president of india",
            "D": "The law minister of india"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "The president of india",
        "explanation": "The President of India (Article 52). Article 222 - Transfer of a Judge from one High Court to another. Article 217 -Appointment and conditions of the office of a Judge of a High Court. Article 124 - Establishment and constitution of the Supreme Court. Article 218 - Application of certain provisions relating to the Supreme Court to High Courts. Article 214 - High Courts for States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-345",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding removal of the President of India ? A. The impeachment process can be initiated in either House of Parliament. B. The impeachment charges must be signed by the one-third members of the House in which the process is initiated. C. In the impeachment process, a 30 days' notice should be given to the President. D. The impeachment resolution is passed by a majority of two-thirds of the total membership of that House.",
        "options": {
            "A": "B and C only",
            "B": "A, B and C only",
            "C": "A, B, C and D",
            "D": "A and D only"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "A and D only",
        "explanation": "A and D only. Article 61: Procedure for impeachment of the President. The impeachment charges must be signed by not less than www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity one-fourth members of the house in which the process is initiated. A fourteen day notice should be given to the president. Impeachment of the President was taken from the US Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-346",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding the State Executive ? A. Article 152 of the Indian Constitution states 'Unless the context otherwise requires, the expression 'State' does not include Jammu and Kashmir'. B. The 7th Constitutional Amendment Act has provided for the appointment of the same person as Governor for two or more states. C. The Supreme Court clearly mentioned that the office of the Governor is under the control of the Central Government.",
        "options": {
            "A": "B and C only",
            "B": "A and C only",
            "C": "A, B and C",
            "D": "A and B only"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "A and B only",
        "explanation": "A and B only. Part VI of Constitution (functioning of state government). Articles under Part VI : Article 153 - Governors of a state, Article 154 - Executive power of the state, Article 155 - Appointment of governor, Article 156 - Terms of office of governor, Article 159 - Oath or affirmation by the governor, Article 163 - Council of ministers to aid and advise governor, Article 165 - Advocate general for the state."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-347",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Governor of an Indian state before entering upon his office takes an oath or affirmation before ____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "the Chief Justice of the High Court exercising jurisdiction in relation to the State",
            "B": "the President of India",
            "C": "the Chief Minister of the concerned state",
            "D": "the Prime Minister of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "the Chief Justice of the High Court exercising jurisdiction in relation to the State",
        "explanation": "Article 159 - Oath or affirmation to the Governor by the Chief Justice of the High Court and in his Absence, senior most Judge of that Court available. Article 155 - The Governor of a State shall be appointed by the President. Article 153 - Governors of States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-348",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the duty of the Chief Minister, as mentioned under Article 167 of the Indian Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Communication of all decisions of the Council of Ministers to the Governor.",
            "B": "Appointment and removal of Council of the Ministers.",
            "C": "Appointment of the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly.",
            "D": "Appointment of Advocate General of the state in consultation with Attorney general."
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Communication of all decisions of the Council of Ministers to the Governor.",
        "explanation": "Article 167 imposes on the Chief Minister the responsibility of keeping the Governor informed of all decisions made by the Council of Ministers concerning administration and legislation. Article 178 - It deals with the corresponding position for Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of a state."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-349",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following served the shortest tenure as the Prime Minister of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "HD Deva Gowda",
            "B": "VP Singh",
            "C": "Chandra Shekhar",
            "D": "IK Gujral"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Chandra Shekhar",
        "explanation": "Chandra Shekhar. Shri Gulzari Lal Nanda (11 January 1966 - 24 January 1966 and 27 May 1964 - 9 June 1964) served the shortest tenure as PM. H D Deva Gowda (June 1, 1996 - April 21, 1997) - 11th Prime Minister of India. V. P. Singh (December 2, 1989 - November 10, 1990) - 7th Prime Minister of India. Chandra Shekhar (10 November 1990 and 21 June 1991) - 8th Prime Minister of India. The longest-serving prime minister was Jawaharlal Nehru, (16 years and 286 days)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-350",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Inter-State Council consists of ______ ministers of Cabinet rank in the Union Council of Ministers nominated by the Prime Minister of India.",
        "options": {
            "A": "six",
            "B": "two",
            "C": "ten",
            "D": "four"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "six",
        "explanation": "Six. Inter-State Council - A constitutional body established by the President of India. Article 263 contemplates the establishment of an inter-state council to effect coordination between the states and between centre and states. Established by the President of India. Composition of the council - PM as chairman, CM of all the states and UTS having legislative assemblies, Administrators of UTs not having legislative assemblies, Governors of states under President’s rule, Five ministers of the cabinet rank are permanent invitees of the council."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-351",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who appoints the Chief Justice of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Vice - President",
            "B": "President",
            "C": "Supreme Court Judge",
            "D": "Prime Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "President",
        "explanation": "President. Article 124 (2) - Vests power on the President to appoint every Judge of the Supreme Court including the Chief Justice of India. Article 124 - States the establishment of the Supreme Court. Article 124 (3) - Qualification of Supreme court Judge."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-352",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age (in years) a person should be if he/she is willing to be appointed as the Governor of a state in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "28",
            "B": "30",
            "C": "35",
            "D": "40"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "35",
        "explanation": "35 years. Article 157 - Qualifications for appointment as Governor (must be a citizen of India and must have completed 35 years of age). Article 153 - Governors of States. Article 154 - Executive power of State. Article 155 - Appointment of Governor. Article 58 - The presidential candidate must complete the age of 35 years. Article 84 (b) - the minimum age for Lok Sabha election shall be 25 years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-353",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the Union Territories of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "President",
            "B": "Prime Minister",
            "C": "Chief Minister",
            "D": "Member of Legislative Assembly"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "President",
        "explanation": "President. The administrator appointed by the President runs the administration on the behalf of the President. Part - VIII (Union Territories), Article 239 (Administration of Union territories). Article 239A (Creation of local legislatures or council of ministers or both for certain Union territories. Example (Pondicherry). Article 239AA (Special provisions with respect to Delhi)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-354",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding the benefits of the retired President of India? A. The former President of India will also be entitled to a monthly pension of ₹2.5 lakh. B. He/She is entitled to a secretarial staff comprising a private secretary, a personal assistant, an additional private secretary, two peons, and office expenses up to ₹1 lakh per annum. C. He/She is also entitled to free highest-class travel anywhere in India, accompanied by one person, by rail, air, or steamer.",
        "options": {
            "A": "A and B only",
            "B": "B and C only www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity",
            "C": "A and C only",
            "D": "A, B and C"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "A, B and C",
        "explanation": "A, B and C. The President {Article (52-62)} of India is the head of state of the Republic of India. First President - Rajendra Prasad (held office for two terms, longest serving president of India)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-355",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following Presidents of India was also the deputy chairman of the Planning Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "VV Giri",
            "B": "KR Narayanan",
            "C": "Ramaswamy Venkataraman",
            "D": "Pranab Mukherjee"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Pranab Mukherjee",
        "explanation": "Dr. Pranab Mukherjee (13th president). Other positions he hold were Minister of Finance (2009 - 2012), Minister of Defence (2004 - 2006), Minister of External Affairs (2006 - 2009), 15th Leader of the Lok Sabha (2004 – 2012), Deputy Chairman of the Planning Commission (1991 - 1996), 14th Leader of the Rajya Sabha (1980 – 1984), Member of Parliament, Lok Sabha (2004 - 2012), and Member of Parliament, Rajya Sabha (1969 - 1981). V.V Giri (4th President), K.R Narayan (10th president). Ramaswamy Venkataraman (8th president)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-356",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements about the Vice President of India is INCORRECT?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Members of State legislatures do not take part in his elections.",
            "B": "He acts as the ex-officio Chairman of the Rajya Sabha.",
            "C": "The Vice President is elected for five years.",
            "D": "He can be removed from his office by the President approved through a resolution passed by the Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha."
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "He can be removed from his office by the President approved through a resolution passed by the Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha.",
        "explanation": "Vice president of India: The vice president is elected for five years. Minimum age: 35. He acts as the ex-officio chairman of the Rajya sabha. In the electoral college for Vice President, both elected and nominated members of both the Houses of Parliament take part."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-357",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The emoluments and allowances of the President and other expenditure relating to his office is charged on the ______ of India.",
        "options": {
            "A": "contingency fund",
            "B": "estimates fund",
            "C": "consolidated fund",
            "D": "public accounts fund"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "consolidated fund",
        "explanation": "Consolidated Funds - Article 266(1). Three types of funds of the Central Government – Consolidated Fund of India - Revenues received by the government and expenses made by it, excluding the exceptional items. Contingency Fund of India (Article 267) - the emergency fund for the nation and Public Accounts of India (Article 266(2) - those funds that are received on behalf of the Government of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-358",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which is NOT correct about the powers of the Chief Minister?",
        "options": {
            "A": "He allocates portfolios among ministers.",
            "B": "He presides over the meetings of the Council of Ministers.",
            "C": "When he resigns or dies, it has no effect in the functioning of the council of ministers.",
            "D": "The Governor appoints ministers on His recommendations."
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "When he resigns or dies, it has no effect in the functioning of the council of ministers.",
        "explanation": "The Governor appoints the Chief Minister and other Ministers (Article 164). The Chief Minister is the head of the State Council of Ministers and the real executive head of state government. Article 167 (Chief Minister acts as a link between Governor and state council of ministers)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-359",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following is NOT appointed by the President of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ambassadors and High Commissioners",
            "B": "Comptroller and Auditor General of India",
            "C": "Attorney General of India",
            "D": "Solicitor General of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Solicitor General of India",
        "explanation": "Solicitor General of India (the second - highest law officer of the country) is appointed by the Appointments Committee of the Cabinet (ACC). Attorney Generals of India (Article 76). Comptroller and Auditor General of India (Article 148)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-360",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following was the third Vice - President of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "BD Jatti",
            "B": "Zakir Hussain",
            "C": "Gopal Swarup Pathak",
            "D": "V. V. Giri"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "V. V. Giri",
        "explanation": "V. V. Giri. Vice Presidents of India - 1st Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan, 2nd- Zakir Hussain, 4th Gopal Swarup Pathak, 5th B D Jatti. 14th- Jagdeep Dhankhan."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-361",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The election of the next Vice - President is to be held within _____ of the expiry of the term of office of the outgoing Vice - President.",
        "options": {
            "A": "90 days",
            "B": "60 days",
            "C": "120 days",
            "D": "75 days"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "60 days",
        "explanation": "60 days. Article 66 of the Constitution of India states the manner of election of the vice president. Judiciary"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-362",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 30 of the Constitution of India gives the Supreme Court wide original jurisdiction.",
            "B": "Original jurisdiction extends to any dispute between the Government of India and one or more states.",
            "C": "The Supreme Court has very wide advisory jurisdiction over all courts and tribunals in India.",
            "D": "The original jurisdiction of the Supreme Court can be exercised by a certificate granted by the High Court."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Original jurisdiction extends to any dispute between the Government of India and one or more states.",
        "explanation": "According to Article 131 of the Indian Constitution, the Supreme Court has original jurisdiction over any dispute arising between the Government of India and one or more States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-363",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the first-ever motion to remove a Supreme Court Justice signed by the members of Parliament?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1991",
            "B": "1988",
            "C": "1993",
            "D": "1995"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1991",
        "explanation": "1991. The first motion to remove a Supreme Court Justice was signed in 1991 by 108 Parliament members. It was filed against Justice V. Ramaswami, accused of misconduct during his tenure as Chief Justice of the Haryana and Punjab High Court from November 1987 to October 1989."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-364",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India grants power to the President to appoint Judges of the Supreme Court?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 124(2)",
            "B": "Article 123(1)",
            "C": "Article 127(3)",
            "D": "Article 128(4)"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 124(2)",
        "explanation": "Article 124(2). It states that every Supreme Court judge is appointed by the President through a warrant, after consulting judges of the Supreme Court and High Courts as deemed necessary. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Judges hold office until the age of sixty-five. Additionally, the Chief Justice of India must always be consulted for the appointment of judges other than the Chief Justice."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-365",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Supreme Court of India comprises the Chief Justice and not more than ______ other Judges appointed by the President of India.",
        "options": {
            "A": "37",
            "B": "35",
            "C": "38",
            "D": "33"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "33",
        "explanation": "33. The judges of supreme court are appointed by the president under the Article 124 (2) of the Indian Constitution. Supreme Court Judges retire at the age of 65. As per Article 124 (3) - In order to be appointed as a Judge of the Supreme Court, a person must be a citizen of India and must have been, for at least five years, a Judge of a High Court or an Advocate of a High Court for at least 10 years or he must be, in the opinion of the President, a distinguished jurist."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-366",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Articles 214 to 231 in Part VI of the Indian Constitution deal with the ____.",
        "options": {
            "A": "High Courts",
            "B": "District Courts",
            "C": "Subordinate Courts",
            "D": "Supreme Court"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "High Courts",
        "explanation": "High Courts. Articles 214 to 231 in Part VI of the Constitution deal with the organization, independence, jurisdiction, powers, and procedures of the high courts."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-367",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which writ is issued by a high court or supreme court when a lower court has considered a case going beyond its jurisdiction?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Quo Warrant",
            "B": "Habeas Corpus",
            "C": "Certiorari",
            "D": "Prohibition"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Prohibition",
        "explanation": "Prohibition. Writs are issued by the Supreme Court under Article 32 and by the High Court under Article 226 of the Indian Constitution. The five types of writs in India are: Habeas Corpus: Ensures that a detained person is brought before the court. Mandamus: Directs a public official to perform a duty. Certiorari: Transfers a case for review by a higher court. Prohibition: Prevents a lower court from exceeding its jurisdiction. Quo-Warranto: Questions the legal authority of someone holding a public office."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-368",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which judgement did the Supreme Court extend the scope of Article 21 and observed that ‘the Right to education flows directly from the ‘Right to life’ ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Mohini Jain v State of Karnataka",
            "B": "Neerja Choudhari v State of M. P.",
            "C": "Kharak Singh v State of UP",
            "D": "Malak Singh v State of Punjab"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Mohini Jain v State of Karnataka",
        "explanation": "Mohini Jain v State of Karnataka. The Supreme Court declared that it was impermissible for any educational institution to charge capitation fees as a consideration for admission. Neeraja Chaudhary vs. State of Madhya Pradesh - addressed the issue of bonded labor. Kharak Singh v State of UP - focused on the constitutional review of Uttar Pradesh Police Regulations."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-369",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following organisations said that India CANNOT have a parallel judicial system - one for the rich and the other for the poor?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Gujarat High Court",
            "B": "Supreme Court",
            "C": "Himachal High Court",
            "D": "Kerala High Court"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Supreme Court",
        "explanation": "Supreme Court (SC). Important Judgements of SC: Navtej Singh Johar vs. Union Of India (2018) - Decriminalized homosexuality by striking down parts of Section 377 of the IPC. K.S. Puttaswamy vs. Union of India (2017) - Recognized the right to privacy as a fundamental right under Article 21. Aruna Ramachandra Shanbaug Vs. Union of India (2011) - Upheld the constitutionality of passive euthanasia."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-370",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that the law declared by the Supreme Court shall be binding on all the courts within the territory of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 151",
            "B": "Article 147",
            "C": "Article 137",
            "D": "Article 141"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 141",
        "explanation": "Article 141. Other Articles: Article 137 - Review of judgments or orders by the Supreme Court. Article 147 - Any substantial question of law as to the interpretation of the Constitution shall be construed as including references to any substantial question of law as to the interpretation. Article 151 - Audit reports."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-371",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of India? A.Original jurisdiction extends to any dispute between the Government of India and one or more States or between the Government of India and any State or States on one side and one or more States on the other or between two or more States. B.Appellate Jurisdiction extends when the Union plus some States are one side and some other States on the other side of the dispute. C.Under Articles 129 and 142 of the Constitution, the Supreme Court has been vested with the power to punish for contempt of court. D. As of now, the International Commercial Arbitration cannot be initiated in the Supreme Court.",
        "options": {
            "A": "B and D only",
            "B": "A and C only",
            "C": "A, B, C and D",
            "D": "A and B only"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "A and C only",
        "explanation": "A and C only. Advisory Jurisdiction (Article 143) - The President to seek the opinion of the Supreme Court. The appellate jurisdiction of the Supreme Court can be invoked by a certificate granted by the High Court concerned under Article 132(1), 133(1) or 134 of the Constitution. The Supreme Court (Article 124) of India is the apex judicial body under the Constitution of India. Inaugurated - On January, 28, 1950."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-372",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The advisory board under provisions of Article 22 of the Constitution is to be consisted of persons who are, or have been or are qualified to be appointed as __________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Judges of Supreme court",
            "B": "Judges of Lower court",
            "C": "Judges of High court",
            "D": "Judges of District court"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Judges of High court",
        "explanation": "Judges of High court. Related Articles : Article 214 - High Courts for States. Article 215 - High Courts to be courts of record. Article 216 - Constitution of High Courts. Article 217 - Appointment and conditions of the office of a Judge of a High Court. Article 218 - Application of certain provisions relating to the Supreme Court to High Courts. Article 219 - Oath or affirmation by Judges of High Courts. Article 220 - Restriction on practice after being a permanent Judge."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-373",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Federal Court of India was established in Delhi by the Act of ______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1908",
            "B": "1919",
            "C": "1905",
            "D": "1935"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1935",
        "explanation": "1935. The Federal Court of India was a judicial body that operated www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity from 1937 to 1950, when it was replaced by the Supreme Court of India. The Federal Court had jurisdiction to solve disputes between provinces and federal states. Calcutta High court is the oldest high court in India (established in the year 1862). Justice Harilal Jekisundas Kania was the first (Indian) Chief Justice of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-374",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions that there shall be a Supreme Court of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 123",
            "B": "Article 121",
            "C": "Article 122",
            "D": "Article 124"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Article 124",
        "explanation": "Article 124. Article 121 - Restriction on discussion in Parliament. Article 122 - Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Parliament."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-375",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Disputes between two or more states come under the _______ of the Supreme Court. SSC Stenographer 12/10/2023 (Morning)",
        "options": {
            "A": "original jurisdiction",
            "B": "advisory jurisdiction",
            "C": "Appellate Jurisdiction",
            "D": "writ jurisdiction"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "original jurisdiction",
        "explanation": "Original jurisdiction - The power to hear and determine a dispute in the first instance. It is provided under Article 131 of the Indian Constitution. Article 143 of the Indian Constitution confers upon the Supreme Court advisory jurisdiction. Article 133 - Appellate jurisdiction of Supreme Court in appeals from High Courts in regard to civil matters."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-376",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following cases the Supreme Court, while laying out the 'basic structure' of the Constitution held that the democratic character of the polity was an essential component of the 'basic structure\" ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Romesh Thappar vs State of Madras",
            "B": "AK Gopalan vs State of Madras",
            "C": "Kesavananda Bharati vs State of Kerala",
            "D": "Sajjan Singh vs State of Rajasthan"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Kesavananda Bharati vs State of Kerala",
        "explanation": "This judgement was delivered on 24 April 1973. The case was filed by Sri Kesavananda Bharati (head of a Hindu religious mutt in Kerala), challenging the constitutional validity of the 24th, 25th and 29th Amendments to the Indian Constitution. Romesh Thappar vs State of Madras: Freedom of speech and expression includes Freedom of press. AK Gopalan vs State of Madras - Deals with the constitutionality of preventive detention. Sajjan Singh vs State of Rajasthan - Involved a challenge to the validity of the Constitution (26th Amendment) Act."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-377",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The State of Kerala Vs Leesamma Joseph case deals with __________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "dowry",
            "B": "the economic weaker section",
            "C": "education",
            "D": "persons with disabilities"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "persons with disabilities",
        "explanation": "persons with disabilities. This case was related to Article 16 (equal opportunity in the workplace). The SC held that persons with physical disabilities have the right to reservation in promotions. Other Important Cases - Kesavananda Bharati case: The Supreme Court gave the doctrine of the ‘Basic Structure’ of the constitution. Shayara Bano vs Union of India: The Supreme Court struck down the practice of triple talaq and declared it unconstitutional."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-378",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Supreme Court of India came into existence on ___________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "30 January 1935",
            "B": "26 January 1950",
            "C": "15 August 1947",
            "D": "2 October 1952"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "26 January 1950",
        "explanation": "26 January 1950. The Supreme Court was inaugurated in the Chamber of Princes in the Parliament House on January 28, 1950. The foundation stone of the Supreme Court building was laid by the first President of India, Rajendra Prasad, on October 29, 1954. The 50th Chief Justice of India is Dhananjaya Y. Chandrachud."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-379",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Till which year did the High Court of Delhi continue to exercise jurisdiction over Himachal Pradesh?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1969",
            "B": "1967",
            "C": "1971",
            "D": "1968"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1971",
        "explanation": "1971. The Indian High Courts Act (1861) established High Courts of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay. The first high court of India was established in Kolkata and formally it was called the High Court of Judicature at Fort William. India has 25 High Courts (now). Article 214 - High Court for each State. Article 226 - Power of high court to issue certain writs. Article 216 - Constitution of High Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-380",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements are true regarding the Family Courts (Amendment) Bill, 2022?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1, 2 and 3",
            "B": "1, 3 and 4",
            "C": "1, 2 and 4",
            "D": "2, 3 and 4"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
        "explanation": "1, 2 and 3. Family Courts (Amendment) Bill 2022 seeks to amend the Family Courts Act, 1984 to establish family courts in Himachal Pradesh and Nagaland. Family Court Act, 1984 - Enacted for the establishment of Family Courts with a view to promote conciliation, and secure speedy settlement of disputes relating to marriage and family affairs and for related matters."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-381",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The High court of Delhi was established in _______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1962",
            "B": "1947",
            "C": "1951",
            "D": "1966"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1966",
        "explanation": "1966. The High Court of Delhi was established with four Judges. They were Chief Justice K.S.Hegde, Justice I.D. Dua, Justice H.R.Khanna and Justice S.K.Kapur. Before 1966 under the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 Delhi was under the jurisdiction of the Punjab High Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-382",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The first High Court in India was established in ______________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "1860",
            "B": "1862",
            "C": "1867",
            "D": "1857"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1862",
        "explanation": "1862. Calcutta High Court: It was brought into existence under the High Court's Act (1861). Location - Esplanade Row West (Kolkata). Jurisdiction - West Bengal and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands. Bombay High Court {(14 August 1862) (Indian High Courts Act 1861)}, Madras High Court {(15 August 1862, Indian High Courts Act 1861}."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-383",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following cases did the Supreme Court of India pronounce the theory of the ‘Basic Structure’ of the Constitution?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Kesavananda Bharati Case, 1973",
            "B": "Golaknath Case, 1967",
            "C": "Minerva Mills Case, 1980",
            "D": "Swarn Singh Case, 1989"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Kesavananda Bharati Case, 1973",
        "explanation": "Kesavananda Bharati Case, 1973 - Parliament can not amend or alter the ‘Basic Structure’ of the constitution. Golaknath Case, 1967 - Parliament www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity cannot take away or abridge any of the Fundamental Rights. Minerva Mills Case, 1980 - Parliament can amend any part of the Constitution but it cannot change the “Basic Structure” of the Constitution. Swarn Singh Case, 1998 - In this case, the SC held the UP Governor's pardon of a convict unconstitutional."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-384",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the structure of the Indian judiciary?",
        "options": {
            "A": "One-tier",
            "B": "Two-tier",
            "C": "Three-tier",
            "D": "Five-tier"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Three-tier",
        "explanation": "Three-tier. The structure of the judiciary - Supreme Court (Article 124) at the top, High Courts (Article 214) below them and session’s courts at the lowest level."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-385",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A judge of the Supreme Court can be removed only on the grounds of ______",
        "options": {
            "A": "disrespect of the Constitution",
            "B": "proven misbehaviour or incapacity",
            "C": "murder charges",
            "D": "lack of knowledge"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "proven misbehaviour or incapacity",
        "explanation": "Proven misbehaviour or incapacity. Article 124 - There shall be a Supreme Court of India. Article 143 - Power of the President to consult the Supreme Court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-386",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following jurisdictions of the Supreme Court allows it to settle disputes between the centre and state and amongst states ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Appellate",
            "B": "Advisory",
            "C": "Writ",
            "D": "Original"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Original",
        "explanation": "Original. The Supreme Court (Articles 124 to 147, Part V) has Original (Article 131), Appellate (Article 133-136), and Advisory (Article 143) jurisdiction. Under Original Jurisdiction, SC can hear the following cases: Any dispute between the Indian Government and one or more States, Any dispute between the Indian Government and one or more States on one side and one or more States on the other side, Any dispute between two or more States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-387",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "A Supreme Court or High Court judge can be removed by the Parliament by:",
        "options": {
            "A": "simple majority",
            "B": "both simple and two third majority",
            "C": "special majority",
            "D": "two third majority"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "special majority",
        "explanation": "Special majority. Special majority as per Article 249 requires a majority of 2/3rd members present and voting. For example, if out of the 245 members in Rajya Sabha, only 150 are present and voting, then the special majority required as per Article 249 would be 101. Simple majority refers to a majority of more than 50% of the members present and voting in the House. Majorities in the Constitution can be categorised into four Types : Absolute, Effective, Simple and Special."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-388",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which is NOT correct about the independence of the judiciary in our country?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The judiciary has the power to penalise those who are found guilty of contempt of court.",
            "B": "The judges are financially dependent on both the executive and legislature for their salaries and allowances.",
            "C": "The Constitution prescribes a very difficult procedure for removal of judges.",
            "D": "The legislature is not involved in the process of appointment of judges."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The judges are financially dependent on both the executive and legislature for their salaries and allowances.",
        "explanation": "Judges salaries and allowances are fixed and not subject to legislative approval. Supreme Court Judges {The Salaries, Pension and Allowances are charged upon the Consolidated Fund of India (Article 266 (1)}, High Court Judges {Salaries and Allowances are charged upon the Consolidated Fund of the States and the Pension is charged on the Consolidated Fund of India} ."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-389",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian judicial system is based on:",
        "options": {
            "A": "both integrated and dual system",
            "B": "dual court system",
            "C": "multiple court system",
            "D": "single integrated system"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "single integrated system",
        "explanation": "single integrated system. The judiciary is the watchdog of democracy, and also the guardian of the Constitution. Structure of Indian Judiciary {Supreme Court at the top, High Courts are below the SC, and below them are the district and subordinate courts}. Government Bodies"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-390",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many other members are there in the Finance Commission EXCEPT, Chairman ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "6",
            "B": "4",
            "C": "3",
            "D": "5"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "4",
        "explanation": "4. The Finance Commission is a constitutional body set up by the President of India under Article 280 of the Indian Constitution. Its primary function is to recommend the distribution of financial resources between the Union (Central Government) and States. The Commission is set up for a period of five years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-391",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years was the Election Commission of India founded?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1955",
            "B": "1952",
            "C": "1950",
            "D": "1947"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1950",
        "explanation": "1950. Election Commission of India (ECI) is a permanent Constitutional Body. The Commissioners have a fixed tenure of six years, or up to the age of 65 years, whichever is earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-392",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the tenure of office for the Chief Election Commissioner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "6 years or up to the age of 65 years",
            "B": "5 years or up to the age of 65 years",
            "C": "5 years or up to the age of 60 years",
            "D": "6 years or up to the age of 60 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "6 years or up to the age of 65 years",
        "explanation": "6 years or up to the age of 65 years. Article 324 - Superintendence, direction and control of elections to be vested in an Election Commission : (2) The Election Commission shall consist of the Chief Election Commissioner and such number of other Election Commissioners, if any, as the President may from time to time fix and the appointment of the Chief Election Commissioner and other Election Commissioners shall, subject to the provisions of any law made in that behalf by Parliament, be made by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-393",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following is NOT a member of the National Human Rights Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "District Magistrate",
            "B": "Former Chief Justice of the High Court",
            "C": "Former Chief Justice of the Supreme Court",
            "D": "Former Judge of the Supreme Court"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "District Magistrate",
        "explanation": "District Magistrate : They are administrative officers who are responsible for maintaining law and order in their respective districts. National Human Rights Commission (NHRC): It is a statutory body established on October 12, 1993."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-394",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution deals with the Election www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Part XV",
            "B": "Part XII",
            "C": "Part IV",
            "D": "Part XI"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Part XV",
        "explanation": "Part XV (Article 324-329). The Election Commission of India (ECI, Established - 25th January 1950) is an autonomous constitutional authority responsible for administering Union and State election processes in India. Originally the commission had only one election commissioner but after the Election Commissioner Amendment Act 1989, it was made a multi-member body."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-395",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "UPSC is a Constitutional Body to conduct examinations for appointments to the services of the Union and the services of the State, respectively, under Article ________",
        "options": {
            "A": "320",
            "B": "324",
            "C": "328",
            "D": "332"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "320",
        "explanation": "Article 320. Article 324 establishes a single Commission to oversee elections to the Central Legislature, including both the Upper and Lower Houses. Article 328 grants state legislatures the authority to create provisions for elections to their respective legislatures, including the preparation of electoral rolls, delimitation of constituencies, and other arrangements for the constitution of the legislature. Article 332 reserves seats in state legislative assemblies for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-396",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The establishment of Union Public Service Commission, State Public Service Commissions and Joint Public Service Commission falls under which of the following features of the Constitution of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Parliamentary Government",
            "B": "Federalism",
            "C": "Fundamental Rights",
            "D": "Directive Principles of State Policy"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Federalism",
        "explanation": "Federalism : It refers to a form of government in which power is distributed among different layers of government. Union Public Service Commission is a central recruitment agency, while State Public Service Commission is responsible for state level recruitment. These are constitutional bodies."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-397",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Office of the Registrar General and Census Commissioner, India comes under the:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ministry of Finance",
            "B": "Ministry of Home Affairs",
            "C": "Ministry of Corporate Affairs",
            "D": "Ministry of Rural Development"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Ministry of Home Affairs",
        "explanation": "Ministry of Home Affairs. Registrar General and Census Commissioner of India, founded in 1961 by the Government of India, Ministry of Home Affairs, for arranging, conducting and analysing the results of the demographic surveys of India including Census of India and Linguistic Survey of India. Headquarters - Delhi."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-398",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following are eligible for free legal aid under the National Legal Services Authority? A. A member of a Scheduled Caste or Scheduled Tribe. B. A victim of trafficking in human beings or beggar as referred to in Article 23 of the Constitution C. An industrial workman D. A person under circumstances of undeserved want such as being a victim of a mass disasters E. To file any case in Supreme Court, if any person needs free legal aid, the person’s annual income must be below 10 lakhs.",
        "options": {
            "A": "A, B, C and D only",
            "B": "A, B and E only",
            "C": "B, C and D only",
            "D": "A, B, C, D and E"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "A, B, C and D only",
        "explanation": "A, B, C and D only. According to the National Legal Services Authority (NALSA), the following individuals are eligible for free legal aid: women and children, mentally ill or disabled persons, and victims of mass disasters, violence, floods, droughts, earthquakes, and industrial disasters. NALSA was founded in 1995 under the Legal Services Authorities Act of 1987 to provide free legal services to the weaker sections of society. Its headquarters is located in New Delhi."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-399",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Finance Commission of India consists of ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "a Chairperson and four other members",
            "B": "a Chairperson and three other members",
            "C": "a Chairperson and two other members",
            "D": "a Chairperson and five other members"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "a Chairperson and four other members",
        "explanation": "A Chairperson and four other members. The Finance Commissions are periodically constituted by the President of India under Article 280 of the Indian Constitution. Its main function is to recommend the distribution of tax revenues between the central government and the states. The first finance commission was constituted in 1951. It is constituted for every five years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-400",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution mentions about the recommendations of the Finance Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Article 281",
            "B": "Article 283",
            "C": "Article 282",
            "D": "Article 284"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Article 281",
        "explanation": "Article 281 - The President shall cause every recommendation made by the Finance Commission under the provisions of this Constitution together with an explanatory memorandum as to the action taken thereon to be laid before each House of Parliament. Article 282 - Expenditure defrayable by the Union or a State out of its revenues. Article 283 - Custody, etc., of Consolidated Funds, Contingency Funds and moneys credited to the public accounts."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-401",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the maximum age for a member of a joint public service commission to hold his/her office as per the Constitution of India ? SSC Stenographer 13/10/2023 (Evening)",
        "options": {
            "A": "62 years",
            "B": "66 years",
            "C": "65 years",
            "D": "60 years"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "62 years",
        "explanation": "62 years. Joint State Public Service Commission (JSPSC) - It can be created by an act of Parliament at the request of the state legislatures concerned. It is a statutory body. Its chairman is appointed by the President. A member of a Public Service Commission shall hold office for a term of six years. In the case of the Union Commission, his or her minimum age is 65 years to attain the office."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-402",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the first chairman of Finance Commission of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "K Santhanam",
            "B": "KC Neogy",
            "C": "Ashok Kumar Chanda",
            "D": "PV Rajamannar"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "KC Neogy",
        "explanation": "KC Neogy. The Finance Commission of India is an independent constitutional body that is set up by the President of India after every five years or earlier to make recommendations on the distribution of financial resources between the Union and the states."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-403",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which of the following Acts www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity was the National Commission for Women established?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The National Commission for Women Act, 1988",
            "B": "The National Commission for Women Act, 1990",
            "C": "The National Commission for Women Act, 1989",
            "D": "The National Commission for Women Act, 1987"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The National Commission for Women Act, 1990",
        "explanation": "The National Commission for Women is a statutory body set up in January 1992 under the National Commission for Women Act, 1990 to review the constitutional and legal safeguards for women; recommend remedial legislative measures; facilitate redressal of grievances and advise the Government on all policy matters affecting women. The First Commission was constituted on 31st January 1992 with Mrs. Jayanti Patnaik as the Chairperson."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-404",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is responsible for attending to disputes concerning recruitment and conditions of service of public personnel at the Centre?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Central Administrative Tribunal",
            "B": "The Settlement and Appellate Tribunal",
            "C": "The Competition Appellate Tribunal",
            "D": "Joint Administrative Tribunal"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Central Administrative Tribunal",
        "explanation": "Central Administrative Tribunal (CAT) - It is a Statutory body, established under Administrative Tribunals Act, 1985. It comes under the purview of Article 323-A (Added by 42nd amendment act 1976). Its chairman and members are appointed by the President after consulting the Chief justice of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-405",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who appoints the State Election Commissioner ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Governor",
            "B": "Speaker",
            "C": "Chief Minister",
            "D": "Advocate General"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. The State Election Commissioner (SEC) is appointed by the Governor on the recommendation of a collegium, comprising the Chief Minister, the Speaker of the State Legislative Assembly and the Leader of Opposition in the Legislative Assembly. Power of SEC - To conduct free, fair and impartial elections to the local bodies in the state."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-406",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who conducts elections for both the houses of Parliament in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ministry of Parliamentary Affairs",
            "B": "Election Commission",
            "C": "President",
            "D": "Prime Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Election Commission",
        "explanation": "Election Commission - established in 1950. Part XV Election Commission (324 - 329): Article 326 - Elections to the House of the People and to the Legislative Assemblies of States to be on the basis of adult suffrage."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-407",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In India, which Ministry issues the coins of all denominations ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ministry of External Affairs",
            "B": "Ministry of Home Affairs",
            "C": "Ministry of Mines",
            "D": "Ministry Of Finance"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Ministry Of Finance",
        "explanation": "Ministry of Finance. The Government of India has the sole right to mint coins. The responsibility for coinage vests with the Government of India in accordance with the Coinage Act, 1906 as amended from time to time. The designing and minting of coins in various denominations is also the responsibility of the Government of India. Coins are minted at the four Indian Government Mints at Mumbai, Alipore (Kolkata), Saifabad (Hyderabad), Cherlapally (Hyderabad) and Noida (UP). It is issued for circulation only through the Reserve Bank in terms of the RBI Act."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-408",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Chairman of a State Public Service Commission can be removed by the order of the __________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "Prime Minister",
            "B": "President",
            "C": "Governor",
            "D": "Chief Minister"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "President",
        "explanation": "President. Provisions regarding the composition of SPSC provided in Part XIV of the Article 315 - 323. Article 317: Removal and suspension of a member of both the UPSC or SPSC. Article 316 (Appointment and terms of office of Members) : The Chairman and other members of the SPSC are appointed by the Governor of the State. Term of Office: A member of the SPSC shall hold office for a term of six years or till the age of 62 years, whichever is earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-409",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding the Finance Commission of India? A. The Finance Commission consists of a Chairman and four other members. B. The recommendations made by the Finance Commission are binding on the government and government needs to grant funds according to the advice of the Commission. C. Article 280 of the Indian Constitution talks about the recommendations of the Finance Commission.",
        "options": {
            "A": "A and B only",
            "B": "A, B and C",
            "C": "A only",
            "D": "B and C only"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "A only",
        "explanation": "A only. Finance Commission (FC) is a constitutional body under Article 280. It is set up after every five years or earlier to make recommendations on the distribution of financial resources between the Union and the states."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-410",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a Constitutional Body in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Election Commission of India",
            "B": "State Human Rights Commission",
            "C": "State Public Service Commission",
            "D": "Union Public Service Commission of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "State Human Rights Commission",
        "explanation": "State Human Rights Commission - It is a Statutory body, established under protection of human right act 1993. The Chairman and the members of the State Commission are appointed by the Governor. Tenure - Three years or till they reach the age of 70 years."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-411",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did the Election Commission of India for the first time in its history become a multi member body? Matric Level 28/06/2023 (Shift - 4)",
        "options": {
            "A": "2004",
            "B": "2014",
            "C": "1995",
            "D": "1989"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1989",
        "explanation": "1989. The Election Commission of India (ECI) is a constitutional body. The Election Commissioner Amendment Act, 1989 (adopted on 1 January 1990) turned the commission into a 3-member Commission. The ECI body administers elections to the Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha, State Legislative Assemblies, State Legislative Councils and the offices of the President and the Vice President of the country."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-412",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Gram Sabha is a meeting of all adults who live in the area covered by a ___________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "district",
            "B": "city",
            "C": "state",
            "D": "panchayat"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "panchayat",
        "explanation": "Panchayat. The term Gram Sabha is defined in the Constitution of India under Article 243(b). Gram Sabha is the primary body of the Panchayati Raj system and by far the largest. It is a permanent body. The power to annul a decision of the Gram Sabha rests with www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity the Gram Sabha only. Related Articles - 243A - Constitution of Gram Sabha."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-413",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Bureau of Indian Standard is a statutory body working under the aegis of which union ministry?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ministry of Commerce and Industry",
            "B": "Ministry of Micro, Small & Medium Enterprises",
            "C": "Ministry of Corporate Affairs",
            "D": "Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food and Public Distribution"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food and Public Distribution",
        "explanation": "The Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food and Public Distribution. It operates various schemes like Product Certification (ISI mark), Management Systems Certification, Hallmarking of Gold and Silver Jewellery/Artefacts and Laboratory Services. Bureau of Indian Standards (BIS), earlier known as the Indian Standards Institution (ISI), was founded in 1947."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-414",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT one of the objectives of the NITI Aayog ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To develop mechanisms to formulate credible plans at the village level",
            "B": "To design and print new currency notes and to bring them in circulation",
            "C": "To pay special attention to the sections of our society that may be at risk of not benefiting adequately from economic progress.",
            "D": "To evolve a shared vision of national development priorities"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "To design and print new currency notes and to bring them in circulation",
        "explanation": "NITI Aayog: National Institution for Transforming India, Established: 1 January 2015, Chairman: Prime Minister of India, First Chairman: Narendra Modi, First CEO (Chief Executive Officer): Sindhushree Khullar, First Vice - Chairperson: Arvind Panagariya."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-415",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The elections to the Panchayati Raj institutions are conducted by the ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Central election commission",
            "B": "State government",
            "C": "State election commission",
            "D": "Central government"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "State election commission",
        "explanation": "State election commission functions - Conducting elections to the Panchayati Raj institutions, Preparation of Electoral Rolls, Appointment of Dates for Nominations, Fixing Time for Poll, Counting of Votes, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-416",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The State Finance Commission is appointed every_____ years by the_______",
        "options": {
            "A": "5, state government",
            "B": "5, central government",
            "C": "2.5, state government",
            "D": "2.5, central government"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "5, state government",
        "explanation": "5, state government. According to Article 243 (I), the Governor of a State shall establish a State Finance Commission (constitutional body) every 5 years (73rd Amendment Act 1992). It distributes state resources to Panchayati Raj institutions at all three levels in the form of taxes, duties, and levies to be collected by the state and local governments."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-417",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the National Commission for Protection of Child Rights established?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2014",
            "B": "2007",
            "C": "2005",
            "D": "2010"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "2007",
        "explanation": "2007. The National Commission for Protection of Child Rights (NCPCR) is an Indian statutory body established by an Act of Parliament, the Commission for Protection of Child Rights (CPCR) Act, 2005. The Commission works under the aegis of Ministry of Women and Child Development, GoI."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-418",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the tenure of the Chairperson of National Human Rights Commission?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Three Years",
            "B": "Five Years",
            "C": "Six Years",
            "D": "Four Years"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Three Years",
        "explanation": "Three years (or until they attain the age of 70 years). National Human Rights Commission: Statutory body, Founded: 12 October, 1993, Composition: chairperson, five full-time Members and seven deemed Members, Appointed by the President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-419",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the National Commission for Women established in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1992",
            "B": "1994",
            "C": "1993",
            "D": "1991"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1992",
        "explanation": "1992. Other Commissions - The National Commission for Scheduled Castes (2004). National Commission for Scheduled Tribes (2004), National Commission for Minorities (1993), National Commission for Backward Classes (1993). Polity of neighbouring countries"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-420",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the official language of Bangladesh, a neighbouring country of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Bengali",
            "B": "Urdu",
            "C": "Dzongkha",
            "D": "Hindi"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Bengali",
        "explanation": "Bengali. Bangladesh: Capital - Dhaka. Currency - Bangladeshi Taka Other Nation’s Official Languages: Urdu (Pakistan), Dzongkha (Bhutan), Hindi (India), Tamil (Sri Lanka), Mandarin (China), Burmese (Myanmar), Dari and Pashto (Afghanistan), Nepali (Nepal) and Dhivehi (Maldives)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-421",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Sri Lanka got independence in the year:",
        "options": {
            "A": "1948",
            "B": "1950",
            "C": "1947",
            "D": "1949"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1948",
        "explanation": "1948. Sri Lanka got independence on February 4, 1948. National animal of Sri Lanka - Elephant, National flower - Blue Water Lily, The national sport - Volleyball. Myanmar (4 January, 1948). Bangladesh (26 March 1971)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-422",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "To which neighbouring country was the Indian Peace Keeping Force (IPKF) sent in the year 1987?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Nepal",
            "B": "Sri Lanka",
            "C": "Bhutan",
            "D": "Burma"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Sri Lanka",
        "explanation": "Sri Lanka. It was formed under the mandate of the 1987 Indo-Sri Lankan Accord that aimed to end the Sri Lankan Civil War between Sri Lankan Tamil militant groups such as the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) and the Sri Lankan military."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-423",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was a new Constitution adopted in Sri Lanka creating the 'Democratic The Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1978",
            "B": "1965",
            "C": "1982",
            "D": "1980"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1978",
        "explanation": "1978. The Constitution of the Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka has been the constitution of the island nation of Sri Lanka since its original promulgation by the National State Assembly on 7 September 1978."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-425",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On which date did Punjab abolish the Legislative Council?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1 January 1971",
            "B": "1 January 1977",
            "C": "1 January 1975",
            "D": "1 January 1970"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1 January 1970",
        "explanation": "1 January 1970. The Punjab Legislative Council (Abolition) Act, 1969 abolished the Legislative Council of Punjab, leading to the cessation of its members' positions. It amended Article 168 of the Constitution, removing reference to Punjab, and made changes to the Representation of the People Act, 1950."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-426",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The ‘Rule of Law’ is a key feature of the Indian Constitution which is a doctrine ascribed to _____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Plato",
            "B": "Adam Smith",
            "C": "Albert Venn Dicey",
            "D": "Karl Marx"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Albert Venn Dicey",
        "explanation": "Albert Venn Dicey was a British Whig jurist and constitutional theorist. Adam Smith is most famous for his 1776 book, \"The Wealth of Nations.\" Karl Marx is best known for his theories that led to the development of Marxism. His books, \"Das Kapital\" and \"The Communist Manifesto,\" formed the basis of Marxism. Plato was an ancient Greek philosopher."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-427",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The National Population Register was created under the provisions of ___________ and ___________ . a. the Citizenship Act, 1965 b. the Citizenship Rules, 2004 c. the Citizenship Act, 1955 d. the Citizenship Rules, 2003",
        "options": {
            "A": "a; c",
            "B": "a; b",
            "C": "b; d",
            "D": "c; d"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "c; d",
        "explanation": "c; d. The Citizenship Act, 1955 provides for the acquisition and loss of citizenship after the commencement of the Constitution. Originally, the Act 1955 also provided for Commonwealth Citizenship. But, this provision was repealed by the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-428",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which party formed the government in Britain in the year 1945?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Democratic Party",
            "B": "Labour Party",
            "C": "Socialist Party",
            "D": "Liberal Party"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Labour Party",
        "explanation": "Labour Party. In the 1945 general elections in Britain, the Labour Party, under the leadership of Clement Attlee, achieved a decisive victory, defeating Winston Churchill's Conservative Party. Democratic Party is one of the two major political parties, alongside the Republican Party, in the United States."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-429",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of Public Interest Litigation originated in _______________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Switzerland",
            "B": "Iceland",
            "C": "USA",
            "D": "New Zealand"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "USA",
        "explanation": "USA. Public Interest Litigation (PIL) means litigation filed in a court of law, for the protection of “Public Interest”, such as Pollution, Terrorism, Road safety, Constructional hazards etc. The concept of PIL was initially sown in India by Justice Krishna Iyer, in 1976 in Mumbai Kamagar Sabha vs. Abdul Thai."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-430",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar described Directive Principles of State Policy as __________of the Indian constitution.",
        "options": {
            "A": "soul of the state",
            "B": "identity card of the constitution",
            "C": "The most precious part of the constitution",
            "D": "a novel feature of the constitution"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "a novel feature of the constitution",
        "explanation": "a novel feature of the Indian constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-431",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The British Parliament introduced the Indian High Courts Act in which year?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1860",
            "B": "1861",
            "C": "1859",
            "D": "1858"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1861",
        "explanation": "1861. The India High Courts Act 1861 was enacted to create High Courts for various provinces and abolished Supreme Courts at Calcutta, Madras and Bombay and also the Sadar Adalats in Presidency towns. The first High Court was established in Calcutta on July 1, 1862. The Supreme Court of India was established by the Regulating Act of 1773."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-432",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct with respect to the political parties in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A political party symbol is assigned by the President of India.",
            "B": "India has a multi-party system classified as national, state or regional level",
            "C": "All parties are registered with the Supreme Court of India",
            "D": "Status of party is accorded by the Parliament."
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "India has a multi-party system classified as national, state or regional level",
        "explanation": "Multi-party system: More than two parties have a reasonable chance of coming to power either on their own strength or in alliance with others. As of September 2024, there are six National parties in India : BJP, INC, Communist Party of India - Marxist (CPI-M), Bahujan Samaj Party (BSP), National People's Party (NPP) and Aam Aadmi Party (AAP)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-433",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years was the Right of Persons with Disabilities Act passed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2010",
            "B": "2002",
            "C": "2016",
            "D": "2019"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "2016",
        "explanation": "2016. The Rights of Persons with Disabilities (RPwD) Act came into force from 19th April, 2017. It replaced the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995. Objective - To ensure that all persons with disabilities can lead their lives with dignity, without discrimination and with equal opportunities."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-434",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When did a States Reorganisation Commission was set up, which recommended the creation of linguistic States on the basis of larger linguistic groups?",
        "options": {
            "A": "December 1963",
            "B": "December 1953",
            "C": "December 1956",
            "D": "December 1958"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "December 1953",
        "explanation": "December 1953. India faced demands to reorganise states based on regional languages after independence. In November 1956, India underwent division into 14 states and six union territories through the implementation of the State Reorganisation Act. The Andhra State held the distinction of being the first state of Independent India, and it was later transformed into Andhra Pradesh on the 1st of November 1956. The State Reorganisation Commission was chaired by Fazal Ali, and two other members, namely K. M. Panikkar and H. N. Kunzru."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-435",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following states is one of those states that have no Panchayati Raj Institution at all?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Assam",
            "B": "Gujarat",
            "C": "Nagaland",
            "D": "Punjab"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Nagaland",
        "explanation": "Nagaland. Panchayats (Part IX, Articles 243 to 243-O): It is the system www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity of local self-government of villages in rural India. Rajasthan was the first state to implement Panchayati Raj in India (on October 2nd, 1959, in Nagaur district), followed by Andhra Pradesh later in 1959. 24th April - National Panchayati Raj Day. Currently, the Panchayati Raj system exists in all states except Nagaland, Meghalaya, and Mizoram, and in all Union Territories except Delhi."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-436",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Citizenship Act, 1955 does NOT deal with ____________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "acquisition",
            "B": "determination",
            "C": "election",
            "D": "termination"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "election",
        "explanation": "election. The Citizenship Act, 1955 deals with the acquisition, determination, and termination of Indian citizenship. Citizenship Acquisition: The Act provides for the acquisition of citizenship by birth, descent, registration, naturalization, and incorporation of territory. Citizenship Determination: The Act defines how to determine Indian citizenship. Citizenship Termination: The Act provides for the termination and deprivation of citizenship. Election Commission of India: PART XV (Article 324-329) of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-437",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Section of the Representation of People’s Act (RPA), 1951 deprives the prisoners of their right to vote?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Section 10 (4)",
            "B": "Section 72 (5)",
            "C": "Section 62 (5)",
            "D": "Section 15 (3)"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Section 62 (5)",
        "explanation": "Section 62 (5) : A person cannot vote in an election if they are in prison or in police custody. However, this rule does not apply to those in preventive detention. Even if someone cannot vote due to imprisonment, they still remain an elector if their name is on the electoral roll."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-438",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The proclamation of which Act by the King of England in 1773 paved the way for the establishment of the Supreme Court at Calcutta?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Pitt’s India Act",
            "B": "Indian Councils Act",
            "C": "Regulating Act",
            "D": "Charter Act"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Regulating Act",
        "explanation": "Regulating Act. The Regulating Act of 1773 led to the establishment of the Supreme Court at Calcutta, which included a chief justice (Elijah Impey) and three other judges. An amendment in 1781 exempted the Governor-General, the Council, and government officials from its jurisdiction while performing their duties."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-439",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which directive principle has been implemented in establishing Handloom and Handicrafts Boards?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Participation of workers in management of Industries",
            "B": "Provision for just and humane condition of work",
            "C": "Protection and improvement of environment",
            "D": "Promote cottage industries on cooperative basis"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Promote cottage industries on cooperative basis",
        "explanation": "The All India Handloom Board (AIHB) and the All India Handicrafts Board (AIHB) were two boards in India aimed to promote and develop cottage industries, such as handlooms and handicrafts, through cooperative efforts and support. The All India Handicrafts Board was set up in 1952 whereas the All India Handloom Board was established in 1992. However, the government decided to abolish the board in 2020 as part of its vision of \"Minimum Government and Maximum Governance\"."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-440",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which south-eastern Dravidian language has been approved by Odisha state to be included in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution of India, on 10th July 2023 ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Kui",
            "B": "Malto",
            "C": "Tulu",
            "D": "Kodagu"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Kui",
        "explanation": "Kui. It is spoken by the Kandhas community. It is closely related to the Gondi and Kuvi languages. Some other languages included in the eighth schedule are: Sindhi was introduced in 1967. Konkani, Manipuri, and Nepali in 1992. Santali, Dogri, Maithili, and Bodo in 2003."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-441",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following organisation’s initiative is ‘India Justice Report’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "HCL Foundation",
            "B": "Infosys Foundation",
            "C": "Tata Trusts",
            "D": "Azim Premji Foundation"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Tata Trusts",
        "explanation": "Tata Trusts. The India Justice Report (IJR) is an initiative by Tata Trusts, in collaboration with the Centre for Social Justice, Common Cause, and the Commonwealth Human Rights Initiative, among others. It was first published in 2019. Karnataka was the top-ranked state in the 2022 India Justice Report (IJR)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-442",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a way to acquire citizenship in India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Incorporation of territory",
            "B": "Renunciation",
            "C": "Registration",
            "D": "Birth"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Renunciation",
        "explanation": "Renunciation. There are five recognized ways to acquire citizenship in India under the Citizenship Act, 1955: By Birth - A person born in India can acquire citizenship by birth. By Descent - A person born outside India to Indian parents can acquire citizenship. By Registration - Certain persons, such as foreign nationals married to Indian citizens, can acquire citizenship through registration. By Naturalization - Foreign nationals can acquire citizenship after fulfilling certain residency requirements. By Incorporation of Territory - If a foreign territory becomes part of India."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-443",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a condition for acquiring the citizenship of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Registration",
            "B": "Descent",
            "C": "Domicile",
            "D": "Holding property"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Holding property",
        "explanation": "Holding property. The Citizenship Act of 1955 is the fundamental law governing the acquisition and termination of Indian citizenship. It outlines five ways to become an Indian citizen: birth, descent, registration, naturalisation, and incorporation of territory. Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019: It provides an accelerated pathway for the citizenship of the members of six communities (Hindus, Sikhs, Buddhists, Jains, Parsis, and Christians) from Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Afghanistan if they have arrived before December 31, 2014."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-444",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is a feature of Directive Principles of State Policy, and also distinguishes it from Fundamental Rights ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is justiciable.",
            "B": "It protects the interest of the individual.",
            "C": "It is non - justiciable.",
            "D": "It is prohibitive in nature."
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "It is non - justiciable.",
        "explanation": "It is non - justiciable. Difference Between Fundamental Rights and DPSP: DPSP are positive as they require the State to do certain things while FR are negative as they impose limitations on the working of the state. Fundamental Rights do not require any legislation for their implementation. They www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity are automatically enforced while DPSP requires legislation for their implementation. They are not automatically enforced."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-445",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Any citizen of India can make a declaration renouncing his/her Indian citizenship under the ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Citizenship Act, 1985",
            "B": "Citizenship Act, 1965",
            "C": "Citizenship Act, 1955",
            "D": "Citizenship Act, 1975"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Citizenship Act, 1955",
        "explanation": "Citizenship Act, 1955. It is an Act to provide for the acquisition and determination of Indian citizenship. Part II of the Indian Constitution deals with citizenship from Articles 5 to 11. Citizenship can be acquired by: Birth, Descent, Registration, Naturalization, and incorporation of territory."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-446",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Sections of the Indian Penal Code deals with 'rape'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Section 370",
            "B": "Section 375",
            "C": "Section 380",
            "D": "Section 385"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Section 375",
        "explanation": "Section 375. Section 370 of the Indian Penal Code (IPC) deals with the crime of human trafficking. Section 380 of the Indian Penal Code (IPC) deals with theft in a dwelling house, tent, or vessel that is used as a human dwelling or for the custody of property. Section 385 of the Indian Penal Code (IPC) deals with putting someone in fear of injury to commit extortion. According to BNS (Bhartiya Nyaya Sanhita) Section for Rape is Section 63 and for Punishment for rape is Section 64."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-447",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the Chief Executive Head of the State ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "President",
            "B": "Governor",
            "C": "CM",
            "D": "PM"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "explanation": "Governor. He is appointed by the President for a five-year term and holds office at the President's pleasure. The Governor has several key powers, including appointing the Chief Minister and other Ministers (Article 164), assenting or withholding assent to bills (Article 200), promulgating ordinances (Article 213), and granting pardons (Article 161)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-448",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many members (elected and nominated) were there in the Council of State under the Government of India Act 1919 passed by the Parliament of the United Kingdom to expand participation of Indians in the government of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "70",
            "B": "50",
            "C": "75",
            "D": "60"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "60",
        "explanation": "60. The Central Legislature was made more powerful and more representative by the Government of India Act, 1919. The Act made the Governor-General the chief executive authority. 26 nominated; 34 elected (20 General, 10 Muslims, 3 Europeans and 1 Sikh)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-449",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following was widely considered as the ‘heaven born service’ for Indians during British rule?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Military service on the Burma front",
            "B": "The Indian Civil Service or ICS",
            "C": "The Indian Judicial Service",
            "D": "The British Indian Army"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "The Indian Civil Service or ICS",
        "explanation": "The Indian Civil Service or ICS. It was brought into existence by Lord Cornwallis (1786-93) to check the corruption in the East India company (EEIC). The Charter Act of 1853 provided for Open competition for ICS examination. Satyendranath Tagore was the first Indian to join ICS in 1863. Aitchson commission (1886) and Lee commission (1926) is related to reform in ICS."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-450",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "During a National Emergency, the term of Lok Sabha can be extended for:",
        "options": {
            "A": "three months at a time",
            "B": "six months at a time",
            "C": "one year at a time",
            "D": "two years at a time"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "one year at a time",
        "explanation": "One year at a time. During a National Emergency in India, the term of the Lok Sabha can be extended by the Parliament. According to Article 83 of the Indian Constitution, the normal term of the Lok Sabha is five years. However, under Article 352, if a National Emergency is declared, the term of the Lok Sabha can be extended beyond five years. The extension can only be done for one year at a time and cannot extend beyond six months after the emergency has ceased to operate."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-451",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Prevention of Seditious Meetings Act was passed in ________ by the colonial Government.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1898",
            "B": "1903",
            "C": "1912",
            "D": "1907"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1907",
        "explanation": "1907. The Prevention of Seditious Meetings Act was brought under the tenure of Lord Minto. The act was intended to prevent public meetings that could promote sedition or disturb public tranquility. The act allowed the District Magistrate or Commissioner of Police to prohibit public meetings in certain areas if they believed the meeting would promote sedition or disaffection."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-452",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The entire salaries, allowances and pensions of the chairman and members of the Union Public Service Commission are charged on the ______.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Consolidated fund of India",
            "B": "Special Fund of the UPSC",
            "C": "Contingency fund of India",
            "D": "Reserve Bank of India"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Consolidated fund of India",
        "explanation": "Consolidated fund of India : The salaries, allowances, and pensions of the chairman and members are charged to the Consolidated Fund of India to ensure their financial independence and security, preventing executive influence, as their expenses don't require Parliament's approval."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-453",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following was the first chairperson of National Commission for Women and a senior congress leader who passed away in 2022?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ambika Soni",
            "B": "Sushmita Dev",
            "C": "Jayanti Patnaik",
            "D": "Sheila Dikshit"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Jayanti Patnaik",
        "explanation": "Jayanti Patnaik. The National Commission for Women (NCW) is a statutory body of the Government of India, primarily focused on advising the government on all policy matters affecting women. Established on 31 January 1992 under the Indian Constitution, it was defined by the 1990 National Commission for Women Act. The first head of the commission was Jayanti Patnaik, and as of 24 February 2024, Rekha Sharma serves as the chairperson."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-454",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is the proposed successor to the Information Technology Act, 2000?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Digital India Bill",
            "B": "Cyber India Bill",
            "C": "Optical India Bill",
            "D": "Multimedia Bill"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Digital India Bill",
        "explanation": "Digital India Bill. The Digital India Act (DIA) aims to regulate the digital ecosystem, including cybersecurity, digital governance, and internet intermediaries. The Information Technology Act, 2000 (ITA-2000), notified on 17 October 2000, is India's primary law addressing cybercrime and e-commerce. Secondary legislation includes the Intermediary Guidelines Rules, 2011, and the IT (Intermediary www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity Guidelines and Digital Media Ethics Code) Rules, 2021."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-455",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT come under Directive Principles of State Policy?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Promotion of the Welfare of the People",
            "B": "Promotion of Indian Local Languages",
            "C": "Uniform Civil Code",
            "D": "Promotion of Cottage Industries"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Promotion of Indian Local Languages",
        "explanation": "Promotion of Indian Local Languages is primarily governed by the provisions of Part XVII of the Indian Constitution, which deals with official languages (Articles 343 to 351). Directive Principles of State Policy (DPSP) is covered under Articles 36-51 of Part IV of the Indian Constitution. Article 38: Promotion of the Welfare of the People. Article 44: Uniform Civil Code. Article 43: Promotion of Cottage Industries."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-456",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The ‘Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana’ (‘PM-JAY’) scheme of the government is associated with which of the following Directive Principles of State Policy ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Participation of workers in the management of industries",
            "B": "Promotion of co-operative societies",
            "C": "Equal justice and free legal aid",
            "D": "Duty of State to raise the level of nutrition and the improvement of public health"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Duty of State to raise the level of nutrition and the improvement of public health",
        "explanation": "Article 47 - Duty of the State to raise the level of nutrition and the improvement of public health. Part IV - Directive Principles of State Policy (Article 36 to 51): Article 38 - State to secure a social order for the promotion of welfare of the people."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-457",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Certain provisions of the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act were struck off by the Supreme Court. In which year was this law originally enacted? SSC Stenographer 12/10/2023 (Evening)",
        "options": {
            "A": "1998",
            "B": "1980",
            "C": "1999",
            "D": "1988"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1988",
        "explanation": "1988. Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act (Name changed to Prohibition of Benami Property Transactions Act, 1988 by Section 3 of the 2016 amendment) - It is an Act to prohibit benami transactions and the right to recover property held benami and for matters connected therewith or incidental."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-458",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following founded an expatriate Communist Party of India at Tashkent in 1920?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Jolly Kaul",
            "B": "M.N. Roy",
            "C": "P.C. Joshi",
            "D": "Shripad Amrut Dange"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "M.N. Roy",
        "explanation": "M.N. Roy (Father of Indian Communism). He was the first person to give the idea of a Constituent Assembly for India and the creator of the Mexican Communist Party. Communist Party of India (CPI) - It is the oldest communist party in India. Founded - in modern-day Kanpur on 26 December 1925. First General Secretary - S.V. Ghate . Headquarters - Ajoy Bhavan (New Delhi)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-459",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Acts prevents disrespect to the National Flag and National Anthem?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Prevention of insults to National Honour Act, 1971",
            "B": "Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 2006",
            "C": "Protection of National Honour Act, 1996",
            "D": "Civil Liberties Act, 2001"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Prevention of insults to National Honour Act, 1971",
        "explanation": "Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 1971: Insults to Indian National Flag and Constitution of India - Whoever in any public place or in any other place within public view burns, mutilates, defaces, disfigures, destroys, tramples upon or into contempt the Indian National Flag or the Constitution of India or any part thereof, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-460",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In the Interim Government formed on 2 September 1946, Liaquat Ali Khan was given the charge of:",
        "options": {
            "A": "the External Affairs Ministry",
            "B": "the Finance Ministry",
            "C": "the Defence Ministry",
            "D": "the Home Ministry"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "the Finance Ministry",
        "explanation": "The Finance Ministry. Interim Government (1946): Headed by Jawahar Lal Nehru. Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel held the Home Affairs, Information, and Broadcasting. Rajendra Prasad held the portfolio of Agriculture and Food. C Rajagopalachari was the Education and Arts Minister. Jagjivan Ram held the Labour Ministry. Jogendra Nath Mandal was the Law Minister."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-461",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Consider the following statement about the Government of India Act, 1935. 1. This act was enacted by the British Parliament. 2. This Act was divided into two separate acts for the India and Burma Government. 3. This act commenced from 1 April 1935. Select the correct statement(s) using the code given below.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Both 1 and 2",
            "B": "1, 2 and 3",
            "C": "Both 2 and 3",
            "D": "Both 1 and 3"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2",
        "explanation": "Both 1 and 2. The Government of India Act 1935 (Commenced in 1937): It provided for the establishment of an All India Federation consisting of provinces and princely states as units. It divided the powers between the Centre and units in terms of three lists, Federal List, Provincial List and Concurrent List."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-462",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who propounded the concept of 'Rule of Law'?",
        "options": {
            "A": "AV Dicey",
            "B": "CK Daphtary",
            "C": "Austin",
            "D": "AK Sen"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "AV Dicey",
        "explanation": "AV Dicey. Rule of Law - It means all laws apply equally to all citizens of the country and no one can be above the law. Three principles of Rule of Law given by A.V. Dicey : Supremacy of law, Equality before law, Individual rights. Chander Kishan Daphtary - First solicitor general of India (1950-63)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-463",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years was the Child Marriage Restraint Act passed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1856",
            "B": "1947",
            "C": "1878",
            "D": "1929"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1929",
        "explanation": "1929. Child Marriage (The marriage of a girl or a boy before the age of 18 years). Prohibtion of Child Marriage Act (PCMA), 2006 :- It replaced the Child Marriage Restraints Act, 1929. The marriageable age to be 18 and 21 for girls and boys respectively Other laws to protect the child :- Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act, 2015, Domestic Violence Act, 2005 and the Protection of Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-464",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Who described the Indian federal system as a bargaining federalism?",
        "options": {
            "A": "KC Wheare",
            "B": "Ivor Jennings",
            "C": "Granville Austin",
            "D": "Morris Jones"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Morris Jones",
        "explanation": "Morris Jones. Federalism - A system of government in which powers are divided between two or more levels of government, such as the centre and the state or provinces. Described - “Quasi www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity federalism” (KC Wheare). “Cooperative federalism” (Granville Austin). 'Federalism with Centralising tendency' (Ivor Jenning). Federalism concept borrowed from ‘Canada’."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-465",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "‘The Constitution of free India must be framed, without outside interference by a constituent assembly elected on the basis of adult franchise’. Who made this statement?",
        "options": {
            "A": "MN Roy",
            "B": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "C": "Sardar Patel",
            "D": "Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "explanation": "Jawaharlal Nehru - Made this statement on behalf of the Indian National Congress (INC) in 1938. The idea of ​Constituent Assembly for India was first given by M.N.Roy in 1934. Constituent Assembly : Formed in 1946. Role - Elected to write the Constitution of India. Committees with their chairman : Union Constitution Committee - Jawaharlal Nehru. Drafting committee - Dr. B R Ambedkar. Provincial Constitution Committee - Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-466",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per the responsibilities defined in National Food Security Act, 2013, which of the following is a responsibility of the state/UT government?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Transportation of foodgrains up to designated depots in each state/UT",
            "B": "Allocation of required foodgrains to states/UTS",
            "C": "Delivery of foodgrains from designated FCI godowns",
            "D": "Identification of eligible households"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Identification of eligible households",
        "explanation": "Identification of eligible households. The National Food Security Act (2013) - 75% of Rural and 50% of Urban population is entitled to receive highly subsidised foodgrains under two categories of beneficiaries – Antodaya Anna Yojana (AAY) households and Priority Households (PHH). Public Distribution System (PDS) is governed by provisions of the National Food Security Act, 2013 (NFSA)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-467",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Justice Indu Malhotra penned a dissenting opinion in which of the following landmark judgements?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Basic structure doctrine",
            "B": "Preamble part of the Constitution",
            "C": "Entry of women to Sabarimala",
            "D": "Land reforms in India"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Entry of women to Sabarimala",
        "explanation": "Entry of women to Sabarimala. Justice Indu Malhotra opined that religious practices cannot be solely tested on the basis of Article 14. The right to equality under Article 14 does not override the fundamental right to religion under Article 25. The notions of rationality cannot be invoked in matters of religion. The Supreme Court struck down provisions of the Kerala Hindu Places of Public Worship (Authorisation of Entry) Rules, 1965, and allowed women, irrespective of their age, to enter Sabarimala temple and worship the deity."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-468",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Taxation Laws (Amendment) Act, 2021, amends the Income Tax Act of ________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1961",
            "B": "1974",
            "C": "1995",
            "D": "1988"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "1961",
        "explanation": "1961. Taxation Law Amendment Act, 2021 - It aims to withdraw tax demands made using a 2012 retrospective legislation to tax the indirect transfer of Indian assets. Income Tax Act (1961) - It provides an elaborate mechanism for the levying of taxes, their administration, collection & recovery. It has 298 sections & 14 schedules."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-469",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Constitution (One Hundred and Twenty Seventh Amendment) Bill, 2021, was introduced in the Lok Sabha by the ______ in August 2021.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Minister of Social Justice and Empowerment",
            "B": "Minister of Minority Affairs",
            "C": "Minister of Tribal Affairs",
            "D": "Minister of Rural Development"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Minister of Social Justice and Empowerment",
        "explanation": "Minister of Social Justice and Empowerment - By Dr. Virendra Kumar. 102 Amendment Act, 2018: Constitutional status was provided to the National Commission for Backward Classes under Article 338B. Articles 338 and 338A - The National Commission for Scheduled Castes (SC) and National Commission for Scheduled Tribes (ST), respectively. 103rd Amendment Act, 2019:- Reservations for the Economic Weaker Section and amendment in Articles 15(6) and 16(6), provide 10% reservation in public employment."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-470",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When were the general elections to the Legislative Assembly of the National Capital Territory held for the first time? Matric Level 27/06/2023 (Shift - 2)",
        "options": {
            "A": "1990",
            "B": "1993",
            "C": "1992",
            "D": "1991"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1993",
        "explanation": "1993. The 69th amendment act, 1991 inserted Article 239AA, which declared the Union Territory of Delhi to be administered by a Lieutenant Governor who works on aid and advice of the elected legislative assembly {Assembly Seats (70), Lok Sabha seats (7)}. The Assembly has all the powers under the State and Concurrent Lists with the exception of public order, police, and land."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-471",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Offences for which the police can arrest a person without an order from the court are called _________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Cognizable offences",
            "B": "Detention offences",
            "C": "Non Cognizable offences",
            "D": "Cross offences"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Cognizable offences",
        "explanation": "Cognizable offenses - It includes murder, rape, theft, kidnapping, counterfeiting, etc. Detention - The act of temporarily holding individuals in custody or confinement, typically by a government or governing authority by removing their freedom or liberty at that time. Non-Cognizable offences - An offence for which a Police officer has no authority to arrest without warrant. These include offences like cheating, assault, defamation etc."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-472",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which act has been amended by the Supreme Court of India to provide equal rights to daughters in their ancestral property ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Contempt of Courts Act",
            "B": "Hindu Succession Act",
            "C": "Hindu Marriage Act",
            "D": "Sharda Act"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Hindu Succession Act",
        "explanation": "Hindu Succession Act (1956) - It governs the inheritance of property by Hindus, Buddhists, Jains, and Sikhs. Contempt of Courts Act (1971) - It defines the power to punish for contempt of court and regulates their procedure. Hindu Marriage Act (1955) - It defines the minimum age of 18 years for the bride and 21 years for the groom."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-473",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Union Finance Ministry issued a notification amending the Electoral Bonds Scheme to allow the sale of electoral bonds for extra _______ days in the year of general elections to the Legislative Assembly of States and UTs with legislature.",
        "options": {
            "A": "45",
            "B": "35",
            "C": "15",
            "D": "25"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "15",
        "explanation": "15. Electoral Bonds Scheme: Launched - 2018 . Bonds are issued only to those political parties that are registered under section 29A of the Representation of the People Act, 1951. Electoral bonds were a mode of funding for political parties in India from their www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity introduction in 2018 until they were struck down as unconstitutional by the Supreme Court on 15 February 2024."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-474",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Dowry Prohibition Act passed in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1973",
            "B": "1982",
            "C": "1961",
            "D": "1954"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1961",
        "explanation": "1961. Dowry Prohibition Act: It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. Important Acts in India - Hindu Widow Remarriage Act 1856, Child Marriage Restraint Act 1929, Muslim Women Protection of Rights on Marriage Act 2019 (Triple Talaq Act), Rights of Persons with Disabilities Act 2016, National Security Act 1980."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-475",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Arms Act passed in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1951",
            "B": "1955",
            "C": "1959",
            "D": "1964"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "1959",
        "explanation": "The Indian Arms Act of 1959: As per the preamble, this Act aims to consolidate and amend the law relating to arms and ammunition. The main objective of this Act is to regulate and restrict the circulation of arms and ammunition, which were illegal. It was enacted by the Indian government after independence, recognizing that certain law-abiding citizens must own and use firearms for sports, crop protection, and self-defence."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-476",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Special Marriage Act passed in India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1958",
            "B": "1954",
            "C": "1962",
            "D": "1950"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1954",
        "explanation": "1954. Special Marriage Act (SMA) is an Indian law that provides a legal framework for the marriage of people belonging to different religions or castes. The applicability of the Act extends to the people of all faiths, including Hindus, Muslims, Sikhs, Christians, Jains, and Buddhists, across India. The minimum age to get married under the SMA is 21 years for males and 18 years for females."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-478",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "What are the two most essential rights of a democracy?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Exploitation, preventive detention",
            "B": "Equality, Freedom",
            "C": "Freedom, preventive detention",
            "D": "Equality, Exploitation"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Equality, Freedom",
        "explanation": "Equality, Freedom. Democracy is a form of government in which rulers are elected by the people in a free and fair elections, on universal adult franchise and governed on the basis of certain fundamental rules like a constitution. Types of Democracy: Direct democracy and Representative democracy."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-479",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the Indian Parliamentary Group established?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1950",
            "B": "1949",
            "C": "1948",
            "D": "1951"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1949",
        "explanation": "In 1949, The Indian Parliamentary Group was an autonomous body formed in the year 1949 in pursuance of a motion adopted by the Constituent Assembly (Legislative) on 16th August 1948. Speaker of Lok Sabha is its ex-officio President."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-480",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "If the State government dissolves the Panchayati Raj Institutions before the end of their five-year term, fresh elections should ordinarily be held within _____.",
        "options": {
            "A": "one month",
            "B": "six months",
            "C": "one year",
            "D": "three months"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "six months",
        "explanation": "Six months. Under Article 243 E - An election to constitute a Panchayat shall be completed - Before the expiry of its duration specified in clause (1) or before the expiration of a period of six months from the date of its dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-481",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which freedom is considered as the ‘Hallmark of Democracy’?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Right against exploitation",
            "B": "Right to freedom of religion",
            "C": "Freedom of assembly",
            "D": "Freedom of speech and expression"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Right to freedom of religion",
        "explanation": "The Right to freedom of Religion (Article 25-28) is considered the Hallmark of Democracy. Fundamental rights are mentioned in Part III (Article 12-35) of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-482",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The detention of a person cannot exceed ________ unless an advisory board consisting of judges of a High Court reports sufficient cause for extended detention.",
        "options": {
            "A": "one month",
            "B": "three months",
            "C": "six months",
            "D": "two months"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "three months",
        "explanation": "three months. Article 22 (Part III) grants protection to persons who are arrested or detained (available to both citizens and foreigners). Preventive detention means the detention of a person without trial and conviction by a court."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-483",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the National Emergency declared for the first time under Article 352 ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1963 - 69",
            "B": "1961 - 65",
            "C": "1961 - 67",
            "D": "1962 - 68"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "1962 - 68",
        "explanation": "1962-68. The National Emergency has been declared 3 times in India : 1962 to 1968 {During the India-China war, when “the security of India” was declared as being “threatened by external aggression”, President (Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan)}. 1971 {During the Indo - Pakistan war, President (V.V.Giri), Prime Minister (Indira Gandhi)}. 1975 to 1977 {The emergency was declared on the basis of “internal disturbance”, President (Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed), Prime Minister (Indira Gandhi)}."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-484",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "How many religious communities are notified as minorities by the Government of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Three",
            "B": "Five",
            "C": "Six",
            "D": "Four"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Six",
        "explanation": "Six {Muslims, Christians, Sikhs, Buddhists, Parsis, and Jains (added in 2014), National Commission on Minorities Act 1992}. According to the 2011 Census {Hindu (79.8%), Muslim (14.2%), Christian (2.3%), Sikh (1.7%), Buddhist (0.7%), Jain (0.4%)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-485",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was the National Youth Policy launched by the Government of India ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "2015",
            "B": "2014",
            "C": "2016",
            "D": "2017"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "2014",
        "explanation": "2014. It seeks to define the Vision of the Government of India for the Youth of the Country. The first youth policy was released in 1988. National Youth Day is held every year on 12th January to observe the birth anniversary of Swami Vivekananda. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf  Pinnacle Polity"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-486",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which freedom fighter abolished the Zamindari System in Uttar Pradesh and was elected as the Home Minister in 1955?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Lala Hardayal",
            "B": "Govind Ballabh Pant",
            "C": "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "D": "Jyotiba Phule"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "Govind Ballabh Pant",
        "explanation": "Govind Ballabh Pant successfully abolished the exploitative Zamindari system and revolutionised laws pertaining to women’s inheritance and marriage. He was appointed Minister of Home Affairs in the Union Cabinet on 10 January 1955 in New Delhi by Nehru. He started a weekly paper called ‘Shakti’. In 1957, he was awarded the Bharat Ratna."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-487",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "As per the coding convention of India Census, how many digit code is used for showing state code?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1",
            "B": "3",
            "C": "2",
            "D": "4"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "2",
        "explanation": "2. The coding convention used: State code (2 digits); District code (3 digits); Sub-district code (5 digits); Village code (6 digits)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-488",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On which day was the National Emblem of India adopted ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "15th August 1952",
            "B": "26th January 1950",
            "C": "15th August 1947",
            "D": "26th January 1959"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "26th January 1950",
        "explanation": "26th January 1950. The state emblem is an adaptation from the Sarnath Lion Capital of Ashoka. Motto- Satyameva Jayate (\"Truth Alone Triumphs\") is taken from the \"Mundaka Upanishad\", a part of Upanishads."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-489",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education Act 2009 is an Act of Parliament which came into force in:",
        "options": {
            "A": "2012",
            "B": "2011",
            "C": "2009",
            "D": "2010"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "2010",
        "explanation": "2010. The Act makes education a fundamental right of every child between the ages of 6 and 14 and specifies minimum norms in elementary schools."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-490",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In which of the following years was an Act enacted to provide for the reorganisation of the states of India and for matters connected therewith?",
        "options": {
            "A": "1947",
            "B": "1956",
            "C": "1959",
            "D": "1962"
        },
        "correct_option": "B",
        "answer": "1956",
        "explanation": "1956. The States Reorganisation Act, 1956 was a major reform of the boundaries of India's states and territories, organising them along linguistic lines. The Government divided the country into 14 states and 6 union territories under the State Reorganisation Act."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-491",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Acts was passed by the Government of India to inquire into allegations of corruption against certain public functionaries?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Delimitation Act",
            "B": "Prevention of Money Laundering Act",
            "C": "Central Vigilance Commission Act",
            "D": "The Lokpal and Lokayukta Act"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "The Lokpal and Lokayukta Act",
        "explanation": "The Lokpal and Lokayukta Act was passed by the Government of India to inquire into allegations of corruption against certain public functionaries."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-492",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian Forest Act 1927 was enacted after repealing which of the following Indian forest acts?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Indian Forest Act, 1882",
            "B": "Indian Forest Act, 1922",
            "C": "Indian Forest Act, 1865",
            "D": "Indian Forest Act, 1878"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "Indian Forest Act, 1878",
        "explanation": "Indian Forest Act, 1878. The Indian Forest Act of 1878 divided Indian forests into reserved forests (completely government-controlled), protected forests (partially government-controlled) and village forests (controlled by abutting villages)."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-493",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "One-third of the members of the Vidhan Parishad retire every ______ years.",
        "options": {
            "A": "four",
            "B": "one",
            "C": "three",
            "D": "two"
        },
        "correct_option": "D",
        "answer": "two",
        "explanation": "two years. Vidhan Parishad or Legislative Council is a permanent body, which can be formed or abolished when the Legislative Assembly passes a special resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-494",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which was the first part of India to hold an election based on universal adult franchise ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Assam",
            "B": "Tripura",
            "C": "Manipur",
            "D": "Bihar"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Manipur",
        "explanation": "Manipur (June 1948). Maharaja of Manipur Bodhchandra Singh signed the instrument of accession with the Indian government on the assurance that the internal autonomy of Manipur would be maintained"
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-495",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "On the night of ______ 1975, Indira Gandhi recommended the imposition of Emergency to president Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed.",
        "options": {
            "A": "1st June",
            "B": "22nd May",
            "C": "25th June",
            "D": "1st July"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "25th June",
        "explanation": "25th June. The third emergency of India started at the mid night of 25th June 1975 and was extended till 23 March 1977. The main reason for this emergency was “internal disturbances”. First emergency of India was started on 26 October 1962 (India-China war). The second emergency was during the India-Pakistan war from 3-17 December 1971."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-496",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is the expanded form of the abbreviation 'Rep.' used in the text of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Repealed",
            "B": "Republic",
            "C": "Report",
            "D": "Representative"
        },
        "correct_option": "A",
        "answer": "Repealed",
        "explanation": "Repealed. The meaning of Repeal is to rescind or annul by authoritative act; especially : to revoke or abrogate by legislative enactment."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-497",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "______ is a set of norms and guidelines to be followed by the political parties and contesting candidates during election time.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Constitutional Norms",
            "B": "Constitutional Rules",
            "C": "Code of Conduct",
            "D": "Rigging"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Code of Conduct",
        "explanation": "Code of Conduct is a set of rules outlining the norms, rules, and responsibilities or proper practices of an individual party or an organisation."
    },
    {
        "id": "POLITY-498",
        "chapter": "GK/GS",
        "type": "Polity",
        "question": "In 1977, who became then President of the Janata Party, which formed a coalition government at the centre with Morarji Desai as the Prime Minister?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Charan Singh",
            "B": "George Fernandes",
            "C": "Chandra Shekhar",
            "D": "Madhu Dandavate"
        },
        "correct_option": "C",
        "answer": "Chandra Shekhar",
        "explanation": "Chandra Shekhar. He was President of the Janata Party from 1977 to 1988. Chandra Shekhar was sworn in as the ninth Prime Minister of India on November 10, 1991 and remained in office until June 21, 1991, for a period spanning 223 days. www.ssccglpinnacle.com Download Pinnacle Exam Preparation App Search on TG: @apna_pdf"
    }
]